<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches and ministery of England, true churches and true ministery. Cleared, and proved, in a sermon / preach'd the 4th of May at Wiviliscombe; before a numerous congregation assembled together to hear the opposition, which had been long threatned to be made that day, by Mr Collier and others of his party, who, with the greatest strength the West would afford them, were present at the sermon. Wherein were these five things undeniably proved: 1. That a mixture of prophane and scandalous persons with reall saints, is not inconsistent with the Church of God or a true church. ... 5. And then, they also must needs be guilty, who forsake true churches and a lawfull ministry, to follow and hear unsent preachers. By Francis Fullwood minister of the Gospel at Staple Fitzpane in the county of Somerset. Before it there is an epistle and preface, shewing the manner, and a narrative subjoyned shewing the substance of the dispute after the sermon, (both which lasted nine hours.) Set forth by the ministers that were at the dispute, and attested under their hands.</title>
            <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E671_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862560</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862560</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E671[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches and ministery of England, true churches and true ministery. Cleared, and proved, in a sermon / preach'd the 4th of May at Wiviliscombe; before a numerous congregation assembled together to hear the opposition, which had been long threatned to be made that day, by Mr Collier and others of his party, who, with the greatest strength the West would afford them, were present at the sermon. Wherein were these five things undeniably proved: 1. That a mixture of prophane and scandalous persons with reall saints, is not inconsistent with the Church of God or a true church. ... 5. And then, they also must needs be guilty, who forsake true churches and a lawfull ministry, to follow and hear unsent preachers. By Francis Fullwood minister of the Gospel at Staple Fitzpane in the county of Somerset. Before it there is an epistle and preface, shewing the manner, and a narrative subjoyned shewing the substance of the dispute after the sermon, (both which lasted nine hours.) Set forth by the ministers that were at the dispute, and attested under their hands.</title>
                  <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
                  <author>Darby, Charls.</author>
                  <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for George Treagle at Taunton, and are to be sold at London by William Roybould at the Unicorn in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: Charls Darby.</note>
                  <note>The word "subjoyned" is enclosed in square brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>"A brief narration of the heads of that long (yet happy) discourse, betwixt M. Fullwood (assisted sometimes with M. Wood, M. Howe, &amp;c.) and M. Collier ..", p. 57-end.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHURCHES and MINISTERY of ENGLAND, True Churches and true Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>Cleared, and proved, In a SERMON preach'd the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> at <hi>Wiviliſcombe;</hi> before a numerous Congregation aſſembled together to hear the oppoſition, which had been long threatned to be made that day, by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Collier</hi> and others of his party, who, with the greateſt ſtrength the Weſt would afford them, were preſent at the Sermon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein were theſe Five things undeniably proved:</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That a mixture of prophane and ſcandalous perſons with reall Saints, is not inconſiſtent with the Church of God, or a true Church.</item>
               <item>2. That then the Churches that are now in <hi>England,</hi> are Churches of God, and true Churches.</item>
               <item>3. That then, the Miniſtry of thoſe Churches, is the Miniſtry of God, and the true Miniſtry.</item>
               <item>4. That then, there is a great and heavy ſin lying at the door of all ſuch, as do preſume to preach publikely among us, without a Call, who have true Churches, and a ſetled Miniſtry.</item>
               <item>5. And then, they alſo muſt needs be guilty, who forſake true Churches and a lawfull Miniſtry, to follow and hear unſent preachers.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By FRANCIS FULLWOOD Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Staple Fitzpane</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Before it there is an Epiſtle and Preface, ſhewing the</hi> Manner, <hi>and a</hi> Narrative <hi>[ſubjoyned] ſhewing the</hi> Subſtance <hi>of the</hi> Diſpute <hi>after the Sermon, (both which laſted nine hours.) Set forth by the</hi> Miniſters <hi>that were at the</hi> Diſpute, <hi>and Atteſted under their Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>George Treagle</hi> at <hi>Taunton,</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>William Roybould</hi> at the Unicorn in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS Honoured Friend, Collonel <hi>JOHN PINE,</hi> A Member of Parliament, and one of the Commiſſioners for the <hi>Militia</hi> of the County of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruth, though above this ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years of age, and hath learned long ſince to <hi>stand</hi> alone; yet experience hath found, it doth ever <hi>goe</hi> the better into the world, when imboldened with the care and gracious protection of a nurſing Father: and I need not <hi>dawb with untempered mortar</hi> to tell the world (what the whole Weſt of <hi>England</hi> well nigh knows) that the <hi>potent influence,</hi> and <hi>pleaſant ſhade</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:114723:3"/> ſo noble a <hi>Tree,</hi> will better <hi>protect</hi> and ſecure <hi>thoſe truths</hi> againſt all the <hi>heat</hi> of preſent oppoſition, then theſe poor contemptible following <hi>Leaves</hi> can do.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Bleſsed be the God of Truth,</hi> that hath inclined your heart to own his truth, and (more particularly) to embrace an opportunity, wherein you may do his ſhaken Churches throughout the world ſo great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; a bold expreſſion, I muſt needs confeſſe, yet, Worthily Honoured Sir, give me leave to be bold, and I ſhall adde, That there is nothing more certain then this, that theſe mens principles we ſpeak againſt, would at once ſtrike down (I ſay, not the credit, but) being and truth of all the Churches, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and Ordinances of Chriſt, that are either <hi>now,</hi> or ever have been in the world ſince the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times;</hi> and (who is not <hi>affrighted!</hi>) from <hi>horrid</hi> principles?</p>
            <p>But ſince the <hi>deſigne</hi> lies ſo deep, I beſeech you Noble Sir, to conſider a little who they are that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it; and with what <hi>Engine</hi> they think to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Who, and what are the men of ſo great an adventure? Methinks <hi>Fame</hi> ſhould carry them to be mightily skil'd in the <hi>Originall tongus,</hi> or deeply read in the <hi>Hiſtory of the Church,</hi> whereby they had <hi>diſcovered</hi> ſomething there, that was never <hi>found</hi> out before: or ſome <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Angels,</hi> or <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſent down from heaven to open ſome truths, that had been lockt up, and kept ſecret from the Church for ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years: but alas! they pretend not to be any ſuch: but what are they? even <hi>men of like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:3"/> 
               <hi>with us,</hi> and in a word no betterthen the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle deſcribes <hi>unlearned, unſtable,</hi> wreſting the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>But ſurely they have ſome weighty Arguments, though the men be weak, they would never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſo great a deſign, as to overthrow all <hi>Churches, Miniſters, Ordinances,</hi> and that ever ſince the Apoſtles times, unleſſe their Engine were ſomewhat anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: O yes, they have allowed <hi>Infant-baptiſm; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> that <hi>baptize infants</hi> are <hi>Anti-christian: Members</hi> that were baptized Infants are <hi>Anti-chriſtian:</hi> and conſequently <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> are all <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:</hi> Ah poor ſhift! and yet you have nothing elſe will hold an Argument but this: Let me now in the <hi>Name of God,</hi> and <hi>all the Churches,</hi> entreat theſe men to conſider a few things, or anſwer a few brief queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons touching Infant-baptiſm; and then they will ſee how <hi>deſperate</hi> and unadviſed they have been in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great moment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Suppoſe we ſhould grant the baptizing of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants an Errour: May not the true Church erre? may not the whole Church erre? may it not erre in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and then, what doth hinder but it may erre in <hi>practice</hi> too, and yet be ſtill a <hi>true Church?</hi> to affirm the contrary is rank Popery.</p>
            <p>Again, If the Church may erre, it may erre in <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance,</hi> without diſpute; and what is the errour of Infant-baptiſm (if it be an errour) more then a <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiall errour?</hi> for have we not ever kept the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of it? the matter <hi>water,</hi> and the form, <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt?</hi> how then I pray you can the errour of <hi>Infant-baptiſm</hi> deſtroy our
<pb facs="tcp:114723:4"/> 
               <hi>Churches,</hi> or nullifie our <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But alas! who told you that Infant-baptiſm was an errour, before the Anabaptiſts of <hi>Germany</hi> did? who told you when this errour <hi>came firſt into the Church?</hi> What <hi>Precept or Precedent</hi> have you againſt it in all the Scripture? or what <hi>command</hi> have you to ſhew for the baptizing <hi>beleevers only?</hi> alas poor men! who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you dare anſwer to any one of theſe queſtions? and how then wilt thou be able to anſwer them all? and much leſſe can you warrant the deſperate conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions you have built upon ſo weak, ſo tottering a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>But why do I trouble theſe poor men? alas! they are but the weapons and Organs of Jeſuites, who play their <hi>game</hi> under theſe mens <hi>cloaks:</hi> Methinks I ſee them inſtilling their damnable doctrines into theſe mens <hi>ears,</hi> and venting them again at their <hi>mouths:</hi> how naturally do all the abominable errours of theſe our times (if you follow them a little) kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaluting each other, and joyning in one ſtream) tend and flow to the Sea of <hi>Rome!</hi> the <hi>Seminaries</hi> are <hi>ſowing</hi> their <hi>Tares</hi> among us, which indeed <hi>ſpring</hi> too faſt all the Land over; and if they be not <hi>rooted</hi> up and ſtopt in time, the <hi>Pope</hi> it's to be feared will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>reap</hi> too large a harveſt among us in <hi>England,</hi> which <hi>Canterbury</hi> I remember warned us off (who know more of their plots and methods (perhaps) then he ſhould, or we do) in <hi>his ſpeech upon the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</hi> Honoured Sir, give me leave I beſeech you to point a little at the Jeſuites drift, as I conceive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:4"/>
            <p> His <hi>generall</hi> laſt <hi>end</hi> is to advance the <hi>Pope</hi> and bring in <hi>Popery,</hi> which hath been hatching many years. The <hi>means</hi> he makes uſe of for this great end, is to bring in a <hi>generall Toleration,</hi> and to <hi>put down the Miniſters;</hi> in a generall Toleration (there being no hedge of Diſcipline to keep him out) he hopes to crowd in with the reſt, and then truſts to his <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> to do well enough; eſpecially can he but get his greateſt enemy, <hi>the able Miniſtry,</hi> down: Which he attempts, by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it <hi>odious</hi> to the <hi>people</hi> becauſe of <hi>maintenance;</hi> and to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> by making them, what in them lies, to be <hi>enemies to the State:</hi> But doth not the <hi>Parliament</hi> very well know, that <hi>every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the Land can produce <hi>divers Miniſters</hi> that have been true to their Cauſe, ever ſince <hi>they firſt ſate,</hi> to this very day? but I need not blaze the friendſhip of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> or indeed of <hi>our adverſaries</hi> more immediate, to <hi>civill Authority,</hi> both in <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and practice:</hi> and in this I am ſure they agree, <hi>that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath nothing to do with matter of Religion;</hi> which caſts a greater blur up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Parliamentary proceedings of that nature, for theſe many years paſt, then the worſt of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (I think I may ſay) that the Miniſtry hath done.</p>
            <p>Honoured S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, I am too bold and tedious: take this I beſeech you as a <hi>pawn</hi> and pledg, of that <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>gratitude</hi> I owe to you: and the Lord inſpire you with the ſpirit of diſcerning, to ſearch into theſe things, more and more: diſcouraging error, and owning <hi>his</hi> truth, who hath ſaid, <hi>thoſe that honour me I will honour:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:5"/> to whoſe grace and glory I am bold to commend both you and yours, and ſubſcribe my ſelf, as indeed I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your very much obliged and moſt humble ſervant <hi>FRAN: FULLWOOD.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:5"/>
            <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſuch a one I ſuppoſe my ſelf ſpeaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; one, who knoweſt thy ſelf concerned in all the affairs of Chriſtianity: and upon that ground art the <hi>Lords Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> at the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> not only for thy ſelf, but for all others alſo, who are <hi>partakers of like precious faith</hi> with thee; and hast powred out many a prayer and tear for the <hi>peace and proſperity of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Thou art, it may be, lately come out of thy cloſet, where thou hadſt ſweet communion with <hi>him whom thy ſoul loveth:</hi> and thou ſawest ſo much of his <hi>comelineſſe</hi> and <hi>beauty,</hi> that thy heart was taken therewith more then ever: and then thou hadst many ſuch holy breathings as theſe; <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee,</hi> &amp;c? I will ſuppoſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 25.</note> this to have been thy last exerciſe (as it is ſometimes if thou art a Chriſtian <hi> indeed.</hi>) Let me intreat thee then to retire to thy cloſet again, and after thy former raptures and extaſies, let it not ſeem unſeaſonable, to reflect a little with ſad thoughts and weeping eyes upon the great diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the Church the ſpouſe of Christ. Spirituall joy doth not uſe to ſtreighten the heart, but enlarge it, and make it the fitter and freer to mourn; nor doth it dry up the eyes, but rather open the fountain of tears. Beleeve me this would be a ſeaſonable exerciſe, nay it is the <hi>mark</hi> of a Saint: The gracious ſoul, as he grieves more, for that he hath ſinned
<pb facs="tcp:114723:6"/> against his God, than for any Croſſe, which reacheth his perſon or estate: ſo alſo he is much more troubled for the ſchiſmes and hereſies, wherewith the Church of God is rent and torn, than for his own private afflications. If thou haſt a <hi>publike</hi> ſpirit, and eſteemeſt the <hi>honour</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>promoting</hi> of Religion far more dear unto thee then thine own <hi>intereſt, credit or preferment;</hi> Tell me, Would it not be lamented, if poſsible, with tears of bloud, that the <hi>good Spirit of God</hi> ſhould be <hi>grieved</hi> by reaſon of that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 30, 31. Ut excontextu patet.</note> 
               <hi>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terneſſe,</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> and <hi>anger,</hi> which are ſecretly fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and too often break out into <hi>clamours</hi> and <hi>evil ſpeakings</hi> of Chriſtians one againſt another? Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth it unto thee a <hi>ſmall</hi> matter, that the <hi>joy</hi> in the heart of Chriſt Jeſus now in Heaven ſhould be <hi>diminiſhed,</hi> by reaſon of the decay of <hi>love</hi> in thoſe who are his members? Certainly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh</hi> 15. 10, 11, 12. Quondam eſt illud gaudium Chriſti in nobis, niſi quòd ille di natur gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere de nobis? <hi>Aug.</hi> in loc.</note> when Chriſtians are <hi>fruitfull in their lives,</hi> and <hi>abound in love</hi> one towards another, Chriſt <hi>rejoyceth</hi> over them even in Heaven. And I ſee no reaſon, why the contrary may not be implied, <hi>viz.</hi> That when the love of the bretheren ſhall grow <hi>cold</hi> one towards another (as wofull experience ſufficiently ſheweth, that difference of <hi>opinion</hi> doth, if not make a <hi>breach,</hi> yet ſecretly withdraw <hi>affection</hi>) the <hi>joy</hi> in Chriſts heart over them is leſsened; which how great an evilit is, I leave to them to judge, who <hi>love the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in ſincerity.</hi> Again, Is it nothing to thee, that the <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> of the Lord <hi>cut</hi> one another? That the ſervants of Chriſt ſhould, as it were, ſet the Spirit againſt it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploying thoſe precious gifts, which they received from him for mutuall help and furtherance, in <hi>bitter</hi> invectives, <hi>unſavoury</hi> diſcoveries of each others infirmities, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and endleſse <hi>logomachies;</hi> ſo that inſtead of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,</hi> they <hi>widen</hi> the breach; and inſtead of <hi>terminating,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:6"/> rather <hi>perpetuate</hi> ſtrife and contention? Canſt thou with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſigh remember, how by this means our <hi>Religion ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers</hi> in its reputation abroad, our <hi>profeſſion</hi> is ſcandalized, our hopeful <hi>Reformation</hi> flouted; as if the holy endeavours of our <hi>Reverend Aſſembly</hi> had all this while produced a ſolemne Nothing; or (which is worſe) had <hi>midwived</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>birth,</hi> of that monstrous <hi>brood</hi> of errors, which now <hi>ſwarm</hi> and <hi>roar</hi> among us? Doth not thy heart <hi>bleed</hi> to conſider how the common enemy <hi>danceth</hi> at our <hi>diſcord,</hi> which makes a pleaſing <hi>harmony</hi> to them? how the Jeſuites triumph in our diviſions, feeding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with aſſured hopes of prevailing againſt us, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their old principle, <hi>Divide &amp; impera?</hi> How much <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Kingdom of Satan is hereby promoted? How many ſouls he hath <hi>drunk up?</hi> how the power of godlineſs is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>laid aſide,</hi> and <hi>working</hi> out our ſalvation turned into <hi>talking, praying</hi> into <hi>diſputing,</hi> and <hi>preaching</hi> into <hi>railing?</hi> How much <hi>dirt</hi> hath been cast into the <hi>face</hi> of the moſt glorious Miniſtry that ever (next to the Apoſtles) the Church of Chriſt enjoyed? And how ſome of them, who at leaſt pretended to the Ministry, have cowardly ſhrunk from their ſtation, nay <hi>traiterouſly</hi> run to the enemy, and (as it is ſaid of the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> that they are the <hi>worſe</hi> enemies to Chriſtianity, for having been <hi>once</hi> Chriſtians, ſo) theſe are the moſt <hi>eager</hi> and <hi>violent ſticklers</hi> againſt the Miniſtery. Reader, here are conſiderations, which if thou hast a tender and gracious ſpirit, may well make thee cry out, <hi>My bowels!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider further, how few <hi>faithfull labourers</hi> there are in the <hi>Lords harveſt:</hi> How many deceivers and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postors are newly ſtarted up? What hideous blaſphemies are now vented? What a multitude of errours and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb facs="tcp:114723:7"/> are now broached, which are obtruded upon the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced people under the ſpecious name of <hi>New-lights,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth they are but <hi>Old darkneſſe:</hi> There is ſcarce an errour, that ever had inventor or fautour amongst that great number which Antiquity hath left upon record, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the black note of <hi>heretiques,</hi> but now it is pluckt out of the <hi>dunghill,</hi> and ſent abroad it may be with a new <hi>dreſſe</hi> put upon it to make it paſſe. So that in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect we may truly ſay, that this our age is the very <hi>draught,</hi> into which all the <hi>ſtinking</hi> opinions which ever have paſſed thorow the <hi>exulcerated bowels</hi> of all the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques of ſo many by-paſt ages, are caſt and deſcended. For the more ſpeedy <hi>diſſeminating</hi> of which errours (grief to behold!) the devil hath the preſſe at command. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall books are printed by thouſands, and diſperſed into all parts of the Land. Nor are they contented to <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>deviſe</hi> new of their own, but they alſo <hi>tranſlate</hi> out of other languages. Not to ſpeak of others, I have ſeen <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He that is minded to ſee ſome of his Divinity, may pleaſe to reade</hi> Wendeline <hi>in his Epiſtle Dedicatory his</hi> Theologia Chriſtiana. <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. 30.</note> the works of <hi>Wrigelius</hi> printed in Engliſh. A more blaſphemous heretique the earth never bare. Thus they will traffique with any body, yea, with <hi>hell</hi> it ſelf, ſo they may have variety of <hi>baits</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> to deceive the more, I hope I need not uſe motives to thee (Chriſtian Reader) to bewail before the Lord the <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>blaſphemies</hi> of this Age; nor ſet any <hi>ſpur</hi> to thy ſide, to ſtir thee to that to which thou haſtest already: Thou art by this time in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> caſe, <hi>who ſought where to weep.</hi> So thou, to <hi>pour out</hi> thy heart as <hi>water,</hi> before the Lord. Yea, thou takeſt up a reſolution to be the Lords <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> and never to <hi>ſtand before</hi> him with any petition, but this ſhall be the <hi>chiefeſt,</hi> That God would <hi>chain</hi> up <hi>Satan,</hi> that he <hi>deceive</hi> no more; That he would powerfully <hi>rebuke</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:114723:7"/> ſpirit of <hi>errour,</hi> that it diffuſe it ſelf no further; Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily <hi>diſcover,</hi> and <hi>ſpread dung upon the faces</hi> of all <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers;</hi> give unto this people a <hi>ſpirit of diſcerning,</hi> that they <hi>may try them which ſay, they are Apoſtles, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ere not, and finde them lyars;</hi> Put it into the hearts of our <hi>learned, wiſe,</hi> and <hi>pious Governours</hi> to reſtrain the licentiouſneſse of theſe Seducers, and put a ſtop to the <hi>growth</hi> of hereſies; <hi>Encourage</hi> his ſervants the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and give them a <hi>mouth and wiſedom,</hi> that they may <hi>mightily convince</hi> and <hi>muzzle</hi> gainſayers, <hi>reclaim</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 16.</note> every ſeduced brother, <hi>ſettle</hi> every ſtaggering ſpirit, and <hi>confirm</hi> every one that loves the truth in the <hi>good old way,</hi> in which alone <hi>reſt</hi> is to be found to a <hi>weary ſoul.</hi> And certainly never was there more need of <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>tears</hi> then now; never did greater exigency call upon us to <hi>wreſtle</hi> with God by the <hi>omnipotency</hi> of prayer. I am <note place="margin">Eſt quaedam precum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potenia. <hi>Luth.</hi>
               </note> perſwaded this mercy <hi>is come to the birth:</hi> it wants but an <hi>Eſay,</hi> who with his <hi>effectuall fervent prayers</hi> might be in stead of a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 3.</note> 
               <hi>man-midwife to bring it forth.</hi> And oh that God would put into the hearts of all, eſpecially Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, a a reſtleſſe importunity; ſuch a <hi>ſpirit of prayer</hi> as would be turned off with no deniall! There have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſires breathed heaven-ward, many prayers and tears already <hi>treaſured</hi> up for this very thing by the <hi>Samuels</hi> and <hi>Eſays</hi> of theſe and former times: But this mercy is ſo great, that it calls for yet more prayers, yet more tears, more ſtruglings and wrestlings to fetch it down. Oh then when God is willing to give, and to this purpoſe hath the <hi>mercy already in his hand,</hi> let not us be backward in asking?</p>
            <p>For mine own part it's true, I have not ſo much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came me, laid to heart theſe ſad diſtractions in the Church;
<pb facs="tcp:114723:8"/> nor multiplied petitions, tears and groans at the Throne of grace, ſo much as one of my place ſhould have done; yet I have had ſome ſad and ſerious thoughts about them. As who is there, whoſe care and deſigns are not terminated wholly in himſelf, who hath not with good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> been <hi>ſad</hi> both in <hi>countenance</hi> and <hi>heart,</hi> to conſider, what a glorious <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> of truth was <hi>breaking</hi> out upon us, which now is <hi>clouded</hi> with fogs of errours: To remember what a comfortable <hi>day</hi> of reformation <hi>dawned</hi> upon us, which now is <hi>cloſed</hi> up again: (Surely we are not worthy of it, we are not fitted for it, nay, the moſt diſtast it) To think how many <hi>Wolves</hi> are <hi>crept in</hi> among us in <hi>ſheep-cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> which worry the <hi>flock:</hi> what a generall defection there is from <hi>obedience to the truth,</hi> even of thoſe who ran with the foremost heretofore, and eſteemed, at leaſt in ſhew, <hi>the feet of them very beautiful that preached the Goſpell,</hi> the good and glad tidings of peace: what a phrentique wantonneſse hath poſſeſſed thouſands, who of looſe ignorants became Sceptiques, Sciſmaticks, Atheists? But that which may more trouble us, is, to obſerve how many ſouls who had received ſlight common illumination, whoſe hearts were become ſomewhat pliable and tender, like wax, fit to receive any impreſſion, theſe the devil, (<hi>who</hi> as one ſaid, <hi>is a good Biſhop in his Dioceſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Latimer.</note> 
               <hi>carefull of looſing, watchfull to win ſouls</hi>) ſtrikes in with, and before any right <hi>ſeeds</hi> of ſaving knowledge were cast in, ſows <hi>tares</hi> in the <hi>ground</hi> of their hearts, which indeed was rather <hi>ſcratched</hi> with the <hi>harrowing</hi> thoughts of death, hell and judgement, then <hi>broken</hi> up with the <hi>plough</hi> of ſound contrition? And which was yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grief, ſome, who dated themſelves <hi>Profeſſors</hi> ſome years before, <hi>Old Diſciples,</hi> were <hi>carried away with the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:8"/> 
               <hi>errour of the wicked, and fell from their ſtedfaſtneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet in the midſt of ſo many ſad thoughts, which every of theſe occurrents did multiply in me, I was not without ſome comfortable conſiderations, which did both raiſe and confirm my dejected and ſometimes (I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to confeſs my weakneſſe) <hi>ſtaggering</hi> ſoul. To omit many, the chief were,</p>
            <p>1. In that <hi>Satan</hi> raved and bestirr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf ſo much. it was a ſign that his Kingdom began to totter. When his <hi>time</hi> is but <hi>ſhort,</hi> he <hi>roars</hi> to purpoſe. When he ſaw ſuch <hi>light</hi> breaking forth, maugre all his malice, and devices to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uppreſs it, which would ſurely <hi>diſpell</hi> the <hi>darkneſſe</hi> wherein he beares ſway, then he falls to his old ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft: if he cannot wholly extinguiſh it, he will dim it. Hereupon he <hi>opens the bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omleſſe pit,</hi> whereout comes <hi>ſmoak of errours, darkening the Sun of truth,</hi> and <hi>wholſome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 9. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ayr of found doctrine.</hi> Thus he did in <hi>Germany,</hi> when <hi>Luther</hi> had (I do not ſay <hi>lighted, but</hi>) brought the <hi>candle</hi> of truth out of the <hi>dark lanthorn,</hi> and <hi>ſet it on a candleſtick:</hi> how did Satan ſtrain his lungs to <hi>blow</hi> it out? When he failed of that, what endeavours did he uſe to cast a <hi>miſt</hi> about it? Then alſo, and not till then, ſwarmed thoſe <hi>Anabaptiſticall locuſts</hi> which did ſo much miſchief. So here, when Popery was not only <hi>lopt,</hi> but even taken away <hi>branch and root,</hi> and religion ceaſed to be in ſhew only, and began to <hi>flouriſh</hi> in the power thereof, how hath Satan laboured to <hi>blaſt</hi> the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſome of it with helliſh <hi>fum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and to eat away the very leaf thereof with infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>locuſts?</hi> Hence my ſoul hath ſtrongly concluded, That as when the Sun in its riſing is darkened with miſts, it port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds the faireſt day: So, the Sun of the Goſpel preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his extraordinary bright riſing in our <hi>Horizon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:9"/> being clouded, puts us in an aſsured hope, that after he miſts are once diſpelled, it will break forth with a more <hi>dazeling</hi> luſtre, <hi>ſhining more and more unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing which refreſhed me was a clear diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of much good already <hi>wrought</hi> and <hi>working</hi> by theſe unlikely means of diviſions. How many <hi>ſparks</hi> of truth have been beaten out by the colliſion even of <hi>flints?</hi> How much precious <hi>flowre</hi> of wholſome doctrine hath been clean <hi>purged</hi> from its bran by the ſomewhat violent <hi>ſhaking</hi> thereof in the <hi>ſcarce</hi> of diſputations? It was obſerved as one good effect of the claſhings of ancient times, in that thereby the ſpirits of ſome <hi>Worthies</hi> then living, were ſtirred up more fully to clear the truth. The quarelling of the <hi>Anti-trinitarians</hi> quickned holy <hi>Auguſtines</hi> learned diligence, and produced his Book <hi>de Trinitate.</hi> And there hath not wanted an <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in our times, who <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Channell.</note> upon the ſame grounds hath done the like, whoſe <hi>name</hi> is hereby made <hi>precious,</hi> and will doubtleſse be ever menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned with honour in the Churches. Above all that moſt vexed queſtion of <hi>Infant baptiſm,</hi> upon what weak grounds hath it hitherto ſtood: In oppoſing whereof <hi>Satan</hi> and his Inſtruments have been moſt forward and cunning; and have concluded their objections irrefragable. But how fully and unanſwerably hath that truth been aſserted (as by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo chiefly) by learned <hi>Baxter?</hi> That God, who <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded light to ſhine out of darkneſſe,</hi> doth often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the beſt effects out of the worſt cauſes. Adde to this, that hereby many <hi>hypocrites,</hi> unſound hollow-hearted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsors, have been clearly diſcovered, even by their falling off to errour. And thoſe who are <hi>faithfull</hi> unto the Lord, are made <hi>manifeſt.</hi> Reade and compare 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:9"/>
            <p> It is notoriouſly known to all that are not <hi>ſtrangers in our Engliſh Iſrael,</hi> how far the <hi>gangrene</hi> of errour hath prevailed and ſpread among us theſe ſeven years laſt past. I meddle not with what I have heard or read of in other <hi>Counties,</hi> (as doubtleſs all have had their ſhare, the diſeaſe being <hi>Epidemicall</hi>) theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> parts ſeem to have not the least <hi>infection.</hi> We confeſs to our grief, the ſeducers have had more advantages over us, then poſsibly they could have otherwhere. They found generally an ignorant and credulous people, and therefore apt to be deceived: and the rather, becauſe many flocks are without a <hi>ſhepheard;</hi> or have <hi>a dumb dog, that cannot bark;</hi> or a <hi>blind watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> that cannot ſee; or an <hi>hireling, that fleeth, when the wolf cometh.</hi> Hence they have ſeduced hundreds, unſetled thouſands, distracted and grieved all. Their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent audaciouſneſs is ſuch, that they have interrupted and diſturbed many Miniſters in their publike exerciſe: and it is ordinary to come with a gang of ſouldiers, and <hi>prate</hi> on a tomb-ſtone, while the Minister <hi>preacheth</hi> in a pulpit. Nay they are grown to that height of confidence, as to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge learned Miniſters to publike diſputes; but with what ſucceſs, I preſume good Reader, thou art able to ſay, though I were ſilent.</p>
            <p>Such a relation I am now to give thee of a diſpute, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Here are the ſigns and marks of an Apoſtle.</hi>
               </note> jangling, had at <hi>Wiviliſcombe</hi> in the <hi>County of Somerſet, May 4. 1652.</hi> between three or four young <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed</hi> Miniſters, and the whole ſtrength of the adverſary. I was an eye and ear witneſs of all, or the moſt, that paſſed: and becauſe I was preſent there, yet none of the number of the Lecturers, they deſired me to write, what I have, to give thee ſome light in the following Sermon and Narrative. I remember what <hi>Thales</hi> anſwered to one demanding,
<pb facs="tcp:114723:10"/> 
               <hi>How far Truth was diſtant from a lye; As much</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>as the eyes from the ears:</hi> Meaning that the eye was a <hi>faithfull</hi> ſpectatour, and <hi>authentique</hi> witneſs of things; but the ear was open to <hi>lies,</hi> and by it fictions and untruths had their entrance into the mind: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould credit their relations, whoſe <hi>ſeeing</hi> eyes had obſerved all paſſages; but worthily ſuſpect them, who were only able to give a <hi>blinde</hi> teſtimony. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I challenge belief from all ingenious Readers. I am not ignorant of the lying practiſes of <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who cry <hi>Victoria</hi> among their injudicious <hi>proſelytes,</hi> and it may be have prepoſſeſſed thee with ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true relation: and therefore my Diſcourſe ſhall bring thee into the place, and (with the help of the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Narrative) preſent to thy view the chief paſſages <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I muſt tell the occaſion thereof. Thou must know, <note place="margin">1. <hi>Occaſion.</hi>
               </note> good Reader, that there is a weekly Lecture at <hi>Wiviliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe</hi> aforeſaid: The Lecturers there unwilling that their meeting at the <hi>ordinary</hi> ſhould be without fruit, agreed among themſelves, that at ſet times they would, for their own better ſatisfaction, diſcuſse ſome of the moſt [at this day] vexed queſtions in Divinity. And becauſe hereſies grew apace, and many of thoſe parts fell away daily, they thought it meet to acquaint their hearers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that all that would, might reſort to the place, and hear them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Queſtion, propounded ſome weeks before, that the defendant might have ſome time to prepare himſelf, was, <hi>An juſtificatio ſit uno actu, ſimul &amp; ſemel?</hi> Whether a beleever be <hi>actually</hi> justified from <hi>all</hi> his ſins, <hi>paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> and <hi>to come, at once,</hi> namely, upon the firſt act of
<pb facs="tcp:114723:10"/> faith, which he puts forth. This M <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fullwood,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the enſuing Sermon, held in the <hi>Negative:</hi> the reſt oppoſed. In the cloſe they all profeſſed their unanimous conſent to what had been made appear to be truth. At the next meeting was the Queſtion about the lawfullneſs of <hi>Infant baptiſme</hi> to be diſcuſſed; which M <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wood,</hi> the Miniſter of the place, held in the Affirmative. Their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence was now much increaſed, even to a chamber-full. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he end the <hi>major</hi> part ſignified their being fully ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the lawfullneſs thereof. But all were not, or rather would not be ſatisfied. And here were the firſt <hi>ſparks</hi> out of which aroſe the <hi>after flame:</hi> the <hi>fewel</hi> whereof was the intemperate <hi>heat</hi> and ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcretion of ſome, who threatned to bring <hi>Collier</hi> to the next meeting, if he were within <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An infamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly famous Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctary.</hi>
               </note> many miles of the place; and the <hi>courage</hi> of others, who promiſed to defend that, or any other Point, againſt him. The third Queſtion (which M <hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">r</hi> Howe</hi> held in the Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative) was, <hi>Whether the now Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>be the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt Excluſively?</hi> This was to be stated and diſcuſſed <hi>May</hi> 4. It ſeems that <hi>this aſſertion</hi> had as much offended thoſe ſeduced and turbulent ſpirits, as that of <hi>Infant baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Hereupon ſwift notice was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to all or the most part of the <hi>Sectarians of the Weſt.</hi> In the mean time many threatn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting ſpeeches were given out by that party; as <hi>that no Presbyterian Miniſter durſt ſhew his head there,</hi> with much to that purpoſe. Nor was any thing more rife in every mans mouth, then the future diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e at <hi>Wivili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day being come, and a great Congregation aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, the diſcourſe, which hereafter is preſented, was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely
<pb facs="tcp:114723:11"/> delivered, yet as a Lecture-Sermon only: however thou maiſt eaſily perceive by the <hi>drift</hi> thereof, that the Preacher intended it as an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt Errour, and as a <hi>Muzzle</hi> for the mouthes of them that came to oppoſe. While he was praying before Sermon, <hi>Collier</hi> comes in, <hi>guarded</hi> as it were, with ſome ſouldiers, and a great company of his <hi>furious diſciples.</hi> It was much wondred, that he ſhould ſo <hi>patiently</hi> hear out ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing</hi> a Diſcourſe; but we have cauſe to think, that the ſtrength of reaſon there urged and delivered, did ſo <hi>daunt</hi> and <hi>confound</hi> him, that he durst not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt; his courage being much quailed, and his minde diſtracted through fear, leaſt he ſhould not in all that daies diſpute, raze out that deep impreſsion, which that Sermon had made in the hearers. After Sermon ended, he ſtood up and ſignified his not being ſatisfied with what was ſpoken; and here began the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute.</p>
            <p>2. Thou expecteſt an account, how it was <hi>carried on;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Manner.</hi>
               </note> but this as to the <hi>matter</hi> thereof is <hi>exactly</hi> and <hi>faithfully</hi> ſet down in the Narrative; thither therefore I ſhall remit thee: but ſome paſſages obſervable in the manner of it, I ſhall relate.</p>
            <p>1. Obſervable: was the <hi>cunning craftineſs</hi> of theſe deceivers, which as it was diſcernable to an obſervant eye thorowout the whole action, ſo it more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In the beginning:</hi> For as if their <hi>hearts</hi> had been of stone, and their <hi>browes</hi> of ſteel, they began the buſineſs with ſuch an <hi>impudent majeſty,</hi> as muſt needs ſtrike a kinde of <hi>horrour</hi> into fools; yea and strangely amuſe even honeſt men of the ſimpler ſort, who had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:114723:11"/> been acquainted with the impudent <hi>boldneſs</hi> of hereticks.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They would not ſuffer M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Howe</hi> to ſtate the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion intended to have been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcuſſed by the Miniſters: they feared belike, that he was too well provided for them: but with eager importunity required M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> to maintain what he had delivered. They hoped to have foyled him, who had been tyred with a two hours preaching, and came nothing prepared for the diſpute, which they intended. For</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Collier</hi> after ſome <hi>velita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions,</hi> like a crafty ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, drawes M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fullwood</hi> into the <hi>ambuſh</hi> of <hi>Infant-baptiſm,</hi> where they think themſelves <hi>invincible.</hi> But yet notwithstanding the diſadvantage of the question, and the confidence of the adverſary, they were <hi>charged</hi> ſo home, that they were <hi>beaten</hi> out of their place of <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>utterly routed,</hi> as the Narrative will ſhew.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They would ever and anon appeal to the people, eſpecially when their arguing was plauſible and ſpecious, or if there had been ſome <hi>verbal</hi> faultrings in any of the defendants. For they well know, that a <hi>Stentorean</hi> voice, and plauſible ſpeech, do much more prevail upon ignorant ſouls, then the ſtrongest reaſon or the most for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Argument. The Apostle hath given them this <hi>Character, Coloſ.</hi> 2. 4. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> (cited by <hi>Davenant</hi> upon the place) ſpeaks of hereticks; that <hi>Priùs perſuadent, quám edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: (veritas autem docendo ſuadet, non ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>docet.</hi>)It is the artifice of deceivers, firſt to perſwade, and afterward to inſtruct: but truth doth not ſo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:12"/>
            <p> 2. Obſervable: was <hi>Colliers notorious hypocriſie.</hi> When I had upon the deſire of the defendant given in my <hi>Greek Teſtament,</hi> that the Original might be ſearched about the true reading of a <hi>Scripture</hi> brought to prove the lawfullneſs of <hi>Poedobaptiſme,</hi> the defendant gave it into <hi>Colliers</hi> hand to read the place; who <hi>takes the book, and looking thereon, moves his lips, as if he had indeed read it.</hi> Is it not likely, good Reader, that he is skilled in the <hi>Greek,</hi> who inſtead of <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> wrote <hi>Primum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Collier <hi>in a Letter to M.</hi> Rob. Gorges <hi>of</hi> Oxford.</note> 
               <hi>obilum?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might fill much paper, and waſt much time in reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their <hi>non-ſenſe, abſurdities, poor and empty ſhifts and evaſions,</hi> to which they were driven; which were ſometimes ſo <hi>palpable,</hi> that the whole Aſſembly did more then once break forth into loud laughter. But I leave them to be conceived by the judicious Reader, who may, without fear of enlarging too much, gueſs at the reſt, by the enumeration of theſe few. But this I cannot omit, which I make</p>
            <p>3. Obſervable: That <hi>Collier</hi> in my apprehenſion <hi>(and I think that I have five ſenſes)</hi> was put to ſilence more then once. But then, when the matter in queſtion was driven to an head, and he over-powred with ſtrength of Argument, and ſo non-pluſt, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the laws of diſputation, he would begin again, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning back to his Argument. And here alſo his fellowes would he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p him at a <hi>dead-lift;</hi> when he knew not what to ſay, they would fill up that <hi>vacancy</hi> with clamours against one or other.</p>
            <p>4. Moſt obſervable was the good hand of God upon us, who there did cleerly own our Righteous cauſe: mightily <hi>ſupporting</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fullwood,</hi> ſo that though he
<pb facs="tcp:114723:12"/> had preached two hours, yet he held out ſeven hours diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation more, without moving from the place, <hi>powring contempt</hi> upon <hi>Collier</hi> and his adherents; oh how vile were they in the eyes of the moſt! much ado to refrain hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them out of the place; There was often breaking out into cachinnations, inſomuch that <hi>Collier</hi> himſelf ſeemed much to be daunted! <hi>giving</hi> the Miniſters favour in the eyes of the people, yea of their very adverſaries, ſo that (which I look upon as no inſignificant demonſtration of the goodneſs of our cauſe) <hi>Collier</hi> himſelf (what wreſted it from him I know not,) ſpake openly to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fullwoods</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. Report alſo ſaith, that the adverſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſince confeſſed, <hi>that they never met with ſuch oppoſition. Thanks be unto God, for his unſpeakable guift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. And what need I now ſpeak of the ſucceſs of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute? <note place="margin">3. <hi>Succeſſe.</hi>
               </note> The adverſaries themſelves know to their <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and we to our <hi>comfort,</hi> that then and there the <hi>Lyons skin was pluckt off from the Aſſe,</hi> which had made him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable before: And that, though there were their whole strength, yet, they received the greateſt foil that ever they did. And indeed what can any one conceive will be the ſucceſse of ſuch a conteſt, when the <hi>father of lies</hi> ſhall conteſt with the <hi>ſpirit of truth?</hi> When ignorance ſhall cope with learning, hypocriſie with piety, errour with truth? When an ignorant <hi>caviller</hi> ſhall diſpute with a prudent <hi>Logician?</hi> I confeſſe indeed their ſtrange cavils and ſophiſtry, made me not a little to marvell: ſo that I thought there had been a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or a tranſmigration of the ſouls of ſome <hi>Jeſuites</hi> into their bodies; or as if they had been principled by ſome Old <hi>Loyoliſt:</hi> Surely they never learned them at the Plough: But they were all ſo
<pb facs="tcp:114723:13"/> ſoundly elided, and their falſity ſo plainly demonstrated, that the people profeſſed themſelves to have received full ſatisfaction. So that by the goodneſse of God that daies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction wan great credit to the truth, reputation to the Ministry, an encreaſe to that [formerly] thin and very diſcouraging lecture, reclaimed ſome deceived ſouls, confirmed many; and is interpreted by ſome as a pledge of the fullfilling of that Promiſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
            <p>Some men may poſſsibly diſlike the action it ſelf, and queſtion the prudence and diſcretion of the Miniſters, who would ſo much undervalue themſelves as to conteſt with ſuch ignorant wranglers. But the happy ſucceſſe thereof may alone ſufficiently anſwer whatſoever may be objected againſt their ſo doing; to ſay nothing of the great ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of truth which were there likely to have been, had there wanted ſtrong oppoſition.</p>
            <p>As for the perſons who with ſuch courage undertook, and with ſuch felicity managed this buſineſſe: thus much I dare ſay, in their behalf, that they aimed more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the maintenance of the truth, then at the praiſe of a Victory. And yet they aimed at victory alſo, but not to credit themſelves but the truth, I have cauſe to think, that there was no Miniſter there, but is of my minde; who could be content and willing to be abaſed, ſcorned, and ſlighted, to loſe all my comforts and hopes on earth, to wander about as a vagabond, being <hi>deſtitute, afflicted, tormented;</hi> So that the name of Chriſt may be glorious, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom advanced; if it were pleaſing to God ſo to have it, and my affliction might be more for his glory then my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and proſperity.</p>
            <p>Nor let any ſupercilious cenſurer diſtaſt the publiſhing
<pb facs="tcp:114723:13"/> hereof. No ſuch thing was ever intended, till the deſires of ſome godly Christians (who were willing that others might receive that benefit by reading of it, as themſelves had by hearing it) and the neceſſity of vindicating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves forced them to it. Some reports were ſpread abroad, that the <hi>Miniſters were not only ſilenced, but did alſo acknowledge their errour, and openly make recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> So that they were neceſſitated to make the whole publique. And herein they have <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, who having had frequent conflicts with the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi> was forced at laſt to commit all his diſputations to Writing, becauſe they alwaies proclaimed themſelves <hi>Victorious,</hi> though indeed (as theſe <hi>Donatiſts at Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſcombe</hi>) they were mightily convinced and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As for theſe, its true, they never left <hi>prating,</hi> but that was looked upon and eſteemed as no other then the <hi>wriggling</hi> of ſome <hi>Inſecta,</hi> when their heads are off.</p>
            <p>Reader, Thou maist not expect any elaborate Diſcourſe here. The diſpute was ſudden and unpremeditated; the Sermon ſuch as was then delivered, when never intended to be publiſhed: and I hope, that theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will <hi>apologize</hi> with thee for the Authour, who was willing, though much to his own prejudice, to impart it to thee, without any manner of dreſse, more then it had when he uttered it.</p>
            <p>I had thought, (Good Reader) to have ſpoken more by way of Exhortation both to the honeſt-hearted, and alſo to thoſe who are for the preſent gone aſtray; but that I have already detained thee too long from the reading of what follows: And I doubt not, but that, if thou reade with <hi>an humble heart,</hi> and <hi>a diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114723:14"/> 
               <hi>Spirit,</hi> thou wilt finde much ſatisfaction in the Points there handled. God in Mercy guide both thee and me into all truth. So prays,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant in the things of Chriſt, <hi>CHARLS DARBY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114723:14"/>
            <head>THE CHURCHES &amp; MINISTERY of ENGLAND, True Churches, and true Miniſtery.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 COR. 1. 2.</bibl>
               <q>To the Church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, with all that in every place call upon the Name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I. <hi>The Text opened and expounded.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words conteining the object of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation, ſhew us to whom he ſends and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates this his Epiſtle, <hi>viz.</hi> in the firſt and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter place, <hi>to the Church of God at Corinth;</hi> and then more at large and ſecondarily, to the Churches of God all the world over; even as it is ſubjoined, <hi>with all that in every place call upon</hi> (that is, by a Senecdoche, worſhip) <hi>the Name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, both theirs and ours;</hi> that is, Jeſus Chriſt, their Lord, as well as ours.</p>
               <p>Now, to be the more particular and pertinent, we pitch upon the firſt and ſtricter object here of this ſalutation and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; touching which the text affords, Firſt its appellation <hi>the Church;</hi> with, Secondly, its deſcription, and that three waies.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114723:15"/> 1. It is deſcribed in its ſpecification, the Church of <hi>God.</hi> 2. Its ſituation, the Church of God <hi>at Corinth.</hi> 3. Its qualification, <hi>'Tis ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, and called to be holy;</hi> all which we ſhall briefly run over again, and, clearing the ſame, make the way more plain for our following diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (moſt eaſily derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>evoco</hi>) here rendred <hi>the Church,</hi> is frequently uſed for <hi>any</hi> company aſſembled together for <hi>any</hi> cauſe, both in <hi>prophane</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 19. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>holy</hi> Scriptures. We may reduce all kinde of aſſemblies to theſe three, <hi>Sinfull, Civil,</hi> or <hi>Sacred,</hi> and finde this word expreſſing them all. For firſt, there is a ſinfull Church, <hi>the Congregation of evil doers.</hi> Secondly, There is a Civil Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 36. <note place="margin">Pſal. 26. 5.</note> And laſtly, There is a ſacred or a godly Church, as this the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was, which is here ſo plainly diſtinguiſhed from the two former, by this ſpeciall attribute, <hi>Of God:</hi> It is not the Church of the <hi>devil</hi> or <hi>men,</hi> but the Church of <hi>God</hi> at <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this ſame <hi>[Church of God]</hi> is of various uſe and meaning <note place="margin">Church of God.</note> too, and a little inquiry made thereinto we ſhall finde a help and furtherance to us in our way.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scripture means ſometimes by the <hi>Church of God,</hi> the whole inviſible, myſticall body of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole number of the elect both in Heaven and earth that are or ſhall be gathered into one under Chriſt the head, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 24, 25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sometimes again the Scrpture uſeth the Church of God for the univerſall viſible Church, which conſiſteth of all the particular Churches and perſons) with their children) through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world that profeſs the true religion: So it is uſed 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sometimes alſo by a Metonimy, for the place it ſelf where a certain number of the viſible Church uſe to aſſemble. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Sometimes alſo by a Synecdoche, for any number of Church-members where ever they be. So in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 19. <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly, Sometimes for a particular viſible Church, whether it conſiſts of one Congregation or more, as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114723:15"/> Church at <hi>Jeruſalem, Smyrna, Thyatira,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo in the text, the Church of God at <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So far then we are come, having found this Epiſtle ſent to a <hi>Church,</hi> and that a Church <hi>of God,</hi> and the Church of God <hi>at Corinth</hi> too.</p>
               <p>There is now but one main thing behind (but that indeed is a main one) namely, the <hi>qualification</hi> of this Church of God at <hi>Corinth,</hi> which is blaz'd before us in the following words; <hi>to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words do plainly intend the matter or members of the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> becauſe all others are expreſſed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>with all that in every place,</hi> &amp;c. and alſo what theſe members are <hi>viz.</hi> of two ſorts; Saints indeed <hi>(ſuch as are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified in Chriſt Jeſus,)</hi> and ſuch as are <hi>called</hi> to be ſo, though indeed they be not ſo; for <hi>many are called and few choſen:</hi> many are called to be members of the viſible, but few to be members of the inviſible Church: <hi>for they are not all Iſrael that are of Iſrael.</hi> Or elſe, if you leave out thoſe two little <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 6.</note> words <hi>[to be]</hi> which the Engliſh ſupplies, it may ſeem to be thus; the words <hi>[to all that are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,]</hi> are expounded by theſe latter words, <hi>called Saints: q. a.</hi> to all that are ſanctified, or ſhould be ſo; that bear the name, the form, though they want the thing and power of holineſs and ſanctification: one of theſe two (chooſe which you will) muſt needs be the meaning of the Apoſtle here; which will be moſt cleer, if we but once think, to whom, and for what end he writes this Epiſtle: to the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and on purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them too, and that for ſuch groſs and vile corruptions, as he knew (and we confeſs) are even inconſiſtent with true ſanctity, faith and holineſs, though not incompetent to a true Church, (as is plentifully manifeſt through his Epiſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) which I ſhall reduce and ſet before you under three heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He reprooves them for the breach of the Laws of <hi>ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sins of the Church of <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi>
                  </note> in the two groſs and known ſins, <hi>gluttony</hi> and <hi>drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> cap. 11. 21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> in their diviſions, envyings, ſtrifes, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 1, 2, 3, 5. and worſe, in inceſt too <hi>cap.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of piety and <hi>holineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (living neither godly, righteouſly,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114723:16"/> 
                  <hi>nor ſoberly:</hi>) And firſt, in defect, I mean in diſcipline, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their mixt and diſorderly fellowſhip, not caſting out the lewd and ſcandalous rout, <hi>cap.</hi> 5. with 11. as alſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, in exceſs, by <hi>ſchiſm:</hi> one deſpiſing <hi>Paul,</hi> and another <hi>Apollo;</hi> cap. 3. 4. <hi>Hereſie,</hi> denying the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Idolatry,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. with (to conclude) a moſt egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>prophanation</hi> of the holy Table, through <hi>ignorance, glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, drunkenneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now doubtleſs all theſe great and groſs corruptions, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to <hi>Paul,</hi> and even juſt now, with this very Epiſtle, about to be reproved by him, in thus Church; he could not ſo groſly bewray his flattery, or ſin ſo deeply againſt his knowledge, as mean to call them <hi>reall</hi> Saints, all Saints, that were the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it. Yea from what hath been ſaid, we muſt conclude; 1. That they were not all <hi>reall</hi> Saints. 2. Nor yet all <hi>viſible</hi> Saints, though indeed called to be both of theſe. Some true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers there were among them, ſome viſible Saints, not true beleevers; thoſe are both likely; but this is certain, there were many vile and openly prophane and ſcandalous perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; and as certain alſo (notwithſtanding them) <hi>Paul</hi> ſalutes them as the Church of God. Notwithſtanding he fore-knew and intended by this his Epiſtle, to reprove all thoſe groſſe and abominable ſins you have heard, yet here and behold his ſalutation runs, <hi>To the Church of God at Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>That a mixture of prophane and ſcandalous perſons with reall Saints, is not inconſiſtent with the Church of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the Text thus opened, we deſcend to inferre ſome <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> Points, which (like unto a chain) though eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry link be not faſtned immediatly to the firſt, we ſhall finde have a plain and kindely dependance each upon other, and they are theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That a mixture of prophane and ſcandalous perſons with</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114723:16"/> 
                     <hi>reall Saints, is not inconſiſtent with the Church of God. or a true Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That then, the Churches that are now in England, are Churches of God, and true Churches.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That then, the Miniſtry of theſe Churches, is the Miniſtry of God and the true Miniſtry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That then, there is a great and heavy ſin lying at the door of all ſuchS, as do preſume to proach publikely among us without a call, who have true Churches, and a ſetled Miniſtry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>And then</hi> (to conclude) <hi>they alſo muſt needs be guilty, that forſake true Churches, and a lawfull Miniſtry, to follow and hear unſent preachers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I ſhall be as brief and plain as I may upon each of theſe in order.</p>
               <p>1. The firſt of theſe immediatly depends upon the text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; <note place="margin">Scandalous perſons in a true Church.</note> for if there were prophane and ſcandalous perſons in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and yet notwithſtanding ſhe bore the name of the <hi>Church of God,</hi> it muſt immediatly and naturally follows, that there may be prophane and ſcandalous perſons in the Church of God: there may be, I ſay, but I mean <hi>de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto,</hi> and not <hi>de jure;</hi> I confeſs they ought not to be there, but if they be, they do not unchurch the aſſembly wherein they are: they are the <hi>diſeaſe</hi> and trouble of the Church, but not its <hi>death:</hi> indeed, ſuch groſs and vile corruptions as we have found to have been in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> are as inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with a pure Church, as boyls and leproſie with a pure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: but yet, for all, as the ſoul doth not preſently leave and diſown the body, for any diſeaſe, except it be mortall; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth Chriſt his body the Church. Both the naturall and miſticall body may be true, though very corrupt: and what I have before aſſerted, is undeniable, <hi>viz. That a mixture of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ſcandalous perſons, with reall Saints, is not inconſiſtent with a Church of God, or a true Church:</hi> for we ſee, in the pureſt times, in the very time of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves, as ſoon as ever the ſeed was ſown, tares are mixt: as ſoon as ever the Churches are planted, they are thus diſeaſed; many corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are known to abound in moſt of them, and yet all of them are owned, none denied to be Churches of God, even by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114723:17"/> the Apoſtles. If this inſtance of <hi>Corinth</hi> be not ſufficient; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica, Galatia, Epheſus, Pergamus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Thyatyra;</hi> who had the <hi>myſtery of iniquity already working;</hi> who ſuffered themſelves to be ſoon carried away to <hi>another</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Goſpel,</hi> who had loſt <hi>the firſt love;</hi> who had thoſe that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>the doctrine of Baladm,</hi> with the hereſie of the Nicola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itans; <note place="margin">Revel. 2. 3. and 3. 14. 20.</note> and who laſtly ſuffered the Propheteſs <hi>Jezabel.</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the <hi>ſervants of Chriſt</hi> (as <hi>England</hi> too much) who yet notwithſtanding are called <hi>Churches,</hi> yea and Churches of Chriſt: and by the Apoſtles themſelves commending the good that was in them, even while, in the mean, they reprove the evil that they did, or ſuffered to be done among them.</p>
               <p>And therefore it was doubtleſs a very groſs errour of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Viſible <hi>Church</hi> not a company of true Saints. Mat. 13. 37. Mat. 3. 12.</note> and thoſe of the old ſeparation, to define the Church to be <hi>a company of faithfull people that truly worſhip Chriſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily obey him.</hi> Alas the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> that is, the Miniſtry ſent to gather Churches, is a <hi>net</hi> that gathereth fiſh both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad:</hi> and the Church is a <hi>floor</hi> that hath <hi>chaff</hi> and <hi>wheat,</hi> and a through-ſeparation ſhall never be attained, till the great diſtinguiſhing day comes. The ground of their errour is this, they confound the <hi>inviſible</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> Church. It is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, I fear, that if none may be ſaid to be a true Church, but ſhe whoſe members are all true beleevers, there is no true Church in the world this day, if there ever have been: Beſides, how ſenſeleſs it is to make true faith (an <hi>inviſible</hi> thing) the mark of the <hi>viſible</hi> Church I</p>
               <p>Again, Though the errour be not ſo groſs, 'tis very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <note place="margin">2. Nor alwaies of viſible Saints.</note> to ſay, that there cannot be wicked and ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in a true Church; for this doth immediatly tend to ſchiſme, and if it raſeth the foundation (as plainly appeareth) of thoſe firſt Apoſtolicall Churches, well may it ours. Alas, a particular perſon may have many failings and groſs corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions powerfull in him, and yet all the while (I hope) be a childe of God: even ſo a Church may be very much degenerate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly corrupt, and all the while be a Church of God, as the <note place="margin">Reaſ, Becauſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions ſtrike not the being of a Church.</note> Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was: And the Reaſon is plain.</p>
               <p>The Reaſon is, Becauſe ſuch corruptions (in <hi>manners</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline</hi>) ſtrike at a Churches <hi>benè eſſe</hi> only, and not at the <hi>being</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114723:17"/> or eſſence of it: as a man with boiles and botches all over his body (like unto <hi>Job</hi>) is yet a <hi>true</hi> man, a man a live, though he be not ſo pure and healthy as other men are: theſe, indeed, do ſend him forward ſo far as in them lies to death and the grave, however he may not be ſaid to be <hi>dead,</hi> ſo long as his ſoul, <hi>his form</hi> abideth in him, which all theſe things cannot touch.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But this doth invite that doubtfull query, <hi>viz.</hi> touching the form and diſtinguiſhing note of a true Church: What it is, or where it lies?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> To which, (though I confeſs I have met with few that write clearly of it) I briefly anſwer, That for ought I finde, all ancient <note place="margin">What and wherein is the form of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church. Generally in Ordinances.</note> Churches and Counſels, before <hi>Rome</hi> was Antichriſt, and all the Churches reformed from her Antichriſtianiſm, together with all Judicious Papiſts themſelves, do jointly conclude, that the formall difference of the true Church, I mean, <hi>as viſible,</hi> lies in communion in true Ordinances; and on occaſion, farther enlarge and explain the meaning thus; that therefore the <hi>more or leſs pure</hi> the <hi>Ordinances</hi> are, the <hi>more or leſs pure</hi> the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> are, and though the Ordinances of Chriſt ſhould ſuffer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, yet if they may be ſaid, but to be true, and if there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main but only ſo much as will carry the Ordinances to be <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> even ſo far are the Churches, the ſubjects thereof, the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">When two or three are <hi>met</hi> together in <hi>my Name,</hi> defines a Church. Matth. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Communion,</hi> contains the <hi>form</hi> and eſſence of a <hi>Church</hi> in generall: <hi>communion in Ordinances of God,</hi> contains the Form of <hi>a Church of God;</hi> and the purer the Ordinances are, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the Churches: and the truer they are, the truer the Churches: but ſo long as the Ordinances may be known to be Chriſts, though the havers be very corrupt, we muſt own the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to be Chriſts alſo.</p>
               <p>But to be a little clearer, might I judge here, I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <note place="margin">Specially in Miniſters of the Word.</note> that <hi>the Miniſtery of the Word,</hi> rather then the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, contains the form of a particular viſible Church, for of ſuch we ſpeake. 1. As for Baptiſm, that enters the partie bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, into the univerſal viſible; and we muſt be conſtitute a particular viſible Church, before we have right unto, much more the enjoyment of the Lords Supper: indeed, none can be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114723:18"/> member of a particular Church unles he be baptiz'd, ſo baptiſm is a <hi>negative</hi> mark: and none can have a right to the Supper of the Lord, unleſs he be a member of a particular Church; ſo that the Lords Supper, I mean the actuall adminiſtration thereof, is a mark <hi>redundant.</hi> But, as for the miniſtry of the word, that <note place="margin">Therefore the Sacraments are called by Reverend <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents on the <hi>Word.</hi>
                  </note> hath in it not only a mark, but the form and difference of the viſible Church of which the Sacraments are but <hi>ſeals,</hi> and ſeem to alter and change the nature, as the <hi>doctrine</hi> doth; as the ſame <hi>ſeal</hi> is of different value, according to the nature and value of the <hi>writing</hi> to which it is ſet. So that when the <hi>doctrine</hi> becomes <hi>antichriſtian,</hi> the <hi>ſeals</hi> thereof, can ſcarce be <hi>chriſtian,</hi> though they be <hi>counterfet</hi> and would be <hi>ſo,</hi> this may not deny the <hi>baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to be lawfull baptiſm; yet thus far it goes, that the <hi>baptiſm</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is no farther chriſtian, then their doctrine touching it is ſo: for ſhould they deny the <hi>holy T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> although they did baptiſe in the Name of the Father, Son and holy Ghoſt, I hardly judg it to be lawfull baptiſme, though haply the old Rule might reach it, <hi>fieri non debuit, factum valet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However this is ſafely concluded, that the chief eſſentiall mark or form of a true particular viſible Church, conſiſts in a <hi>fixt and ſetled viſible fellowſhip in the miniſtry of the word of Chriſt.</hi> A Church is ſo called from its gathering together, and where is this ſo plainly ſeen as in its viſible communion in the miniſtry of the word, eſpecially being ſetled and conſtant? what <hi>advantage hath the Jew above the Gentile?</hi> the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the world? much every way, but chiefly becauſe to them is <hi>committed</hi> the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God: this is the particular privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>But a little more diſtinctly, I mean the miniſtry here on both ſides: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Docens, utens.</hi> The Papiſts of late deny this: but <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton</hi> one of the chief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſaith, The preaching of the Goſpel is the proper and</note> the <hi>teaching</hi> part: and the <hi>uſing,</hi> hearing and receiving part. 1. The miniſteriall Churches have their mark, <hi>viz. true doctrine,</hi> and this eſpecially join'd with the other, is very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to diſcover to us the <hi>true Church.</hi> For this ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 2, 3. As if Chriſt ſhould ſay, join your ſelves to them; though wicked and prophane, yet they are a <hi>true Church.</hi> But how is that known? why, their miniſtry is true; they ſit in <hi>Moſes chair:</hi> But how doth that appear? becauſe their word and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114723:18"/> doctrine is true, though their lives be wicked; <hi>hear them, but do</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">a very cleer Note of the Catholick Church, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters. <hi>Princ. dort.</hi> c. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>what they ſay, not what they do.</hi> And anſwerable to this, is our Saviours rule, for triall of Prophets, By their <hi>fruit,</hi> that is, by their doctrine ye <hi>ſhall know</hi> what they be, whether true or falſe: preachers of the ſound and orthodox truth, is both a <hi>means</hi> and a <hi>mark;</hi> a means of <hi>gathering,</hi> and ſtrengthening, or <hi>confirming,</hi> or keeping the Churches thereby together. Now as the preaching of the word is a means to gather and conſtitute Churches at <hi>firſt,</hi> ſo it being uſually occaſionall only, it is not ſaid to be a mark of the true Church: but being gathered by the word, and church'd by Baptiſm, the <hi>miniſtery ſetled</hi> and fix'd (as was ſaid) among them, becomes an eſſentiall mark of the true Church. Not only of the <hi>teaching</hi> (which it doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly) but of the <hi>profeſſing</hi> Church alſo, ſince who can ſay where the true Church is, but where the true <hi>doctrine</hi> and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is <hi>fix'd</hi> and ſetled? and therefore we ſhall never read that God did ever divorce any Church, though ſhe deſerv'd it long <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 5. <hi>Nulla poſſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſchiſmatius fieri tanta corruptio,</hi> i. <hi>emendatio, quanta eſt ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis pernities,</hi> if the doctrine of faith be ſound, <hi>Tert. de praeſ. cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Si confeſſio ejus convenit cum Scripturis verus eſt Chriſtianus, ſin minus falſus.</hi> Chryſoſt.</note> before, untill he removes his <hi>candleſtick</hi> from them. Which is moſt remarkable <hi>in the Jewiſh Church,</hi> who, while a Church, God did not <hi>deal ſo with any Nation,</hi> neither had the heathen knowledge of his Laws; and the Apoſtles are charged to preach the Goſpel to none other; and who continued without all doubt to be a viſible Church of God, untill the courſe or the miniſtery is turned from her to the Gentiles: then and not till then, God <hi>cut off the Jew</hi> and <hi>ingrafted the Gentile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. There is another chief mark of the viſible Church, which lieth on the Receivers part, I mean, (as before the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo here) the profeſſours of the truth: <hi>My ſheep hear my voice,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, that is, my <hi>reall</hi> ſheep hear my doctrine really and my viſible ſheep, apparently and viſibly; ſo that a <hi>people baptized, profeſſing the true doctrine of Chriſt, and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly united in the publike and conſtant hearing and receiving the doctrine of Chriſt, from the true Miniſtry, are a true Church, and are hereby known to be ſo.</hi> I ſay, this profeſſion is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, when the company do openly and viſibly own and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe by frequenting the publike Ordinance of hearing, the true doctrine; and ſufficient to diſcover them a true Church, though very corrupt in other regards. Now each of theſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114723:19"/> the ſetled Preaching, and conſtant receiving (by publike at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending) the doctrine of Chriſt, are very good marks of a true particular viſible Church; and in both together I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive conſiſts the form of the ſame, <hi>viz. in a fixt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant viſible fellowſhip with God and each other in the ſacred Ordinance of preaching and hearing the doctrine of Chriſt:</hi> and from this a Church may recede and die two waies: being ſtarved to death through a Famine of the Word, with the Church of the Jews. 2. Or elſe being <hi>poyſoned</hi> to death by contagious doctrine, with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> 'Tis but weak to object, That the preaching or hearing of the Word may not be marks, or contain the eſſence of a true Church, becauſe theſe are <hi>common to Infidels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> For the Preaching and hearing of the Word, as common with Inſidels, is occaſionall only, as it was with <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Paul:</hi> but as it is an infallible mark of the viſible Church 'tis (as before) fixt and ſetled: and in that as occaſionall preaching and hearing of the Word is the only proper means of gathering Churches; ſo where it hath ſo far wrought and prevailed, as that it is become fixt and conſtant with any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is to me a certain mark of gathered Churches; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alwaies, ſubmiſſion hath been made to the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p>To which I ſubjoyn this argument: That which doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally conſtitute or make a member of a Church, doth conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or make a whole Church: But <hi>profeſſion of the faith</hi> doth formally conſtitute a member of the viſible Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole viſible Church; ſince the whole here is made of parts of the ſame nature: viſibility denominateth the parts, and therefore the whole of the viſible Church: as true faith is eſſentiall to a member of the Church inviſible, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that faith to a member of the viſible: ſo truth of faith doth conſtitute the inviſible Church, and profeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a viſible Church, according to the rule, <hi>quae eſt ratio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutiva partium, eſt etiam conſtitutiva totius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But what ſhall we think of thoſe Churches then, that in time of perſecution loſe their Miniſters, ſo that the publike means of viſible profeſſion is gone?</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114723:19"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, Such ceaſe not preſently to be true Churches: for while they own, they profeſſe the truth and profeſſion, we have ſhew'd, is a good mark on the peoples part.</p>
               <p>2. While they deſire the ſame they have a right thereto, and enjoy this publike communion in its firſt act, though they want the <hi>actuall administration</hi> and enjoyment of it.</p>
               <p>3. But conſidering how much of the form of the Church <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecclefia est uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregationis cujus membra inter ſe combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur &amp;</hi> ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nariè <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt uno in loco ad publicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</hi> Ame. Med. p. 215. 2. 2.</note> conſiſts in this publike communion together, I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſuch a people better then to a man in a ſwound, in whom for a time the ſoul, the form, ceaſeth to perform its formall actions; though it be not yet ſevered and gone from the body, yet if ſuch a fit as this continue, Phyſicians tell us 'tis very dangerous, and experience reckons it a ſure infallible ſign of death: even ſo, when <hi>Viſion fails, the People periſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>That the Churches that are now in</hi> England <hi>are Churches of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe next concluſion doth naturally follow, and cloſely and immediatly depend upon the former, for ſince (as we have found) a mixture of prophane and ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with reall Saints, is not inconſiſtent with the Church of God, or a true Church; <hi>Then our Churches that are now in England, are Churches of God and true Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare not ſay they are pure, and much leſſe perfect, yet I <note place="margin">Our Churches true Churches.</note> doubt not to prove them <hi>true</hi> Churches.: but by Churches I mean not (though I highly commend that hand of wiſedom that made the parochiall difference) the Pariſhes here (or at leaſt not as under the notion of Pariſhes) but the fixt and ſetled and uſuall aſſembling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſiſting of Pariſhes, or more or leſſe. Theſe I affirm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Churches of God, and true Churches. In the proof whereof, though I might very ſafely confine my ſelf to what hath been ſaid, touching the eſſence and marks of a Church before, I ſhall lay my line ſomewhat larger, to make (if poſſible) ſurer work.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114723:20"/>
               <p> Yet all ſhall be reduced to two Arguments, and the firſt is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> There is nothing in our Churches to make them falſe, and nothing wanting in them to make them true Churches: and <note place="margin">Nothing in them to the contrary.</note> what then can hinder them from being true? Firſt, I ſay, there is nothing in our Churches to make them falſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Neither of <hi>manners,</hi> nor 2. of <hi>government.</hi> 1. For <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. If either, we in theſe later daies ſhould have ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance above theſe firſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Churches, for the Church is compared to a ſhip, the which the more it ſails upon the ſea the more it is ſubject to leakes: to a houſe, that with oldneſs doth decay and grow to ruine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Morney</hi> of the Church. p. 38.</note> we confeſſe that the Lord hath much againſt us, both of ſin and errour, diſorder, prophaneſſe, blaſphemy and hereſie: but conſider, all this cannot unchurch us: this may <hi>de jure,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking the Lord to remove his Candleſticks away from us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we repent: but while we have theſe, I mean his <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks,</hi> Word and Ordinances, our corruptions cannot <hi>de facto</hi> make us no Church, nor yet a falſe: no more then it did the Church of <hi>Corinth:</hi> unleſſe there have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing revealed from heaven ſince then, that hath placed the eſſence of a viſible Church in the conditions and manners of the members thereof; which if, we pray, when, where, and how?</p>
               <p n="2">2. For matter of <hi>government,</hi> indeed of late we were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Epiſcopacy: all whoſe appurtenances ſavoured of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: yet could they never denominate our Churches An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Churches: while our <hi>doctrine</hi> pure our <hi>heart</hi> was ſound though our <hi>heads</hi> did ake: for juſt ſo it was with the Church of the Jews in our Saviours time; the Rulers were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, the Prieſt corrupt, yet notwithſtanding (their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pure) our Saviour accounts them a true Church, and accordingly adviſes his own Diſciples to joyn unto them, as before we ſhewed, the doctrine heretofore among us, is ſtill extant: and none can pick any materiall errours in it, our Epiſcopall ſervice, Courts, tyranny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were very groſſe, yet not inconſiſtent with true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>rine, and much leſſe doubtleſſe with true Churches; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were even then when ſuch like abuſes were higheſt, ever acknowledged, ſometimes defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by preaching and printing, againſt the Browniſts, as is very well known by thoſe very men, that touching our corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions were <hi>Non-conformiſts.</hi> But ſuppoſe we ſhould give you what you beg for, that our Churches then under (I mean)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114723:20"/> the Epiſcopall government were Antichriſtian thereby: what gain you? muſt we be therefore Antichriſtian ſtill? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid. Are we not reformed (at leaſt ſo far) from that very thing for which you impleade us? Are not Biſhops gone? their Courts and Service-book, and all their dependencies gone along with them? I hope then we are not Antichriſtian ſtill? becauſe you and your brethren were Heathens and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels before you were dipt, are you ſo ſtill? that you will ſay is but poor reaſoning: what then is there left to make us An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian? You will not ſay Presbytery, for that will be vain, vainer then vain, ſince as it can never be proved Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, ſo neither are we yet governed by it.</p>
               <p>And as there is nothing in our Churches in <hi>England</hi> to <note place="margin">2. Nothing wanting in them.</note> make them <hi>falſe,</hi> ſo is there nothing wanting in them to make them <hi>true;</hi> now we can be pretended to want but 3. things that are neceſſary to a Church; <hi>Church-governours, Church-government,</hi> and <hi>Church-Covenant.</hi> Now as for <hi>Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> we have ſo many of them as the being of a Church (though not as the well-being of it) requires; ſince the form of a Church conſiſts in Ordinances (not in Diſcipline) and we have ſufficient adminiſtrers of them, <hi>who rule over us by ſpeaking to us the word of God,</hi> Heb. 13. 7. 2. As for <hi>Church-government</hi> in ſome places, in ſome branches, <hi>viz.</hi> of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, 'tis wanting among us; but the want thereof cannot unchurch us, for the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> wanted the ſame (<hi>Cap.</hi> 5.) and yet is ſaluted as the Church of God. 3. And laſtly, We want not either a <hi>Church-covenant,</hi> ſince the word of God requires it not. 2. Since we have it implicitly, though not expreſly: for we muſt have ſome agreement or other who walk together in the ſame fellowſhip, for <hi>how can two walk together unleſſe they be agreed?</hi> 3. Beſides our Brethren of the <hi>Congregationall way</hi> that are ſo much for this Covenant, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count us true Churches, though we want it and ſhould have it; What want we then? yea, what have we not? have we not the Sabbath, Word, Prayer, Sacraments, and Cenſures too in many places with us? however what want we, eſſentiall to a Church, who have matter and form? <hi>matter,</hi> in that we have both reall Saints to gratifie you, and viſible profeſſors to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114723:21"/> us! Touching the qualification of Church-members in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and of our own in particular, ſufficient hath been ſaid before: and for the firſt <hi>conſtitution</hi> of our Churches in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> though that be nothing to our preſent condition, we have largely cleared it in the <hi>debate</hi> related and printed after the Sermon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>The Churches that are now in England are the Churches of God, becauſe they are in Covenant with him.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cauſe in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Pſal. 50. 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now the conſequence here will not be queſtioned, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is Analogicall, upon that Text, <hi>Gather my Saints to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unto me allye that have made a Covenant with me,</hi> &amp;c. implying hereby, by being in Covenant with God they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a Church, for that they have a right to be an <hi>Actuall Congregation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Aſſumption hence, <hi>viz. That we are in Covenant with God,</hi> cals for proof, which is eaſily performed by three Arguments, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe we have the <hi>Seal</hi> of the Covenant, the <hi>word</hi> of the Covenant, and the <hi>bleſſings</hi> of the Covenant; all which we ſhall finde not only to prove us in Covenant with God, but immediatly to conclude us a Church of God too.</p>
               <p>Then firſt, We have the <hi>ſeal</hi> of the Covenant, the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Having the Seal of the Covenant.</note> 
                  <hi>of Baptiſm,</hi> which in its predeceſſour, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> was called the <hi>token</hi> of the Covenant, or a token from God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhould know themſelves to be in Covenant with God; and this token or ſeal was called by God (and commanded by him to his people under the name of) the Covenant; inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating to us, that thoſe that denied the ſeal denied the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or exclude themſelves from any intereſt in it; as is the folly and weakneſſe of too many with us, in renouncing their <hi>baptiſm.</hi> Now as this is the <hi>ſeal</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo is it alſo the <hi>door of the Church;</hi> for perſons though really converted by the preaching of the Goſpel, and the Children of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, born in the Church, are not (though virtuall) actuall members of the viſible Church, before <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which ſeems to be built upon the known Text, <hi>Go, diſciple all Nations, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them:</hi> that is, <hi>diſciple,</hi> not by <hi>teaching</hi> only, not by tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching properly, but by <hi>baptiſm:</hi> the participle uſing to ſignifie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114723:21"/> the manner of doing: <hi>Go, diſciple,</hi> but how muſt we diſciple? why as before by <hi>circumeiſing,</hi> ſo now by <hi>baptizing,</hi> and in this Commiſſion in <hi>Matthew</hi> to the Apoſtles, the Commiſſion given to our <hi>Father Abraham,</hi> is but enlarged: 'tis the ſame <note n="*" place="margin">The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Jewiſh Church in ſubſtance were one and the ſame with our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Heb. 13. 8. 1 Cor. 10. 1, 2, 3. Joh. 8. 56. Joh. 6. 50, 51. Col. 1. 11, 12. 1 Cor. 5. 7. all ſay this except Papiſts, Anabaptiſts, Arminians and Socinians.</note> for ſubſtance though it differ in circumſtance: the <hi>work</hi> is the ſame to <hi>diſciple,</hi> and make up Churches, though the matter is larger; <hi>Abraham</hi> chiefly, that <hi>one Nation</hi> to come out of his loines, together with all that would joyn as <hi>proſelytes;</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel Miniſters</hi> muſt diſciple all nations, <hi>(i.)</hi> ſo far as they can, and <hi>the nation will ſubmit unto them. Abraham</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to diſciple, by that <hi>initiating</hi> ordinance of <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> and the Goſpel Miniſters, by this of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> indeed there is teaching prerequiſite, to prepare and fit <hi>men out of the Church</hi> for the ordinance of Baptiſm; and ſo much was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make men proſelytes, for Circumciſion: which thing makes it cleer, that not only <hi>Abrahams</hi> naturall ſeed had right to this Ordinance, or that his ſeed were circumciſed as his ſeed, but, as they were capable of being members of the viſible Church: and therefore we finde, that when heathen people were willing to become members of the Church, they had the Ordinance of initiation, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> to enter <hi>them</hi> in, and not <hi>them</hi> only, but their <hi>children</hi> alſo: which is a cleer pattern for the Miniſters of the Goſpel towards the Gentiles: How ſhall we behave our ſelves to them? why, we have commiſſion to diſciple them. But how? why as the Miniſters of Law did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, Gentiles before us, by Circumciſion; ſo muſt we now by Baptiſm: but whom among them? why, as they before us, the proſely to Gentiles, and their children too; ſo muſt we alſo diſciple (by baptiſm) the nations of the Gentiles, and their children too, ſo far as they ſubmit themſelves, and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Ordinance of Chriſt. But I muſt return; Baptiſm wee ſee is the door of the Church, which further appears by <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Except a man be born again of water and of the spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> this Kingdom of God, I conceive to be the Church (for Chriſt is telling <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> here of earthly things,) and you may conceive the Church inviſible or viſible: if <hi>inviſible,</hi> here is a door to let you in, the baptiſm of the <hi>spirit</hi> and regeneration <hi>reall:</hi> if <hi>viſible,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114723:22"/> here is another door for that too, the baptiſm of <hi>water,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation <hi>viſible:</hi> a man may be born again <hi>(i)</hi> become a new man, two waies, and accordingly may have place in the Church two waies: he may be born again <hi>indeed</hi> by a <hi>reall</hi> work of the ſpirit within, and thus becomes a member of the <hi>inviſible</hi> Church: or elſe a man may be born again <hi>in ſhew</hi> only, from a <hi>viſible member of the world</hi> and the divel, <hi>diſcipled by baptiſm,</hi> and made thereby a viſible member of Chriſt, and entered into the <hi>viſible Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> the viſible Church: which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is ſometimes firſt, according to the order of the words, except a man be born again of <hi>water</hi> and of the ſpirit, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into (the viſible or inviſible Church) the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Now to end with this, it cannot be denied upon a good ground, but we in <hi>England</hi> are a diſcipled nation, and are entered into the Kingdom of Heaven, the viſible Church, being <hi>born again by water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither have we the <hi>ſeal</hi> only, for we have the <hi>writings</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. And word of it. Church is built upon the foundation of Apoſtles and Prophets.</note> too: not only a <hi>pledg</hi> or token of the bargain, but the <hi>word</hi> of the Covenant alſo, <hi>the Scriptures in purity, and the Ordinances of them in power and fullneſs:</hi> which is undeniable, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have the <hi>Covenant</hi> (Deut. 4. 13. Heb. 9. 4.) alſo; above all reaſonable contradiction; and therefore we are the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God for full ſatisfaction. To <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 9. 4.</note> the Jews belonged the <hi>Adoption, glory, and Covenants;</hi> but how does it appear? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to them belonged <hi>the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God.</hi> And what <hi>advantage</hi> had the <hi>Jew</hi> by being a Church above the Gentile, that was none? why, much every way, but chiefly, becauſe to them were committed <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3. 1, 2. The walls of the Church have their foundation in the Names <hi>(i)</hi> doctrine of the twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and is therefore the pillar and ground of truth. Rev. 21. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the Oracles of God:</hi> ſhewing, that they were a peculiar priviledge to, and a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing character of the viſible Church: for <hi>God ſheweth his word unto Jacob, his Statutes and judgements unto Iſrael, and hath not dealt ſo with any nation,</hi> that is; among the heathen that have no Church. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147. 19, 20. compared with <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 7 other nations doubtleſs might have the <hi>Bible</hi> among them, as we at this day have the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoron;</hi> but here lay the difference, God did not <hi>ſhew,</hi> promulge or preach his word to them; it was not with them as the <hi>Oracles of God,</hi> the <hi>word of the Covenant</hi> to them.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114723:22"/>
               <p> Goſpel Ordinances, are a great part of the outward admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ubi eſt fides il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic eſt Eccleſia, ubi non eſt fides, ibi non eſt eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> Chryſo.</note> of Goſpel Covenant, where God is pleaſed to hold a viſible communion with us, and we with him (as before,) and ſo long as we have theſe we are no doubt in covenant with God, and then, a Church of God.</p>
               <p>And to make all ſure, we have the <hi>peculiar bleſſings</hi> of the <note place="margin">3. And the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of it.</note> covenant which God beſtows on none but ſuch as are in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with him, his own Churches. Theſe are chiefly three: the bleſſing of his <hi>spirit,</hi> of his <hi>providence,</hi> and of his <hi>people:</hi> the firſt is inward, the two later outward, but all ſpirituall and all ſpeciall and peculiar bleſſings: but of them in order.</p>
               <p>The firſt and inward bleſſing of the Covenant, is the bleſſing <note place="margin">1. Converſion.</note> (I mean not only the common convictions, enlightenings with the knowledge of the Goſpel, which is indeed peculiar to the Church however, but the ſpeciall bleſſings) of <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> accompanying his word, for the work of converſion, in the hearts of our hearers. This I make an infallible Mark of the truth of our Churches, <hi>Converſion ordinarily wrought in our Churches.</hi> Converſion may be extraordinarily wrought by diſcourſe; what's that? we ſpeak of a uſuall and ordinary work: and 'tis vainer to ſay, we convert from ſinne to duty and not to God: this is againſt charity, ſenſe, and reaſon: firſt, againſt <hi>charity,</hi> to damn all thoſe that have no other grace then what was received from the hand of our Miniſtery: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>ſenſe,</hi> for bloudy experience hath proved that faith to be true that was wrought by our Miniſtery, in its ſubjects, <hi>martyrdome:</hi> and laſtly againſt <hi>reaſon,</hi> yea, I may ſay, all Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture too, as if duty was not in ſubordination to God. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you cannot over throw the Scriputre, which faith, <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and that by the Word of God preacht,</hi> by a ſent Miniſter, which is uſually fixt in a Church; whence hath been written, and ſealed by all ages, without contradiction, that good rule, <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla ſalus,</hi> no ordinary ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and therefore no converſion, is uſually had out of the Church: which clearly concludes thoſe Churches true where it is ſo.</p>
               <p>The ſecond (outward) bleſſing peculiar to a Church in <note place="margin">2. Speciall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</note> Covenant with God is his <hi>ſpeciall Providence:</hi> for God hath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114723:23"/> doubtleſſe a different care and providence over his garden the Church, and the common wilderneſſe of the world: now all his dealings with us ſince reform'd and ſeparate from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath plainly manifeſted his ſpeciall garden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care and providence over us, who can deny it? not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts themſelves, who have ſeen and felt ſuch ſignall teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of it in 88. powder-Treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hath God long agone caſt us off as Antichriſtian Churches, and yet all the while ſtill ſo remarkably kept us from the ſlavery of Antichriſt? what an inſufferable contradiction is this? nay more, conſider his Providences towards us of late years: how long hath there been workings and ſtirrings in the bowels of this Land for a further reformation and diſtance from <hi>Rome?</hi> and how much in order thereunto of late hath God wrought for us? and all the while that we have been cleanſing in the fire of affliction, what wonderfull power and goodneſſe hath he ſhewn us? and is this the way that God uſeth to walk with a people divorc'd and caſt away? who can lift up his face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt heaven and ſay it? no rather, ſuch a manner of neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>if they be filthy, let them be filthy still;</hi> and if they be Antichriſtian, let them be ſo ſtill; If not a giving them over to <hi>strong deluſions</hi> to beleeve lyes.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt bleſſing of the Covenant, is outward <note place="margin">3. Salutation of all Churches.</note> too, <hi>viz. the bleſſing of the people, and Churches of God:</hi> this I take to be a peculiar Church-bleſſing, and ſufficient to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a people in Covenant with, and a Church of God; which bleſſed be God, we have in abundance, who have the ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Churches, which the Apoſtle ſets down as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort for us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 16. Conſider now, Have not the Churches the keys of the Kingdom, and power on earth to looſe us from all thoſe black aſperſions you caſt upon us? have ſpirits judgement to try the ſpirits; and not Churches judgement to try the Churches? Shall he be counted a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican and Heathen that ſleights the judgement of a particular Church, and not he much more that ſleights the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Churches? Conſider what you do, beloved, and lift not up ſo bold a face and voice againſt the verdict of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114723:23"/> all the reformed Churches in the world: but if you will, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what was ſaid, You engage againſt the hand of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Providence, and have juſt cauſe to fear ſome ſtrange judgement will fall from heaven, to ſtop your mouths alſo, as it hath other of our enemies before you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. IIII. <hi>That the Miniſtery of the Churches of</hi> England, <hi>are the Miniſtery of Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ARe our Churches Churches of God and true Churches? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concluſ.</hi> 3.</note> then hence it further follows that we conclude, <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of our Churches is the Miniſtery of God and the true Miniſtery;</hi> for where can we think or imagin, the Miniſtery of God, the true Miniſtery ſhould be, but where the Churches of God, the true Churches are? and now had we nothing elſe to commend us unto you (unleſs you recede from your own principles) you cannot deny us a lawfull Miniſtery, who have <hi>call</hi> and allowance from <hi>true</hi> Churches.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall a little enlarge my Argument (which ſhall yet be but one, though of many parts,) and prove our Miniſtery thus unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Miniſters of our Churches in</hi> England <hi>muſt needs be the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Arg. in generall, to prove our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</note> 
                  <hi>lawful Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they have as much to make and manifeſt them ſo to be, as their very Adverſaries themſelves either have or allow and pretend unto; and over and above, what ever elſe their adverſaries want, and any other reaſonable men may require more: together laſtly with what the very Scripture it ſelf doth require, or hath ſet and left, as a canon or rule for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and diſcovering the lawfull Gospel-Miniſtery by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the making good hereof I am to clear three things, <note place="margin">The parts of the Argument.</note> 1. That our Miniſters have that to make, and manifeſt them true Miniſters, that is agreeable to the principles of their very <hi>adverſaries;</hi> and this being found will eaſily carry us above <hi>contradiction.</hi> 2. To the principles of all other indifferent men. 3. To the principles and rules of the Word of God:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114723:24"/> which two laſt being cleared and proved, may ſerve I think for full ſatisfaction.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>Firſt then, let us ſee what theſe buſie men have, or rather would have, that deny our Miniſtery, and proclaim them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <note place="margin">1. From princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</note> to our people as the only lawfull Miniſtery, in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like preaching: let us examine the manner, and theſe men a little; and we ſhall ſee their boaſting vain, for they have no more in <hi>pretence</hi> then we have <hi>really:</hi> they acknowledge they have (and plead for) no more to give them a call, then themſelves acknowledge many of us have: there is doubtleſſe very much in this, let us ſearch it a little.</p>
                  <p>There are but four things left (ſince the men for ſhame have laid down their claim and pretence to a call immediate <note place="margin">Who lay claim to four things.</note> and extraordinary) that all of their party together profeſſe to have any influence upon their call; and we ſhall finde them all four agreeing with us, though ſcarce any of them lay claim to them all, onely ſome of them to one, and ſome to another. 2. Of them are inward, a ſecret impulſe and gifts. The other two are outward, and are the choice and deſire of the people.</p>
                  <p>Some of them ſay, truth is like a fire in them; they cannot hold ſire in their breaſts and not be burnt; it will have vent, <note place="margin">1. An inward impulſe.</note> it burns in their bowels, inflames their tongues, they muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what things they have heard and ſeen: O brave, is this your plea for offering up of your ſtrange fire, that hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd and almoſt conſumed the Churches of Chriſt? Is there no other way to vent the truth (if you know ſuch a thing as truth) but from a pulpit? to ſet up your fire as a Beacon on a hill, to make a greater combuſtion among us? however my friends, conſider a little, doth this give you a call? how can you then deny ours? do you think that none of our Miniſters can ſay from their hearts the love of <hi>Christ conſtrains us:</hi> and woe is me <hi>if I preach not the Gospel?</hi> if ſo, then let that firſt plea fall to the ground, or elſe give us leave to be preachers as well as your ſelves.</p>
                  <p>2. Some of them, and truly the chiefeſt of them pleade their <note place="margin">2. Gifts.</note> gifts for calling: they are not, they ſay, ſince God hath light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114723:24"/> their candle for them, to put it under a buſhell, but on the houſe top (upon the mention of thoſe things I cannot but ſay a word unto them, though their anſwer is reſerved for their proper place) to ſuch I ſay, Cannot the ſtarres ſhine and glitter, unleſſe they do manage the Chariot of the Sun? My Brethren, have you gifts, as you ſay? be humble and thankfull, have grace in your hearts, as well as gifts in your heads; truſt me then you would know your ſelves, your gifts, and places better; yea. and ſhine more too, to the benefit of others: for we are not the better for the light of the ſtars while the Sun ſhines: be not angry though I call you ſtarres, for your own hearts ſmite you, ſaying, Your greateſt light was borrowed from us; which may be my Apology if I boaſt not when urg'd of our own gifts: however ſuffer me to beg this queſtion of you, what one gift have you wherein the Miniſtery you ſo much blame excell you not? unleſſe it be in boldneſſe and out-braving confidence? there are two great gifts the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in a Goſpel-Preacher, <hi>a being apt to teach, and able to convince gain-ſayers:</hi> the firſt implying <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> the laſt <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick;</hi> both which you call Antichriſtian, and diſclaim as <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate;</hi> certainly brethren, if you are apt to teach, then the old rule fails <hi>(qui benè diſtinguit benè docet;)</hi> for you are the worſt at diſtinguiſhing that ever I knew any (though indeed too cunning to divide) you cannot diſtinguiſh between extraordinary and ordinary ſending; between inviſible and viſible Churches: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween private and publike pteaching; ſtill apt to miſtake the one for the other, and errour for truth too often; how then are you apt to teach? the rule is, he that is good at diſtinguiſhing is good at teaching; but you are not able to diſtinguiſh well, and therefore not able to teach well, yea, you are not able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh at all, and therefore not fit to teach at all, nor is it indeed fit you ſhould: the Apoſtle means by <hi>[apt to teach]</hi> an aptneſſe of habit, not of exerciſe; an ability and fitneſſe, and not a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity and proneneſſe to be teachers: now whether you allow the firſt to us or no, the latter of theſe we cannot deny you, who are in this ſenſe ſo apt to teach, that truly you <hi>Run before you are ſent:</hi> and are you better able to convince gainſayers? let your publike diſputes throughout the Land be a witneſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114723:25"/> between us: though we need not ſo much ſince your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions declare againſt you, while you openly declare you are enemies to, becauſe ignorant of the very rules of diſpute, which gainſayers walk by, for how can you then convince them?</p>
                  <p>3. Others among them fly to the <note n="*" place="margin">Election of the people.</note> choice <hi>of true believers,</hi> for the proof of their call: they are, they ſay, elected to preach by precious, choice and holy people, whoſe call they cannot but <note place="margin">3. <hi>Ames</hi> himſelf ſaith thus, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus in judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cando dirigi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, ac ordinariè debet a judicio aliorum paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum electionem vel praeeunte vel comitante.</hi> Cont. Bell. p. 96.</note> hear and anſwer: but as this can never create a Miniſter in a ſetled Church, ſo is it greateſt arrogance for you to claim it, with defect in charity or exceſſe in impudence to deny it us: yea we have this choice priviledge of you, in that we are elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both by <hi>Miniſter and people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Others of them mention the deſire of the people, as giving them a call; then theſe <hi>Itineraries</hi> muſt have as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calls as Sermons almoſt; for if their call conſiſts of the peoples deſire, ſo often as they move to another place where they were not before, they muſt have a new call, or elſe preach there without a call, for the former people do not deſire, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">4. The peoples deſire.</note> therefore call them to preach to others, but to themſelves; however, can you ſay, that you have this call, and dare you ſay, that we have it not? Alas! Every one knows, if you do, the publique proceedings of the preſent Authority, and ſtate of things, will give you the lye; for none are inducted into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place according to the Rule and Order of Parliament uſually, but ſuch as are choſen, deſired and petitioned for by their people, provided they be capable of ſuch a priviledge; beſides, that <hi>deſire</hi> and invitation to be preachers they have from their <hi>friends</hi> and acquaintance, which is all for the moſt part that any of you can plead or challenge.</p>
                  <p>Now conſider, I beſeech you, is not this all that you can ſay <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the firſt branch of the Argument.</note> for your ſelves, and can you deny us any part of it? nay, dare you ſay, that in thoſe very things we have not the advantage? How then, I pray you, is it, that you ſpeak ſo boldly, that you rail ſo frequently, publikely, bitterly againſt us? and tell the people with all confidence, <hi>That you are the men that are called and ſent by God himſelf to preach the Goſpel, and that we have no call at all;</hi> Have you one grain more? yea, have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114723:25"/> you not many grains leſs then we, in theſe very particulars your ſelves boaſt of? I beſeech you, <hi>in the name of God,</hi> conſider this, and let it for ever ſtop thoſe mouthes that preach ſo much againſt our call; that they either preach no more who have no better call, then what they condemn; or elſe preach no more againſt our call to preach, who have the very ſame in every particular that themſelves either have, or allow, or pretend unto.</p>
                  <p>But here we muſt part, you can go no further in the way of a call: We muſt ſtep further, for aſſure your ſelves, <hi>Had we no better call to preach then you pretend unto, we durſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thereupon, as you do, in a ſetled Church:</hi> But I paſs on, to ſhew wherein we <hi>excel</hi> you, and what warrant we have above you; for we have yet behinde over and above what any other reaſonable indifferent men, and the word of God it ſelf requires: To which we proceed for your further (and if poſſible full) ſatisfaction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SEC. II.</head>
                  <p>Now there are four other things which may be required <note place="margin">The ſecond part of the Argument. Four other things the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters have which their adverſaries want.</note> for the warrant of our preaching by other men; all which will be found to commend our Miniſtery to you, as the want of the ſame will very much diſparage, if not wholly condemn the preaching of others.</p>
                  <p>The firſt particular of them, is, <hi>humane learning;</hi> this our adverſaries allow us to have, who do not ſo much for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall part of them as pretend unto it: and be not now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, beloved, to ſuffer <hi>that little</hi> we have of it to commend <note place="margin">Humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> us ſo far above them that want it. O but alas! you abuſe it, ſay they: ſo beloved do you your gifts, and muſt you therefore deſpiſe and reject them? I pray you, examine, doth not your knowledge puffe you up that lifts you ſo high as the pulpit, and higher yet in your own conceit and vain-boaſting? this I am certain of, that if we do abuſe learning, you abuſe both it and us much more: (I ſpeak not here of your undervaluing, but ſlandering both:) while you ſay of learning it is Antichriſtian, an Idoll, and I know not what: and while you deceive the hearts of the people, by a bold and more ſlanderous perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114723:26"/> of them that we ſay, None may preach, unleſſe he comes f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om the Univerſity, that all our calling lies in our learning: which things you your ſelves either do or might know we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; we do not ſay, beloved, that humane learning doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power, but <hi>enable</hi> to preach: it doth not make us <hi>Miniſters</hi> (for that I ſhall ſhew you anon, we have by Ordination ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word) but <hi>able Miniſters.</hi> Beloved, do not think that humane learning is an enemy to God, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> outward <hi>bleſſing</hi> of this life, it being not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nox<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous to the <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Omnia mea mecum porto.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>worlds violence</hi> as all other outward bleſſings are, and ſo neerer to <hi>grace.</hi> Think not humane learning is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth, which the God of truth himſelf hath made ſo much, and ſuch honourable uſe, in all ages, of, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his truth unto the world: Conſider the penmen of holy Scripture, and to whom among them, if it be ſafe to make ſuch a compariſon, are we moſt beholding? and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether they had not the benefit of humane learning. As for <hi>Moſes,</hi> that publike Miniſter and honourable penman of the very <note n="*" place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are but expounders of the Law. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                     </note> theme and ground of the old Teſtament, he was learned in all the learning of the Egyptians: as for <hi>Solomon, Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> (to mention no more) whoſe <hi>Songs, Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> and <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> you value above all the reſt of the Bible; had not theſe, all of them, the gift and bleſſing of humane learning? <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of men, the greateſt <hi>Philoſopher</hi> that ever was, who writ from the Cedar to the Iſop that growes upon the wall: <hi>Iſaiah</hi> bred up at the Court, and had by his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſion the <hi>tongue of the learned:</hi> and who know's not that <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>bred up at the feet of Gamaliel?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are three parts of humane learning that are judg'd <note place="margin">Three parts of humane learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judg'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for a Divine.</note> expedient to make a Miniſter ſuch a workman as needs not be aſhamed; <hi>Hiſtory, Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Arts,</hi> and theſe only ſo far as they are <hi>neceſſary helps for true underſtanding</hi> and expounding the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is our <hi>onely text</hi> to preach upon: I do not ſay we have all theſe ſo far as we ſhould, yet this I ſay, that ſo far as we want them, ſo far we are <hi>workmen that had need be aſhamed;</hi> and thoſe that have attained a ripeneſs in them, are the more to be commended and honoured, by how much the more they are fitter for their work thereby. 1. For <hi>History,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Hiſtory.</note>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:114723:26"/> the <hi>ſtory of the Bible</hi> commends that to us, and not only in it ſelf but <hi>in other hiſtories,</hi> beſides it ſelf, without which truly the hiſtory of the Bible, nor Prophecies, nor Promiſes, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our times, can well, if at all, be underſtood. 2. For <hi>Arts,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Arts.</note> we require no more then may ſerve to anſwer the Apoſtles <hi>precepts</hi> before named, that a man that deſires the <hi>office of a Biſhop</hi> be able to <hi>convince gainſayers, and apt to teach;</hi> which cannot, indeed, as experience proves in theſe times of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acquiring abilities be gained and had without competent acquaintance with <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick.</hi> 3. And laſtly for <note place="margin">3. Tongues.</note> 
                     <hi>Tongues,</hi> I only deſire you to think with your ſelves, how it had been poſſible for Apoſtles themſelves to have <hi>kept</hi> their commiſſion, and <hi>preacht to all nations,</hi> as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. unles they had had <hi>the gift of languages:</hi> and whether the gift of tongues be ſuch a contemptible thing as you make it, if acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which we ſee God made (when inſpir'd) the great <hi>gospel miracle,</hi> and means for the tranſplanting his Church from the <hi>Jew to the Gentiles?</hi> withall, how your ſelves (your ſelves may conſider) would ever have enjoy'd the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of it, ſo much as you do, had you not been beholding to the <hi>humane learning</hi> of other men for it.</p>
                  <p>Yea, my brethren, if you recollect, you may eaſily remember <note place="margin">All which three the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe partee had occaſion to uſe in their diſpute at <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſcomb.</hi>
                     </note> that ſenſible experience ſhew'd you the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>need</hi> of all three, at that one [late] conference with us at <hi>Wiviliſcombe:</hi> where your ſelves had occaſion to quote the <hi>Original:</hi> to retire to the ſtate of our Churches in <hi>England</hi> for <hi>many years agon:</hi> and alſo to diſpute in <hi>form and method;</hi> which if you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, above a thouſand of people I ſuppoſe will for you: and which, if you remember, me thinks, ſhould poſſeſs you with better conceit of humane learning in all its parts, of <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, Tongues</hi> and <hi>Arts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſecond particular that the eyes of men may look upon, <note place="margin">2. Allowance of all the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches in the world.</note> and ſee in us, and not in you; is of great weight, and is this; that we are <hi>members</hi> of, and allowed lawfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> by a <hi>true</hi> Church, yea, and by <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> in the world. Then how can your <hi>blaſt</hi> poſſibly <hi>hurt,</hi> or your <hi>pretences reach</hi> or equall us; when alas poor men, you are neither <hi>members</hi> of, nor <hi>allowed</hi> lawfull Miniſters, by any one <hi>true</hi> Church, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114723:27"/> have been condemn'd, and ſilenc'd, by the verdict of all the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> that ever were.</p>
                  <p>I ſay, you are no members of a true Church; becauſe you <note place="margin">They are not ſo much as members of particular, Nor of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church.</note> have rent your ſelves, by dangerous <hi>ſchiſm,</hi> from all the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches</hi> in the world: Beſides, you are not in the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal viſible Church:</hi> for why? you were indeed, but by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing your Baptiſm,</hi> you are again gone out of the <hi>door</hi> of that Church alſo: poor ſouls, you little imagine, of what <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> conſequence, the renouncing of the ordinance of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm is, which was in due time adminiſter'd to you in a true <note place="margin">Much leſſe Miniſters.</note> Church, by a lawfull Miniſter; for the bare repeating of it, by one that is neither a Miniſter nor member of the true Church. O which way, can you then become true Miniſters? or be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſo to be by any lawful Church? out this ſhould ſeem to be according to your principles, which is ſo agreeable to many of your practices; I mean, to be Preachers before you are Chriſtians: there are two fellows, within our knowledge here, within a few miles of this place, that were publike preachers, (and one of them to my knowledge hath taken a Church, a Pariſh, a Pulpit upon him, for a long time,) and yet were not rebaptiz'd (though long before againſt Infant-baptiſm) till about a moneth ago: I do not affect to relate ſuch ſtories, but the paſſage was ſo full to my preſent purpoſe, though ſo groſs and ridiculous, I could not hanſomely leave it out.) Then no wonder if all Chriſtian Churches and Chriſtian Councils re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and condemn ſuch unworthy preachers as you are; while we have the commendation, allowance, and liking of all the reformed Churches in the world, and may commend our ſelves to you and to all people elſe, without vainglory, as <hi>judged worthy by the spirits of the Prophets, whom all the Churches of Chriſt ſalute,</hi> a thing not ſleighted by modeſt men.</p>
                  <p>A third particular that men may juſtly look for in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <note place="margin">3. A being fixed and ſetled in the Church. 1. In place.</note> of the Goſpel is, that they be <hi>fixt and ſetled:</hi> and this may commend the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> above their <hi>oppoſers,</hi> who are not fixt either with regard to <hi>place or time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. With regard to place; we are fixed ſtars in the hand of Chriſt, having our ſtation and place in the body of the Church; every one knowing his particular people and flock, over
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114723:27"/> which <hi>he is made an over ſeer:</hi> while ſince the Apoſtolicall times, ſuch a <hi>ſteering, Miniſtery</hi> was never known, in a ſetled Church not under perſecution that could make a lawfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, for our wandering Comets, theſe itinerary ubiquitarian oppoſers of ours.</p>
                  <p>Indeed a ſetled Church of Chriſt may ſometimes appoint <note place="margin">Note.</note> ſome able men (whom with ſafety and prudence they may) to preach the Goſpel among the <hi>heathens:</hi> or upon ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table exigence, and want of Miniſters, in a <hi>true Church;</hi> that might bear the name and perform the Office of Itinerary Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: yet in ſuch an extraordinary caſe as this, theſe men ſhould be <hi>ſent</hi> by the Church, and have their <hi>bounds</hi> and limits too. But <hi>our Itineraries</hi> are without all <hi>order, bounds and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> but what they allow to themſelves, and never remember themſelves to be in a <hi>conſtituted Church,</hi> wherein indeed though the labourers be <hi>few,</hi> yet is there no ſuch extraordinary need of <hi>ſuch</hi> preachers as <hi>they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. We are fit in regard of time, while they (in all ages that <note place="margin">2. Of time.</note> have known ſuch men) have riſen and fallen, riſen and fallen, riſen and fallen, like the proud inconſtant waves of the ſea in a ſtorm, raving, raging, roaring and daſhing againſt the rock the Church (the fixt and abiding foundation of our houſe) untill they daſhed themſelves to pieces, <hi>fiaming out their own ſhame,</hi> and fretting and chaſing themſelves away into ayr and nothing: while the Church of Chriſt, and the ſetled Miniſtery hath <hi>ſtood as mount Sion that cannot be moved</hi> throughout both <hi>ſtorms and ages.</hi> The Scripture doth more then allude to the difference in hand, deſcribing <hi>them</hi> thus; <hi>falſe prophess ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 28.</note> but the lawfull Miniſters of the Goſpel thus; <hi>He hath ſet them in the Church.</hi> 1. Falſe prophets ſhall <hi>ariſe,</hi> (i.) <hi>actively a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 3. 1 Joh. 4. 1.</note> of their own accord raiſing up themſelves; while the true ones are <hi>paſſive, ſuch as the Lord God ſhall raiſe upto us.</hi> Like to this is that other expreſſion, <hi>there are many falſe prophets</hi> gone <hi>out,</hi> of their own accord, <hi>running</hi> before they are <hi>ſent:</hi> while the true ones ſtay for Commiſſion and miſſion, for how ſhall they preach except they be ſent, yea and thruſt out too ſometimes? 2. Falſe prophets ſhall <hi>ariſe</hi> (i.) from <hi>beneath:</hi> while the true ones with <hi>Paul</hi> have their call <hi>from Heaven,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114723:28"/> come down from above, as <hi>Eliah</hi>'s mantle, and the <hi>gifts</hi> and bleſſings of Chriſts <hi>Aſcenſion.</hi> 3. Falſe prophets <hi>ſhall ariſe</hi> (i.) of a <hi>ſudden</hi> and unexpectedly, while the true ones God hath <hi>ſet</hi> (i.) <hi>fixt, poſuit,</hi> hath placed in the Church, to the end they <note place="margin">Eph. 4. Mat. 28. 20.</note> may abide by the bleſſing of his preſence, and fellowſhip with them, <hi>to the end of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now let it be ſuppoſed that the ſcale is even in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, yet doubtleſs there's ſomething of weight in this in the balance of reaſon indifferently carried: for who doth not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue ſtaid conſtancy, before uncertainty? upſtart novelty may pleaſe the vulgar, while the old and ſtanding truth will onely ſatisfie ſolid men.</p>
                  <p>The fourth and laſt particular thing I ſhall mention here, that men may expect in the Preachers of the Word in a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Allowance and order from a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</note> 
                     <hi>Common-wealth, is allowance and order from the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate:</hi> Which we have, and you have not: you know well enough that the Laws of the Land, and two Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Parliament <hi>never yet repealed,</hi> are againſt you; ſo that the diſorderly practice of publick preaching by men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is is a <hi>breach of the Laws</hi> of the Land, which is manifeſt ſin by the Word of God, unleſſe the ſame word doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to do what the Magiſtrate forbids, which I am ſure you cannot, and think you dare not offer to prove: but as for us, the ſetled Miniſtery of Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> 'tis known to the world, we are own'd and authoriz'd by the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, which is more my brethren, for the clearing of our call in a Chriſtian Common-wealth then you imagine; yea, that ſomething is neceſſarily to be done by the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate for the full and regular Ordination of Miniſters, is jointly agreed on, both by <hi>Calveniſts</hi> and <hi>Lutherans, Prala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Presbyterians;</hi> and <hi>Ames</hi> the head of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall way: and certainly ſuch as deny it, are in this particular no good friends to Miniſters or Magiſtrates, to make ſuch a diſtance betwixt them: <note n="*" place="margin">Caution. The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters regular call.</note> but take heed, I ſay, not the power of ordaining is held by them, or by us, to lie in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates hands, yet they and we ſay, that in a Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, ſomething belongs to the Magiſtrate to do, in order thereunto: the Lutherans whom you applaud ſo much
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114723:28"/> for the making of a full and regular ordination, Place ſome-what in the hands of all the three Orders, Claſſes, or Eſtates, (as they term them) <hi>viz.</hi> the Miniſtery, Magiſtracy, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cura etiam us omuia</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters call) <hi>rectè ſiant, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet ac Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum,</hi> Ameſ. <hi>de conſu. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>num.</hi> 27.</note> and to the Miniſtery they give examination, ordination, and inauguration; to the Magiſtrate nomination, preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, confirmation; to the people conſent, ſuffrage, approving, or as circumſtances may require poſtulation: Not willing to give all to the Miniſter with <hi>Papiſts;</hi> to the Magiſtrate with <hi>Eraſtians;</hi> or to the people with <hi>Libertines, Anabaptiſts, Browniſts,</hi> &amp;c. and to the purpoſe <hi>Ameſius</hi> ſpeaks, who goes as far in this as we deſire, for <hi>the care that all things</hi> (ſaith he, touching ordination of Miniſters he means) <hi>be done rightly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe care and power doth contribute to us; and diſown you.</p>
                  <p>'Tis but vain to ſay, that this is to fetch our power from the earth, for we rather look on the favour of Magiſtrates and their aſſiſtance, as a plain performance of that Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. <hi>And Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and their Queens thy nurſing Mothers;</hi> which I know not how can come better to paſſe, then by their providing <hi>the ſincere milk of the Word</hi> for us.</p>
                  <p>Now thus far we are come, having ſtept beyond you four degrees into the approbation of indifferent men, we are found to have for our wartant in preaching what you have or allow, and over and above what may well be required by any other men: yet one thing remains of greater concernment then all the reſt: for further yet we excell you in this, that we have beſides what the Word requires either to make or manifeſt us true Miniſters, the ſum of the following Section.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>And we are not allowed true Miniſters only by our <hi>adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">We have what the Word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</note> 
                     <hi>principles,</hi> by our own Congregations, by all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in the world, and by a Chriſtian Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as hath largely been ſhewed, but by the <hi>Word of God</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; we having whatever the Word requires to make us Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or to evidence us ſuch. <note place="margin">1. To make us Miniſters.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have firſt, whatſoever the Word requires to make us
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114723:29"/> Miniſters, <hi>viz. Ordination according to the Word of God:</hi> now <note place="margin">The nature of Ordination.</note> that this may appear, I ſhall briefly unfold the <hi>nature</hi> of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-ordination of Miniſters; and for that end, I pitch on, and deſire you to turn to that of <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3. where we ſhall learn two things. 1. What the nature of Ordination is. 2. In whoſe hands the power of ordaining lies.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Ordination</hi> is deſcribed here with reſpect to its ſubſtance; and ſo it is a <hi>ſeparating,</hi> v. 2. or a <hi>ſending,</hi> v. 3. as alſo, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to its <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> v. 3. which are <hi>faſting and prayer, and laying on of hands:</hi> Now from both theſe we have this Rule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ordinary Goſpel-ordaining of Miniſters is a ſacred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating and ſetting them apart for the work of the Miniſtery, which ought to be ſolemniz'd, and diſtinctly ſignified by faſting and prayer, and laying on of hands.</hi> Concerning which I lay down theſe rules.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>This Ordination is more or leſſe neceſſary, the more or leſſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rules touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                     <hi>the means thereof may be had.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Therefore it is not ſimply neceſſary, or with a neceſſity of means, as if in no caſe a man might be made a Miniſter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Yet it is neceſſary,</hi> ſecundum quid, <hi>by Apoſtolicall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Whole Ordination is of neceſſity required in a conſtituted Church, on the Ordainers part, not on the part of the perſon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi> I mean, though God requires they obſerve his rule in ordaining, yet the omiſſion of ſome circumſtances doth not null the ſubſtance of any ordination had without them: upon this Rule, <note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Seaman In talibus non eſt aliquid ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum,</hi> ſaith a Canon of the Papiſts themſelves. Note. Becauſe <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> place ſo much in a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</note> the <hi>edification of the Church is ſo neceſſary that it muſt be endeavoured as providence makes way:</hi> and I had rather have the ſubſtance only, <hi>viz. a ſetting apart by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters authoriz'd thereto by the Civill Magistrate, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other convenient ceremonies; then to have full Ordination, both ſubſtance and ceremonies from men not allowed by publike Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>We muſt then diſtinguiſh betwixt the ſubſtance and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Ordination; and then we ſay, that the ſubſtance which I take to be neer the ſame with vocation, is far more neceſſary then</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:114723:29"/> 
                     <hi>the circumſtance of fasting, and prayer, and impoſition of hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>The ſubſtance of Ordination is abſolutely neceſſary to make a Miniſter a lawfull Paſtor to any particular flock; though not ſo, to licence a mans teaching to heathens out of a Church:</hi> for ſuppoſe the higheſt caſe: a company of Chriſtians are caſt upon the ſhore among heathens, and there is no returning for them to the true Church again: one of theſe may be made Paſtor and overſeer to the Church none doubt; but how? it muſt be by the calling of the reſt, whereby they ſeparate him for the work, which is the ſubſtance of <hi>Ordination;</hi> and without the ſame no man among them may <hi>take that honour unto himſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All theſe ceremonies of Ordination are to be gladly received,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The neceſſity of impoſition of hands in ſome reſpects, either for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſake or to avoid ſcandal, is acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by theſe Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines who make leaſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands. M. <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> p. 74. Note. Our Ordination is ſuch as the word holds out.</note> 
                     <hi>when they may be had and readily ſubmitted to, not as the practice but the plain inſtitution of the bleſſed Apoſtles; and that that therefore will render a mans call into the Miniſtery moſt clear from ſcandall or any touch of offence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Rules I doubt not, to lay before you as the <hi>concluſions of Proteſtant Divines,</hi> and very much favoured by holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which would eaſily appear, ſhould I not exceed the bounds of a Sermon.</p>
                  <p>Now as theſe do keep the middle way 'twixt Papiſts (uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the abſolute neceſſity of Ordination in all caſes) and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> that deny it to be any way neceſſary at all: ſo do they allow and maintain the lawfullneſſe of out Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and calling to the Word of the Miniſtery, both now and heretofore in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> being no other but what is moſt clearly and evidently gathered from the Text be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, this <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 2, 3. with many other places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> But how ſhall we know that the way of ordaining in the text is the ordinary way for the Churches of Chriſt to walk in, ſince the perſons ordained ſeem to us to be extraordinary men, <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas and Paul?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> That very thing proves it: for if both theſe men had a call <hi>extraordinary</hi> before: this their call then, muſt needs be <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> was ordinary.</note> which is more plain too, if we conſider the work is the <hi>work</hi> of ordinary Miniſters hereunto they are called, <hi>viz.</hi> to preach, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. and to ordain others, <hi>cap.</hi> 14. 23. they having an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114723:30"/> call before, that need not be repeated; but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſent about the work of ordinary Officers; they have therefore moreover an ordinary call and Ordination confer'd, as a Rule for the practice of ſuceeding Churches to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>2. If we doubt of the meaning of the Text, let us weigh and conſider its interpretation in the practice of the Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches afterwards, as alſo of all the Churches of Chriſt ſince thoſe daies; for the practice of both doth undoubtedly conclude that this was ordinary Ordination: but the doubt lies not touching the practice of future Churches; for that's without doubt, that all the Records of former Churches ſince the Apoſtles mention <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nos enim</hi> (ſai. h <hi>Tarno.</hi> of the buſineſs in hand) <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onamus ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid, nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quia citra ſcandalum omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti hodiè non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, qui tot annos in eccleſiâ ufita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuit.</hi>
                     </note> no other Ordination but this: and though this hath much weight in it doubtleſſe, and nothing leſſe then preſumption will offer to queſtion the uninterrupted practice of the Churches through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages, ſince the primitive times yet let us conſider, Was it not ſo alſo from the beginning? do we reade of any other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in the Primitive Churches but this? Did not <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ordain others in the ſame manner? <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 23. Did not <hi>Paul</hi> charge <hi>Timothy</hi> with the ſame order, (the negative command containing an affirmative) when he ſaid, <hi>Lay hands ſuddenly on no man,</hi> 1 Tim. 5, 22? and did not the Apoſtles take the ſame courſe in <hi>Act.</hi> 6?</p>
                  <p>Indeed, the Scripture ſpeaks more careleſly of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <note place="margin">Note.</note> of it; in ſome places taking no notice of one, nor in ſome, of another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though we cannot thence argue they were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and all that we can gather from ſuch a non-mentioning of them, is this, that the Ceremonies ſeem to be of weaker neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity then the ſubſtance of our call, which is ſtill moſt carefully noted and expreſſed by the holy Ghoſt in every place, that men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions any thing of Ordination; by the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> I mean here as before, <hi>a ſolemn ſeparating and ſetting apart</hi> by the Church for the work of the Miniſtery: but however, unleſſe you can ſhew us ſome place of Scripture where this way of Ordination by faſting and prayer, and laying on of hands, is forbidden, or where another way or courſe is appointed and uſed? we may not ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lay aſide the old, much leſſe preſume to invent a new: alas! what harm or danger is there in faſting and praier? the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114723:30"/> Chriſtian means to ſolemnize and ſpeed an important buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? or in laying on of hands; whoſe three uſes in Scripture <note place="margin">Gen. 48 14, 20</note> concurre and meet in ordaining Miniſters, <hi>viz. bleſſing,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Num. 8. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating, and ſetting apart</hi> unto an office.</p>
                  <p>So much for the <hi>nature</hi> of Ordination it ſelf, now follows the <note place="margin">Perſons or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining.</note> conſideration of the <hi>perſons</hi> in whoſe hands the power of ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lies.</p>
                  <p>Who are either <hi>principall</hi> (according to the Text) or <hi>miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Principall, the holy Ghoſt.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>principall</hi> perſon <hi>ordaining</hi> here, is the <hi>holy Ghost:</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whoſe act in this buſineſſe, the Text affords two expreſſions; the one before, the other after the <hi>mediate Ordination</hi> of the Church: the firſt, we have in <hi>ver.</hi> 2. the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>ſeparate me Barnabas and Saul</hi> for the work, whereunto <hi>I have called them.</hi> Whence we note.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That an inward or ſecret call by the holy Ghoſt is not enough, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>to the order and rule of the Goſpel, but requires for the regular making a Miniſter, the formall Ordination of the Church beſides.</hi> Or,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whom the holy Ghost doth call to be Miniſters, he doth hint to the Church to be ordained.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond expreſſion that diſcovers the finger of the holy Ghoſt here, we have (immediately after the Churches Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.) in ver. 4. ſo they being ſent forth by the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> Whence,</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Thoſe that be ordained according to the Rule by the Church of Chriſt, may be ſaid to be ſent by the holy Ghoſt: And when they hed faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them,</hi> they ſent them away; and the very next words, are <hi>v.</hi> 4. ſo they <hi>being ſent by the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. The <hi>Ministeriall</hi> perſons ſending or ordaining here, you <note place="margin">2. Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall ordinary teaching El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> have deſcribed in <hi>ver,</hi> 3. <hi>Such as miniſtred to the Lord,</hi> by office, <hi>Miniſters:</hi> and <hi>nam'd,</hi> verſ. 1. 1. From their Offices, Certain Prophets and Teachers. 2. By their proper names, <hi>Barnabas, Simeon, Lucius, Manaen, and Saul.</hi> Theſe were miniſtring, <hi>theſe</hi> were ſpoke to by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>the reſt faſted and prayed, and laid on their hands on Barnabas and Saul, and ſent them away.</hi> So then, the <hi>perſons ordaining</hi> here, were <hi>Prophets and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114723:31"/> which names do ſignifie their offices, and are in this place <hi>ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nimous,</hi> as <hi>Marlorat</hi> judgeth: mark then, they are not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to confute the Papiſt: nor yet can they be the body of the people without any Officers, to ſilence the Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the power of ordaining lies then in the hands of <hi>Prophets and Teachers:</hi> of ordinary <hi>teachers</hi> as well as of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Prophets, elſe it would have been ſaid, that the Prophets onely laid hands on them: yea, of Prophets, not as ſuch, but as they were <hi>Teachers</hi> (the greater ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the leſſe) for as we never finde that it was proper to <hi>Prophets,</hi> as ſo, to ordain; ſo nor as extraordinary Officers onely, for then Ordination had ceaſed with extraordinary Officers, which would gratifie the Seeker too much. Therefore it is ſaid both Prophets and Teachers, to intimate to us that Teachers and ordinary Officers have a ſtewardly power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, and Prophets, as <hi>ſupplying the place, and doing the office of ordinary Teachers,</hi> that are to ſucceed to the end of the world, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. Whence the note and Obſervation is,</p>
                  <p>That the power of ſending or ordaining Miniſters lies in the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obſerv.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>hands of ordinary Officers, as ſtewards of it:</hi> not in the hands of <note place="margin">Five Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove the power of Ordaining in the hands of ordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> Apoſtles only; not in the hands of the people, ordinarily; for which I ſhall but name five Arguments, two of which I hinted in the clearing of the Text.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the power of ordaining had lain in the hands of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trordinary Officers only, there had been no way left for the perpetuation of a Goſpel-Miniſtery, which Chriſt hath reſolv'd to continue in the world to the end thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If Teachers had power to ordain, then ordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers had power to ordain, for Teaches were ordinary Officers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>But Teachers we ſee in the Text, had power to ordain: <hi>Ergò.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If men, by vertue, and with and in their own Ordination, receive power to ordain; then ordinary Miniſters have power to ordain, for they are ordain'd. But men by vertue, and in and with their own Ordination, receive power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to ordain others; as appears abundantly, <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, this ſeems to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114723:31"/> in anſwer to ſecret Objections which the Apoſtles made againſt their call to preach the Goſpel: as if they had ſaid by what authority do or may we preach? why, do not doubt ſaies Chriſt, <hi>My Father ſent me, and in his ſending me he gave me Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to ſend others;</hi> As he ſent me, ſo I ſay, or by that, I had power to ſend you, and give you power to ſend others: He ſent me to preach and ordain, I ſend you to preach and ordain: and do you ſend others to <hi>preach and ordain,</hi> &amp;c. therefore we finde the Apoſtles executing their Commiſſion accordingly along, as occaſion requires. <hi>Paul</hi> ſends <hi>Timothy, Titus,</hi> &amp;c. bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them <hi>ordain:</hi> and ſo ſucceſſively to the end of the world: which thing is moſt plain in the Text we are upon, with regard to the perſons ordaining and ordained: Perſons ordaining are <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Teachers:</hi> and perſons ordained in this <hi>ordinary</hi> ſending what power receive they? they are ſent 'tis moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by an ordinary ſending, and what to do I pray you? why to preach <hi>ver.</hi> 5. and to <hi>ordain Elders</hi> in every Church, <hi>c.</hi> 13. 23. clearly intimating, that <hi>Ministers by their very Ordination have power to ordain as well as to preach.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>If a Presbytery have power to ordain, then ordinary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have power to ordain:</hi> for a Presbytery is nothing but a Colledge-combination or company of Presbyters or ordinary Miniſters. But a Presbytery hath power to ordain, for <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> was ordained by the laying on of the hands of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> But there were Apoſtles in theſe Presbyteries. </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> What if? this ſtrengthens the Argument if rightly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for if it was counted an act of the Presbytery when Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were there, it appears that the Apoſtles joyning with ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Elders, acted <hi>as Elders</hi> and not as <hi>Apostles</hi> or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers: there being Apoſtles in the Presbytery that doeth ordain, and yet Ordination is ſaid to be done <hi>by the Presbytery,</hi> cleerly ſhews, that Ordination is a <hi>proper act</hi> of an ordinary Presbytery, and not of Apoſtles as <hi>ſo;</hi> and to make it out of doubt, Ordination is defin'd in that text to be <hi>the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> But this hands me to another Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If ordinary Officers had a hand in Ordination in <hi>Apoſtles</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114723:32"/> 
                     <hi>times;</hi> much more and ſafer may they ordain, now there are no extraordinary Officers among us. The <hi>minor</hi> implied is already proved: and for the conſequence, I ſay, <hi>much more:</hi> but how ſo? why, becauſe <hi>(à pari) the people,</hi> where there are no Miniſters to do their work, have <hi>power to Ordain,</hi> by the warrant of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: then much more <hi>ordinary Miniſters</hi> may: now there are none extraordinary left, if they <hi>as ſo,</hi> had a hand in Ordination; by the like warrant and law of neceſſity. And now that that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms me about all doubting touching the Ordination of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers, is the <hi>practice of the primitive Churches,</hi> next the Apoſtles, and ſo down along, through all ages and Churches to this day, without interruption or contradiction, unleſs by a few inconſiderable men as the <hi>Seekers</hi> are.</p>
                  <p>Thus we have ſhew'd what Goſpel Ordination is, and in <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> whoſe hands the power of ordaining lies; <hi>it is a ſetting men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with faſting and prayer, and laying on of hands by preaching Elders:</hi> which is indeed in every jot and title of it, the very ſame with the Ordination allow'd and practic'd in the <hi>Church of England</hi> time out of mind. The <hi>additional Ceremonies, and harſh Oaths,</hi> are taken away, and we now have nothing left but <hi>pure Ordination according to the word:</hi> ſo that the <hi>word doth allow</hi> us lawfull Miniſters, becauſe we have what the <hi>word requires to make us ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> To ſay we were ordained by Biſhops, is not worth the while: for ſtill there were ordinary Presbyters joyned with them, and they themſelves were no more but ordinary Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, though they thought themſelves more: their <hi>thought could not add one cubit to their ſtature,</hi> whom neither Church nor State did ever declare to be a ſuperior Order to other Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But for this I refer you to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Seaman,</hi> who hath given five Anſwers to this very Objection; every one of which are ſo ſound and ſolid, that they are ſingle and apart from each other, abundantly ſatisfying. See <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 85.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> But the great Objection yet remains, <hi>viz.</hi> That we muſt needs be Antichriſtian, becauſe by a <hi>line of ſucceſſion</hi> we deſcended from Antichriſt: this indeed is all they have to ſay againſt our Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> There are two <hi>knots</hi> in the <hi>line</hi> of <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> of the Goſpel-Miniſtery
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114723:32"/> to our times: The firſt is, as it paſſeth the <hi>bounds</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles daies,</hi> and this the <hi>Seekers</hi> tie: but we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſſolved it. The other is, in the paſſage of it, from the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to the reformed Churches, as it lies in this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, <note place="margin">Four Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to cleer the ſucceſſion of Ordination.</note> made by <hi>Browniſts,</hi> Anabaptiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which I ſhall now untie; I ſhall touch but four <hi>Arguments</hi> (for I am in haſt) every of which experience hath proved very effectuall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I judge it a truth, not to be queſtion'd, that there hath been certain Miniſters of Chriſt in the world, ever ſince there were any: and more certain it is, that there were <hi>true Miniſters in the Church of Rome,</hi> when our firſt Reformers began to think of breaking off from her: for <hi>there was converſion there,</hi> elſe God <hi>would not have had a people there;</hi> and converſion is the work of <hi>ſent</hi> Miniſters, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14, 15. now can any man in reaſon think, that thoſe that forſook both <hi>Rome</hi> and her har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotry, and obey'd that known command of God, and <hi>come out from Rome,</hi> were not the <hi>beſt</hi> of the Miniſters there, and ſo by conſequence the Miniſters of Chriſt, if there were <hi>any,</hi> which may not be doubted? Yea therefore remarkeable providence did ſeal to their Miniſtery immediately, upon their leaving <hi>Rome,</hi> being uſed by God to preach that doctrine and preſſe that command, <hi>Come out of her my people:</hi> and to prevail with a great number to follow their ſteps and leave the whore. And when God by them had drawn his people into the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> he did feed them there by the <hi>ſame Paſtors, Rev.</hi> 12. 6, and 14. which helps me to conclude, that <hi>as the best of the members leaving Rome were owned by God for the true Church; ſo the firſt of the Miniſters leaving Rome, were acknowledged by God for the true Ministery, every man abiding in that calling wherein he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> whether members or Miniſters.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Again, It is not ſo much as queſtion'd, but that our firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers had an <hi>inward</hi> Call; and if their <hi>outward</hi> call be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd, it is no great matter, ſince both <hi>we</hi> and our <hi>adverſaries</hi> agree in this, that in ſuch a ſtrait and a caſe ſo <hi>extraordinary</hi> as that was, the people are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>chuſe and call</hi> a Miniſter; and theirs is <hi>valid,</hi> no man doubts, in ſuch a caſe; and therefore the Call of our firſt Reformers may not be queſtioned by our op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents any more, untill they leave their <hi>Principles,</hi> ſince it was <hi>confirmed</hi> by <hi>God</hi> and the Church.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:114723:33"/>
                  <p> But as to their <hi>outward Call</hi> receiv'd in <hi>Rome,</hi> there may be <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rome</hi> not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, before the Councel of <hi>Trent:</hi> though Antichriſtian, not wholly ſo.</note> more ſaid than you can Anſwer, and that is this, That <hi>Rome</hi> was not ſo far <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> then, but that ſhe had ſome of the Ordinances of the <hi>true,</hi> though not <hi>pure;</hi> and that though ſhe had plaid the Harlot before, yet ſhe had not an expreſſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute divorce till the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi> When ſhe by a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deliberate Councel diſ-own'd and razed the fundamentals of Religion, which ſhe had not done before: that that makes me of this mind is, <hi>Rome</hi> we ſay, <hi>was not built in a day,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The <hi>Myſterie of iniquity,</hi> that <hi>diſeaſe</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had its <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> was not at her height of ſin, till that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel.</note> before its <hi>ſtate:</hi> and ſo far its certain, that ſhe was not at her <hi>height,</hi> before this deadly and deſperate <hi>fit</hi> of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> as appears,</p>
                  <p>1. Becauſe thoſe groſſe <hi>fundamentall errours</hi> that are now ſo firmly laid in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and which carrieth ſo great a ſtroak in the <hi>ſeating</hi> of <note place="margin">Which appears becauſe there was never ſo many and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies decreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </note> Antichriſt <hi>there;</hi> were not only complained of, declaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by private ſingle Miniſters, both in their Preaching and Printing, but diſowned by <hi>Decrees</hi> made againſt the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of them by <hi>publick Counſels:</hi> and we do hardly read of any former <hi>Counſel,</hi> that did not onely not <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> all the Errors or the groſſeſt of the Errors of the Counſel of Trent; but that on the contrary did expreſſely declare againſt ſome one or more of the very worſt of them. There are ſix chief or <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> Errors of the Church of <hi>Rome, The Popes ſupremacie;</hi> the <hi>dividing of the Bread and Wine</hi> in the Sacrament; allowing the people no Wine: the <hi>Worſhipping of Images,</hi> the <hi>denyall of the Bible</hi> to the common people, <hi>Juſtification by works,</hi> and <hi>beleeving of Traditions.</hi> Now theſe <hi>ſix</hi> were never eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed together by any Councel, but the <hi>Councel of Trent.</hi> Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Popes Supremacie</hi> was decree'd <hi>againſt</hi> by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of <hi>Calcedon, Affrick, Milevi, Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Baſil.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Communicating in both kinds</hi> was decreed by the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Baſil,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The <hi>Divine Worſhipping of Images</hi> was forbidden in the ſecond <hi>Nicen Councel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. The <hi>Councel of Nice</hi> decreed, that <hi>no Chriſtian ſhould be without a Bible.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114723:33"/>
                     <item> 5. And <hi>Thomas</hi> an acknowledged writer of the Roman faith in his time, denieth <hi>Juſtification by works,</hi> Ceremoniall or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</item>
                     <item>6. And we were never bound or commanded to <hi>beleeve tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> untill the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> decreed it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now while <hi>Rome</hi> declared againſt, or had not by councel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed any one of theſe errours, ſure ſhe was not at ſuch a pitch of hereſie, or ſo deeply died with Antichriſtianiſm, as now ſhe is made by the councell of <hi>Trent;</hi> where they are all and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ratified as firm as hell can make them: yea, very much of Antichriſtianiſm was brought to <hi>Rome</hi> with the laſt of theſe errours touching tradition, which ſhe had not before the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Trent;</hi> for the Church is built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, the Scriptures: and what doth wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Scripture more, and conſequently the foundation of the Church more then making tradition (contrary to it) a compart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with it in the Churches faith? eſpecially, if we adde the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of originals; (the <hi>Greek and Hebrew</hi> Text) preferring the latin corruption above them: which was with ſuch ſtrictneſſe and weight impoſed by the <hi>Councel of Trent,</hi> and never before, <note place="margin">The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt Argument.</note> with the deniall of the vulgar to reade it. Now Phyſicians do not count a diſeaſe in its ſtate untill it have reigned to its full height: and therefore how to condemn the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as wholly Antichriſtian before <hi>Trent</hi> councel, I cannot ſee; the diſeaſe was daily encreaſing upon her, ſhe ſeemed not however to be at the <hi>height,</hi> or <hi>mortally</hi> ſick before: for from what hath been ſaid, the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> did deſperately wound the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in three reſpects.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>In that it did heighten and multiply her damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>In that it did draw all the poyſon into one entire monſter</hi> and body of errour, and preſented it all to the world as the doctrine of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In that theſe were more ſolemnly, ſeriouſly, deliberately, publikely, by the pretended <hi>repreſentative of the whole Church,</hi> as the <hi>work of years</hi> delivered, ratified, as the <hi>perpetuall</hi> doctrine of the Church: which made the <hi>errors rather the errors of Rome,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <hi>though many particular perſons were against, then if all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114723:34"/> of the Church of Rome had held the ſame apart,</hi> that is, <hi>without a councell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My ſecond Argument to prove, that <hi>Rome</hi> was not at the <note place="margin">Becauſe there were ſtrange mottions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in <hi>Rome</hi> before, and ſomewhat effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall.</note> ſtate or height of this her diſeaſe, till the <hi>Councell of Trent</hi> is taken from her ſtrange motions all along after Reformation; every age almoſt complained of abuſes in <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> and were ſo urgent and impetuous, that they prevail'd to have a councell cal'd; for to adviſe about a <hi>Reformation,</hi> and every councell before this laſt, for ought I can finde, did ſome good: and this very wicked councell, the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf was occaſioned by <hi>univerſall and potent</hi> complaints of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and errour: and ſuch was the power of the better people, that the malignant party were forc'd to yeeld, to call a counſell, on which there lay great hopes, being called indeed upon faireſt pretences: this I would inferre from hence, that God had not wholly caſt <hi>Rome</hi> off: who doth not leave <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> while and where there is any the leaſt appearance of hope, of which it ſeems there was not a little in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> till the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſecond Argument to prove that there might be ſomething <note place="margin">A ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that <hi>Rome</hi> was a true Church till the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Trent</hi> at leaſt.</note> of Chriſt in <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſhe was not wholly Antichriſtian, and no true Church, till the <hi>Councel of Trent;</hi> is taken from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of moſt of our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> in this thing: the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts moſt of them acknowledge that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> had true Baptiſm, and ſome of them (as <hi>Johnſon,</hi> &amp;c. held, they had true <hi>Ordination</hi> too: and ſuch as broke off from <hi>Rome,</hi> had not any need of the Repetition of either: Now let us conſider, could there be true and valid Ordinances in a Church, that was <hi>true in no respect?</hi> could there (do we think) be Ordinances of Chriſt, in a Church that was wholly Antichriſt? Suppoſe the Church of Turks ſhould <hi>baptize, In the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> were that true Baptiſm if not, then a difference muſt be made betwixt the Baptiſm of <hi>Rome</hi> and that: and if ſo, where lies the difference but in the Church? and what is the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, but that one is more, Chriſtian then another? and then there is granted ſome Chriſtianiſm, and not all Antichriſtianiſm in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and ſhe was, at leaſt, before that wretched Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> a Church of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114723:34"/>
                  <p> Now my concluſion hence is this, That if it be granted, that <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> 
                     <hi>Rome</hi> was a true (though wicked) Church, before the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Trent</hi> ſate, then our firſt Reformers had a lawfull out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward call, a lawfull Ordination unto the Miniſtery: for were not they ordained Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of a true Church? were not they ordained Miniſters <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reformatio Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiarum per</hi> Angliam, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1547. See more <hi>Sleid. de ſtatu Relig.</hi> pag. 599. l. 19.</note> by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> before the Councell of <hi>Trent?</hi> none can deny it: and then we have a known <hi>viſible ſucceſſion</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Office of the Miniſtery, from the Apoſtles times to this day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>None may object, That this is nothing to the Miniſtery of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for certain it is, that the Miniſtery of England (as may be remarkably obſerved) had their Ordination (if from Rome) before the Councel of Trent ſate; for they with the Church of England broke off from Rome, even while that councell ſate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider therefore theſe things. <note place="margin">Seven Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derables to clear the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our firſt Reformers in <hi>England.</hi> You may reade thoſe decrees in <hi>Sleidan.</hi> they were made <hi>An.</hi> 1539. as pag. 346. and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht <hi>An.</hi> 1547. as pag. 399.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf was a true Church, and her Miniſters true Miniſters before the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> ſate, and therefore much more the Churches in <hi>England</hi> were <hi>true Churches,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> thereof true Miniſters before that time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Churches and Ministery of England,</hi> in the time of that councell broke off from <hi>Rome,</hi> aboliſht her fatall <hi>decrees touching Religion,</hi> demoliſh't the images and ſtatues in the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and thus began the bleſſed Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> even then while <hi>Rome was declining towards Antichriſtianiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Who then can chooſe but ſee and know that our <hi>firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> had (I mean the Miniſters) their Ordination in a <hi>true Church,</hi> from <hi>true Miniſters?</hi> and we from them, unto this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, have had a ſucceſſion of lawfull Miniſters in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and upwards from them ever ſince we bore the name of a Church, which may I ſuppoſe be computed to be upwards of 1500. years.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Moreover might <hi>Rome</hi> be ſaid and acknowledged to be a true Church ſtill, though extreamly corrupted, yet could not this blame but commend our <hi>leaving of her;</hi> for we ſeparate not from her as a Church, much leſſe as <hi>true:</hi> but as a corrupt and <hi>Apoſtate</hi> Church: that is, we ſeparate from her corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from her only, as we cannot joyn with her, but we
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114723:35"/> muſt partake of her ſins and plagues: Juſt as the <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> who did not joyn in ſome acts of worſhip heretofore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not ſafely do it, without having communion with corruption in it; yet did not all the while diſown our Churches, or ſeparate from them, but in them only, as <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> diſtinguiſheth.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. But to cleer the matter a little further; conſider the Church as one <hi>univerſall viſible Church of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> to be but a <hi>member</hi> of it; and ſo far as the ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi> is Antichriſt, <hi>but ſitting in the Temple</hi> (or univerſall Church) <hi>of God;</hi> (for though ſhe would uſurp her ſelf to be the whole viſible Church, yet God accounts not ſo we ſee, for ſhe is but in the <hi>Temple</hi> of God, though ſhe would be as God there:) Now is it a ſin for one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church to deny communion with a <hi>ſiſter</hi> Church in thoſe things wherein ſhe offends, both God and other Churches? no, doubtleſſe; but a vertue rather, if one <hi>particular Church</hi> ſhould deny communion with the <hi>whole viſible Church</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſides her ſelf in ſuch a caſe. Now <hi>Rome</hi> of right, and in Gods account, is <hi>but a ſister,</hi> no <hi>mother Church,</hi> to the Church of <hi>England</hi> (what authority ſhe had over it was uſurp'd on her part, and utterly unlawfull (if yeelded to) on ours; Now had the ſiſter (in the word) denied to commit that folly with her <hi>brother,</hi> and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his hands by flying from him, ſhe <hi>had done virtuouſly;</hi> then alſo if <hi>England</hi> broke out of the hands of her ſiſter <hi>Rome,</hi> and would not commit that <hi>Adultery</hi> with her, ſhe hath praiſe of God for obeying his will and command, <hi>If a ſinner entice, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thou not:</hi> One particular Church bears ſome Analogy to another, like that of a member of a particular Church to another member of the ſame: two <hi>particular</hi> Churches are members of one <hi>univerſall;</hi> as two particular members are of one particular Church: Now therefore if a member of a particular Church muſt not partake of the ſin of another member; no more muſt one particular Church of the ſinne of another: Again, ſo a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church may not joyn with the ſinnes and corruptions of the univerſall; no more, then one member may joyn with the Church of which he is, in any ſinne or errour whatſoever. In <note place="margin">We leave <hi>Rome</hi> in two things.</note> two things the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is forſaken by us. 1. In <hi>her cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and ſuperiority of us;</hi> in neither of which without
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114723:35"/> ſinne and loſſe, could we joyn with her or yeeld unto her.</p>
                  <p>Now what hath been ſaid upon this particular, as it ſerves to pleade for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r lawfull diſtance to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though ſhe ſhould be found to be a true Church ſtill; ſo alſo, to maintain the practice of <hi>Luther,</hi> &amp;c. who left the Romane Church before that wretched Councel ſate, we ſo much ſpeak and complain of.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Nor can there be any thing of moment urg'd, from any <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption</hi> of Popery ſince; againſt our <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> or Churches in <hi>England;</hi> could it be granted that the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> did wholly and fully make <hi>Rome</hi> Antichriſt: for the Proteſtant Religion flouriſh'd from <hi>Henry the eighth's,</hi> through <hi>Edward the ſixth's</hi> to <hi>Queen Maries</hi> Reign: indeed ſhe made havock of the Churches: however, ſhe reign'd but four years and four moneths: and what of Popery ſhe brought among us, was by <hi>force,</hi> ſo that by Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> gentle commands, we eaſily <hi>redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> our ſelves to our <hi>former profeſſion</hi> of the Proteſtant truth: however what could this <hi>ſhort ſword</hi> effect, as to the <hi>cutting</hi> the line of ſucceſſion of true Miniſters? none can think that all were butchered, but that many of our Miniſters and people too did <hi>temporize throughout her Reign,</hi> not daring to ſuffer for the truth, ſecretly beleeved, though not openly profeſſed by them as by others: <note n="*" place="margin">And as to this worſt of the caſes; <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt himſelf helps us: ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, that in caſe of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry (in the time of the Law) the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites and Prieſts that had revolted, upon Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance kept their firſt fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions without any new a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing or impoſition of hands: and for this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quotes many Texts.</note> Again, many other Miniſters <hi>might be blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> and <hi>fall away in time of perſecution for advantage ſake;</hi> who yet being ordained (before Queen <hi>Mary)</hi> lawfull Miniſters, might out-live both her and Popery, and come over again to preach the truth, for which they were firſt ordained. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and chiefly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> many that could not turn from the truth in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> practice, were known to fly for ſafety hence to other Churches beyond the Seas, where they remain'd in the day of our calamity, but when it was once over, they returned to us to reduce our Churches, to reform our Miniſtery; and did with the gracious aſſiſtance of God, and the Queen, bring us back into the former Channell of Proteſtant profeſſion: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have freely (though ſometimes fouly runne) to this day.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But as for you, it may juſtly be feared, you came by a later
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:114723:36"/> and neerer paſſage from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though under ground. Firſt, None can doubt but we are as Full of <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Now, (who love rather to fiſh in <hi>pudled waters,</hi> where they, <note place="margin">Our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may be feared to have to do too much with Jeſuits.</note> nor their baits may be ſeen) as before theſe diſtracted, unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led times, when they were capable of <hi>gaining leſſe;</hi> and more liable to be <hi>diſcerned</hi> by us. Secondly, and if the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> be buſie among us (as no doubt they are) where and with whom are they likelieſt to be, with you or us? They cannot be thought to be among the Miniſters, for they are in a ſetled way, and known by all to be the Jeſuites ſworn enemies. Thirdly, but your diſorders, aptnes to receive any opinions, indiſcretion, &amp;c. doe indeed invite them to cloſe in with you. Fourthly, ye take it for certain, (though poor ſouls you ſee it not) you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of late, and been uſed by Jeſuites, to vent at leaſt <hi>twenty er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> for the <hi>Popes Advantage:</hi> which with little time and place convenient I could reckon up, and one among the reſt to the purpoſe in hand, <hi>That we are Schiſmaticks to the Church of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Coll.</hi> Pulpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard Routed,</note> 
                     <hi>Rome; and having unlawfully Rent our ſelves from her, we ought to return again unto her.</hi> Which leads me on to the laſt Anſwer to the old Objection againſt us; <hi>Becauſe we came by ſucceſſion from Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I Anſwer; Suppoſe what you will, that when we left <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe was a <hi>true</hi> or a <hi>falſe</hi> Church, we have yet a defence invincible (though I ſuppoſe each one of the former Anſwers are ſufficient ſatisfaction to men that will take it) it is this: I never heard or read of any that owned the name of a Chriſtian, (the Papiſt excepted) but did acknowledge, that <hi>Luther,</hi> and the reſt of our firſt Reformers, were <hi>lawfull Miniſters,</hi> whether their Call was an <hi>extraordinary,</hi> or an <hi>ordinarie</hi> Call. Now if ſo, Had not they power to ordain others? The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had no <hi>ordinary Call,</hi> yet they had power (as the greater) to ordain ordinarie Miniſters, and to <hi>confer</hi> an <hi>ordinary</hi> Call: yet they <hi>ordained ordinarily,</hi> and ſo did <hi>Luthrr,</hi> &amp;c. And from thence we have had a ſucceſſion of a regular ordination to this day: and thus (though as it is frequently uſed it wil not hold) the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>ratione Principii &amp; medii</hi> touching Ordination, is of great uſe: for when our firſt Reformers ordained others, <hi>they did not regard Ordination as the Channel of Rome had defiled</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:114723:36"/> 
                     <hi>and defaced it;</hi> but they fetch the manner of it from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, the <hi>Scripture, Apoſtolical Example, and Inſtitution;</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine of Ordination as in the Scripture was never toucht,</hi> though the <hi>practice</hi> of it in the <hi>Popes hands</hi> was very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; and that their <hi>practice</hi> is now nothing to us, that have <hi>reformed</hi> from it: our <hi>Reformers</hi> they were lawful Miniſters, and they reformed abuſes in Ordination too, according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and from them ſucceſſively hath it paſſed true (not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether pure ſometimes) to us: and what corruptions it received in Biſhops days, it is reformed from, of late alſo, and <hi>our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> is at this day, according to the <hi>Word</hi> in every thing: and therefore to conclude, we are, as I ſaid, <hi>true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus far then we have proceeded, namely, to prove the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of <hi>England</hi> to be of Chriſt, from our <hi>adverſaries own Principles,</hi> from the <hi>principles of any indifferent men;</hi> and laſtly from the grounds and principles of the <hi>Word:</hi> But from the Word we promiſed <hi>two things:</hi> Firſt, to make it appear that the Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> have whatſoever the <hi>Word</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to <hi>make</hi> them ſo: And this we have largely handled, and whatſoever the word requires to manifeſt them ſo: and this I ſhall as briefly touch.</p>
                  <p>If the Miniſtry be in queſtion, the Scripture gives us two <note place="margin">Our Miniſtrie manifeſted:</note> Rules to know it by: by which we are bound to try it, before we reject it.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is its <hi>fruit: By their fruit ye ſhall know them,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">1. From its Fruit.</note> our Saviour <hi>of falſe Teachers:</hi> By their fruit, that is, <hi>their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> you ſhall know them; that is, whether <hi>they be of God:</hi> which makes it evident that though we cannot clear a ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of perſons, yet as all that Wright againſt the Papiſts, hold a <hi>ſucceſſion of Doctrine</hi> is enough to evidence the true Miniſtrie: Suppoſe it be doubted where the Miniſtrie of Chriſt is, if it be but granted that he hath a <hi>Miniſterie</hi> ſomewhere in the world, it is eaſily concluded to be, <hi>where the Doctrine of Christ is preach'd:</hi> where can it be elſe? This I make a mark when there is juſt cauſe of ſcruple touching the Call of a preſent Miniſtrie: otherwiſe the very <hi>Ordination</hi> it ſelf when known, to be lawful, is a readier way to prove and clear a lawfull Call. Now <hi>we</hi> that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:114723:37"/> cannot be denyed to have <hi>both,</hi> have <hi>two ſtrings</hi> that the adverſe hand <hi>can never break.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other is taken from its <hi>effects;</hi> whereby God is pleaſed <note place="margin">2. Its effect.</note> to own his ſervants, and doe his work by them: <hi>Who is Paul, Who Apollos, but Miniſters by whom you believe?</hi> would you know who they are? obſerve their work, by them you come to <hi>believe,</hi> and then doe not queſtion but they are <hi>Miniſters:</hi> why ſo? Becauſe <hi>Faith is the gift of God,</hi> which he doth not uſually give but by his <hi>Miniſters</hi> hands: Miniſters by whom you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>as God gave every man;</hi> for how ſhall they beleeve on him of whom they have not heard; and how ſhall they hear that is ſo as to beleeve without a Preacher, a ſent Preacher? Whence we conclude, that ordinary Converſion wrought by our Miniſtrie is an infallible mark of the truth of our Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and that we are ſent by Chriſt, who do the work of Chriſt. I dare not ſay but a true and honeſt Miniſter may have <hi>cauſe to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <hi>complain, That he hath ſtretched forth his hands all the day long unto diſobedient and gain-ſaying people.</hi> Yet this I ſay, that he that is ſo happy in his labours as to convert ſome, and eſtabliſh more, is hereby declared from heaven, if queſtioned before to be both an able and lawful Miniſter: And further, he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to waſh a Black-more, to reform a people that <hi>hate to be reformed,</hi> and reaps no viſible fruit of his labours, he wants an apparent <hi>Seal to his Commiſſion,</hi> to make its <hi>authority</hi> known to ſuch as queſtion it: but this is our comfort, that we can ſay without boaſting (the Miniſtery of <hi>England</hi> in every age) can ſay to our Churches, to our Friends and Enemies, <hi>Ye are the Seal of our Apoſtleſhip,</hi> God hath Sealed our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in your <hi>Converſion</hi> and <hi>Confirmation,</hi> in your <hi>increaſe</hi> in knowledge, grace and comfort: in your <hi>perſeverance</hi> to the end, though through <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> when occaſion of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome</hi> or <hi>Perſecution</hi> hath called you to it: thanks be to God for ſo good a <hi>Seal</hi> both of your <hi>Redemption</hi> and our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> which the Devil or his Inſtruments ſhall never be able to <hi>Cancell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now conſider (in a word, and I have done with this) Can we (as I have ſhew'd) have the Ordination of Chriſt, and yet be Antichriſtian? Can we preach and uphold the Doctrine of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:114723:37"/> Chriſt, and be Antichriſtian? Can we (to conclude) doe the work of Chriſt, and yet be Antichriſtian? Truly, whom theſe things will not ſatisfie, I muſt leave unſatisfied.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. V. <hi>That they are guilty of a great ſin that preſume to preach without a Call.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus we are come to the fourth Concluſion: for if our Churches, as (we have proved) are true Churches, and the Miniſtery of them, true Miniſters (as our very adverſaries cannot but grant, if they will but acknowledge <hi>themſelves,</hi> or <hi>God;</hi> their own principles are Gods Word;) then <hi>there is a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ſin of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Preachers.</note> 
                  <hi>great and heavy ſin lying at the door of all ſuch as doe offer to preach publickly without a Call.</hi> What! Preach without a Call, in <hi>true</hi> Churches, that are bleſt with a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſetled Miniſtery!</hi> Was ever ſuch a thing heard or read of, that was not purſued and overtaken by ſome horrid <hi>judgement?</hi> O who can think of the ſad effects that this one piece of mad diſorder hath wrought upon this poor land of ours, without an amazed, blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding heart! it hath put the <hi>Foundations out of frame; and what can the righteous doe?</hi> But ſhall not God be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this? I wonder the <hi>earth</hi> doth not open <hi>again,</hi> and ſwallow both <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us</hi> up quick. Was not the ſin of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company juſt the very ſame with the ſin of theſe men? viz. <hi>A contemning of Gods Miniſters?</hi> and was not their plea the very ſame? <hi>viz. That all the Lords people are holy; the ſons of Levi, take too much upon them?</hi> Then, ô then, what pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is it, that bears up the earth under theſe men? that holds the heavens from falling upon them, and daſhing them down into hell? that they yet <hi>periſh not in the gain-ſaying of Corah?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there are ſpiritual <hi>judgem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts</hi> ſomewhat more ſutable to <hi>ſpiritual times,</hi> which I fear are prepared for theſe men; to be caſt into a Gulf, (though not of the <hi>earth</hi>) of <hi>error,</hi> which is worſe, to be given over <hi>to a reprobate mind,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong deluſions</hi> to believe lies. For I muſt needs obſerve, that they, ſo ſoon as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:114723:38"/> they fall to this <hi>trade</hi> of Preaching, they preſently <hi>vent</hi> moſt dangerous errors. Whence I conclude, that none dare preſume to preach unſent; but men of ſuch erroneous and <hi>desperate prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> theſe men are of; or elſe God <hi>puniſheth</hi> this their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſin, with <hi>delivering them up to ſuch ſtrong deluſions as they are in:</hi> which I am indeed inclined the rather to believe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch was the puniſhment of <hi>the Jewiſh Nation</hi> for the <hi>lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſinne:</hi> and what was <hi>that, but a killing the Prophets, and ſtoning them that were ſent unto them?</hi> A rejecting Chriſt in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the <hi>Gospel:</hi> And what was the <hi>judgement</hi> that fell upon them for this their ſinne? even that that hath remained as a Plague to their hearts; for above this ſixteen hundred year. And what was that? Read <hi>Romans</hi> 11. 8. and ſee how like it is, to that which theſe men, though <hi>paſt-feeling</hi> labour under: <hi>God hath</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>given them the ſpirit of ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; eyes that they ſhould not ſee; ears that they ſhould not hear. O heavy judgement, and ſo much the more, that it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath given them the <hi>ſpirit of ſlumber,</hi> and now I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not why they pretend <hi>to dream dreams:</hi> but alas! <hi>they ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> with their <hi>ſences lockt,</hi> their <hi>eyes are ſhut,</hi> their <hi>ears are ſtopt,</hi> they are in a maze, not knowing <hi>where</hi> nor <hi>how</hi> they <hi>are,</hi> nor what they would have, poſſeſt and troubled with the reſtleſs ſpirit of <hi>Giddy ſlumber:</hi> They ſtrongly perſwade themſelves and others, that their eyes are open, and <hi>they ſee ſuch</hi> things, as <hi>no men</hi> ſee, when alas! what they ſee, is but <hi>a viſion of the night,</hi> the work of <hi>inward phanſie</hi> only, and their <hi>eyes are ſhut</hi> all the while: and ſuch is their miſery, though men cry to them, and in their very ears, to awake and rouſe them out of their dream, their ears are <hi>heavy, they cannot hear,</hi> or they cannot hear (at leaſt) of that ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But may not any Preach that are able? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> There is a known diſtinction or two that may end the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie: 1. We muſt diſtinguiſh of the <hi>ſtate of the place</hi> wherein we are: If it be that we are caſt upon the <hi>Heathens, Turks,</hi> or the like, where there is no <hi>Church nor Miniſtry,</hi> there every man is bound to make known the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſo far as he may with prudence do: Or again, if Churches
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:114723:38"/> were not yet conſtituted, though the truth of the Goſpel was entertained by many; we may grant without danger, that then men without a formall ſending may exerciſe their gifts in ſuch a way as is not lawfull in a ſetled Church. But in ſuch a Church as ours is, that is already <hi>constitute,</hi> and hath within her a ſetled Miniſtry, for private men to preſume to Preach, is ſuch a notable ſin in the Scripture, that it is there condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from heaven, in as great a remarkable <hi>vengeance</hi> from God, in <hi>Corah's company,</hi> and the <hi>Nation of the Jews,</hi> as any we reade of. <hi>We therefore knowing the terrour of the Lord, perſwade our brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. We muſt in a ſetled Church diſtinguiſh of <hi>Preaching publiquely,</hi> and <hi>Teaching privately;</hi> the later, which conſiſts in private <hi>exhortation, reproof, comfort, counſel,</hi> and the like, every member in private conference ought to perform from a principle of love, for the edification of the <hi>whole body:</hi> but for the firſt particular of the diſtinction, the thing we are only upon, the <hi>publique preaching of the word,</hi> it being an act of <hi>Office,</hi> doth belong peculiarly to Church Officers, and may not be aſſumed by any other (let their parts and abilities be what they will) unleſs it be in order (as our Expectants) to ordination, and that by the <hi>leave</hi> and invitation of the <hi>Church</hi> wherein they are; I mean by publike preaching, a preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>declare</hi> the minde of God by expounding and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Scripture in the place of our Aſſemblies before the Church in the ſeat of the Miniſter or any other. For any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, or man uncall'd, to offer this, is great preſumption, condemn'd by the Scripture throughout, and nothing war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable with God or man.</p>
               <p>Two things I ſhould undertake here, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew you the ground of this diſtinction of publick Preaching and private teaching; and to clear and confirm my concluſion thereupon, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rutherford, Hall, Collings, Ferriby,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>though private teaching be the duty of all, yet publick Preaching is the ſin of any, but men in Office;</hi> which (having been done ſo fully by others, to whom I refer you) I ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch in a word.</p>
               <p>For the ground and reaſon of this clear diſtinction one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (of many) ſhall ſerve the turn: and it is of <hi>women,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:114723:39"/> whom we find in Scripture commended for <hi>private teaching,</hi> yet alſo forbidden there in <hi>publick Preaching,</hi> ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 26. There <hi>Aquilla and Priſcilla took Apollos unto them</hi> (it is ſaid) <hi>and expounded the word:</hi> Mark, <hi>they took him to them,</hi> aſide, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to private, and there the <hi>woman,</hi> as well as the <hi>man,</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the way of God unto <hi>Apollos.</hi> Well then, here is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a womans teaching in a private way; but doth this allow a womans <hi>publick Preaching?</hi> no alas; that's clearly <hi>forbidden in another text,</hi> which tels us, we muſt not <hi>ſuffer a woman to ſpeak in the Church;</hi> neither to the end ſhe may <hi>teach</hi> or <hi>learn.</hi> And as women are forbidden to ſpeak at all, ſo are men forbidden to <hi>preach in the Church</hi> without a call; <hi>For no man taketh this honour to himſelf, unleſſe he be called of God, as Aaron was:</hi> As if it had been ſaid, in the times of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel <note place="margin">Heb. 5. 4.</note> a call is as neceſſary to licence a Preacher, as it was in the time of the law: For <hi>how ſhall they Preach except they be ſent?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 15.</note> That is, none can perform the Office of a Preacher (as juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>How ſhall they hear without a Preacher?)</hi> unleſs he be ſent, that is, as we largely explained before, ordained according to the order of the Goſpel, by the power of the Church.</p>
               <p>Now, we never read of any in Scripture that were <hi>ſent</hi> to preach, but they were thereby <hi>put into Office:</hi> yea this <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> in the Text is expounded there, to be an exerciſe of one that <hi>is ſent</hi> and none other: and this <hi>[being ſent]</hi> doth expound it ſelfe, to make <hi>a Preacher,</hi> as in the laſt words of the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth <hi>verſe;</hi> and this word Preacher is never given to any in Scripture <hi>but to men in Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then thoſe that to preſume to preach muſt needs pretend to be ſent ſome way or other: and I know no other ſending but extraordinary or ordinary: now I wiſh our Adverſaries to take which they pleaſe. Are they ſent extraordinarily? That, though ſome of them have pleaded heretofore, they are all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, and do not now ſo much as pretend unto it: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is great blaſphemy. Neither doe they pretend to be ſent in an ordinary way, according to the nature of the word <hi>ſending,</hi> or the Rule of the Goſpel, as we have this day declared to you. How? and yet dare to preach? upon what account I beſeech you?</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:114723:39"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Object.</hi> There is a ſending of Duty as well as Office, ſaith one of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How many abſurdities are couch't together in theſe few words?</p>
               <p n="1">1. It would devide betwixt the <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which differ no more than Ghoſt and Spirit; the ſame thing in two words.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It would devide betwixt a mans <hi>being ſent by God,</hi> and <hi>put into Office</hi> by him; ſtill one and the ſame thing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is but the old diſtinction put into worſe and harder words; which is, That <hi>private Chriſtians may exerciſe their gifts in a way of love,</hi> in a private way: but there is <hi>a preaching in Office that onely is lawfull for men that are ſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. To ſpeak all in a word, this ſending in the very <hi>nature</hi> of the word, and <hi>ſence</hi> of Scripture doth plainly exclude what ever ſuch men pretend unto; to authorize their ſinful diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practice of publick preaching: even all the four things we nam'd before.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It excludes the ſecret <hi>impulſe of their</hi> own ſpirit: for no man that goes of his own accord, can be ſaid to be ſent; the one is <hi>Active,</hi> the other <hi>Paſſive:</hi> and this is confirm'd by that known Text, <hi>No man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron,</hi> clearly expreſſing that <hi>going</hi> and <hi>calling</hi> are two things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sending excludes the <hi>call of gifts alſo;</hi> for we not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that every man that is fit <hi>(eo ipſo)</hi> a Juſtice of Peace, <hi>abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> is one thing, <hi>commiſſion</hi> another: as moſt evidently appears by that clear Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 1, 5. In the firſt verſe they have their <hi>qualification,</hi> and in the fift they receive their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and are bid <hi>goe:</hi> and therefore examination or <hi>proving of gifts</hi> is but the <hi>way</hi> to <hi>Ordination:</hi> as in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> doth plainly appear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sending excludes <hi>Electing</hi> from the whole work: and therefore we finde <hi>ſending and electing</hi> two things, and even perform'd in a different way, and by different perſons, in <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 5, 6. The people choſe, and ſet the men before the Apoſtles, but they are not <hi>ſent yet,</hi> and therefore the Apoſtles <hi>lay hands upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:114723:40"/> 4. Sending is more than <hi>deſiring</hi> (laſtly) for this is but an act of an equal: but <hi>ſending</hi> is ever an act of <hi>Superiors. Deſiring</hi> doth leave the power in the partee <hi>deſir'd:</hi> but <hi>ſending</hi> implyes the power to be in the <hi>partee ſending. Deſiring</hi> doth not, while <hi>ſending</hi> doth ſtill put a man into Office: and a Miniſter <hi>in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial,</hi> giving him authority to deliver his Meſſage intruſted to him: <hi>for how ſhall he preach except he be ſent?</hi> That is, perform the Office of a Preacher, except he hath receiv'd a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> ſo to do, <hi>except he be ſent?</hi> Which I conclude with this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the ſum of this matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>None may preach except he be ſent: But Self-will, Gifts, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Deſire or Invitations of the people are not ſending. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that have no other Commiſſion then theſe four, may not preach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But though we have not the Doctrine of Scripture we have many <hi>examples</hi> of Scripture that favour our <hi>preaching.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 1. Suppoſe it, yet you muſt know theſe two things. 1. That <hi>Example</hi> will never warrant the practice of any, unleſſe all <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances</hi> of <hi>time, place, perſon, &amp;c.</hi> that are materiall, meet together: if thou beeſt not in all reſpects in the ſame condition, with that man thou lookſt at in Scripture, his action is no <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern</hi> to thee. 2. That <hi>Examples</hi> in Scripture are not further to be <hi>imitated</hi> by us, then they are <hi>agreeing</hi> with the <hi>Word</hi> of Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But ſecondly, as you have not one <hi>Word,</hi> ſo neither one <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> in the holy Scripture that will ſtand you in ſtead in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Did not <hi>Apollos</hi> preach? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> So may you in non-conſtituted Churches; eſpecially if you were known to be <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as he is <hi>called,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But did not <hi>Philip</hi> preach? </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> So may you, in the ſame ſtate of the Church, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ordained as <hi>Philip</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. and an <hi>Evangelist</hi> too, <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But did not the Perſecuted Saints goe <hi>Preaching the Word? Acts</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> So might you, if you were <hi>ſcattered by Perſecution</hi> among
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:114723:40"/> 
                  <hi>Heathen and Infidels</hi> as they were; though you can never prove that any of them preached even in Perſecution, but ſuch as were <hi>Officers;</hi> for which we have two Reaſons. Firſt, from the word there ſignifying preaching, which is as Doctor <hi>Seaman</hi> obſerves, never made uſe of in holy Scripture, but to expreſſe an act <hi>of Office</hi> and Officers: and indeed the very <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> word from whence this is immediately deriv'd, doth ſignifie the <hi>Gospel,</hi> or a <hi>good Meſſage,</hi> and is derived from another word, which ſignifies a Meſſenger, or one put <hi>into Office</hi> and ſent to declare this <hi>happy Meſſage</hi> to the ſons of men: inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating to us, that the word Goſpel doth <hi>carry a ſtrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Argument in it againſt all thoſe that offer to preach it, and are not ſent.</hi> Which indeed the Apoſtle ſeemeth to laugh at, as a plain contradiction, in the words before mentioned, <hi>How ſhall they preach, except they be ſent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But all might <hi>propheſie</hi> one by one, in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> why may not we?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> You may, when you are Prophers as they were: for that is a miſtake to think that all in the Church might propheſie: for certainly none could <hi>Propheſie</hi> but <hi>Prophets:</hi> And are all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? No ſurely: Therefore expound the 31 <hi>verſe</hi> with 29. and 32. and the matter is ended: <hi>All may propheſie;</hi> that is, <hi>All that are Prophets;</hi> let the <hi>Prophets ſpeak two or three,</hi> and let <hi>the other judge, and all thoſe that are Prophets may have time enough to ſpeak by turn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have now no more to urge, but that <hi>of Paul;</hi> whom we made before to appear to be a Miniſter, even as ſoon as he was made a Chriſtian (though not before, as ſome of you were) as you read <hi>Acts</hi> 26. 16.</p>
               <p>What now can you further urge for your ſelves? No more? O that the Lord would open your eyes, to ſee the Error and Danger of your wayes: Alas! What can I do more than to pray for you? and to him that is able to reſtore your ſouls, to him to commend you, with him to leave you? Yet with you I deſire to leave this advice, before I take leave, That though it ſeem a hard matter, yet <hi>you would</hi> take the Apoſtles Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,, and <hi>ſtudy to be quiet;</hi> henceforth doing no longer ours, but <hi>your own Buſineſſe;</hi> or elſe, if that be too hard, and you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:114723:41"/> will needs have the work that you would deſire, ſeek and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour (by giving up your ſelves to be prov'd and ordain'd) <hi>the Office of a Biſhop;</hi> and be aſſured by me, you ſhall find the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 1.</note> Miniſters very ready, upon the leaſt deſert, to afford unto you <hi>the right hand of fellowſhip.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. VI. <hi>That the People who leave the true Miniſters to follow ſuch as have no Calling, are guilty of a very great ſin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE are now attained to the laſt Concluſion, which is, That if for men to preach in a true Church, where there is a lawful Miniſtrie ſetled, be ſo great a ſinne; then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>for any to forſake a true Church and a lawfull Miniſterie, to follow and hear ſuch ſinfull Teachers, is a very great ſinne too;</hi> Though alas! poor ignorant deluded wretches think not ſo; they that offer thus to preach, are deeply guilty, as I have told you, this very action of theirs bringing ſo much diſorder with it, and coming from ſuch dangerous principles, endeavours the ſubverſion, and utter over-throw of all the Churches of Chriſt in the world, and Chargeth Apoſtacy upon all the Churches that have been in the world ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles: of ſo deep a nature is their ſinne; and you by following of them, do plainly become <hi>partakers of their ſinne;</hi> be it never ſo great or dangerous: and when Judgement comes, 'tis ſpeciall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, <hi>if the Congregation that joyned with them be ſpared,</hi> while Corah <hi>and his company are ſwallowed up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many, in a ſort, that are not <hi>approvers</hi> of the men and ways <note place="margin">Hearers are partakers of the ſin of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Preachers.</note> we now ſpeak of, are yet <hi>partakers of theſe mens</hi> ſinnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not what God requires and in them lies, to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> the ſame: But how much more are they that <hi>approve of,</hi> and <hi>joyn with</hi> them! as many hundreds of ignorant Creatures doe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, you are not partakers with them in their ſins onely
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:114723:41"/> hereby; but you directly ſinne your ſelves <hi>many wayes.</hi> I <note place="margin">Sin in hearing of them direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too.</note> cannot tell you how many ſinnes you commit in this one, of following theſe unſent Preachers, nor indeed how ſore <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> belong unto you for it. Sins of <hi>omiſſion,</hi> in that you neglect to attend on the <hi>publick Ordinances</hi> to which you are called: in that you ceaſe to own, reſpect and countenance the <hi>Over-ſeers</hi> Chriſt hath given you: of <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> in that you <hi>rent</hi> your ſelves by unlawfull Schiſm from the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, and his <hi>Miniſtry:</hi> in that you doe thereby what in you lies to break and ruine all the Churches and Miniſters of Chriſt <hi>in the world:</hi> in that you againſt expreſſe command, hear <hi>thoſe Prophets that God never ſent;</hi> and have, to conclude, a very great ſtroak in <hi>all theſe Confuſions, Errors and Hereſies, that now ſwarm within our Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider, O conſider, I beſeech you dearly beloved, and lay <hi>theſe things to heart:</hi> I perſwade my ſelf, that could you be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and patient in weighing theſe things a while, you would be at a ſtand, if not face about.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider, what good can you get (though you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe much) while you lie under that heavy curſe, <hi>They ſhall</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 23. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>not profit—you:</hi> That is, they doe you <hi>much hurt,</hi> and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall damage. And doe you not find it by daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Whom among you, but at his very entrance upon theſe wayes, hath the foundation of his whole Religion ſhaken im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately? I have wondred often at the frequent truth of this Obſervation, untill I conſidered this Text and Curſe, <hi>They ſhall not profit this people at all.</hi> Oh that you would conſider it alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider what good you may doe us too, by <hi>leaving them at laſt,</hi> and returning again <hi>to the Fold and Shepherds of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> For as your <hi>itching ears</hi> have heaped up ſuch a <hi>multitude of Teachers;</hi> ſo your eares well bored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain would throw them down as faſt. Alas! what doth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them but the pleaſant Aire of your Encouragement; would you withdraw, they fall immediately with ſhame and ſorrow: were there no <hi>Hearers, there would be no ſuch Teachers.</hi> For as we <hi>cannot hear without Preachers,</hi> ſo they <hi>will not preach without Hearers:</hi> and now will you not recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:114723:42"/> your former prejudice to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>your ſelves</hi> beſides, while ſo fair an advantage remains in your hands? However, if love cannot win and prevail, let the terror and fear of the Lord perſwade, whoſe ſtrict com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand I reade unto you, and leave upon you; Thus <hi>ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Hearken not unto the words of the Prophets that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 23. 16. with 21.</note> 
                  <hi>to you, they make you vain.</hi> And why? <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſied.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:114723:42"/>
            <head>A Brief Narration of the heads of that long (yet happy) Diſcourſe, betwixt M. <hi>Fullwood</hi> (aſſiſted ſometimes with M. <hi>Wood,</hi> M. <hi>Howe,</hi> &amp;c.) and M. <hi>Collier</hi> with the ſtrength of his party in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> upon <hi>May</hi> 4. 1652. at <hi>Wiviliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe,</hi> commonly known by the name of <hi>Wilſcome</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>M. <hi>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLWOOD,</hi> whoſe turn it was to preach there that day, having ended the Sermon, which precedes this <hi>Narrative:</hi> the <hi>Adverſo party</hi> flockt together as neer as they could to the Pulpit: and M. <hi>Collier</hi> in the Name of the reſt, declared himſelf unſatisfied touching what had been <hi>delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We deſired them to have a little more patience, and to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the <hi>ſtating</hi> of the queſtion, touching the Miniſtery, which M. <hi>How</hi> had on purpoſe provided for our Diſcourſe that day, <hi>in private:</hi> they replied again, that there was more matter in the <hi>Sermon</hi> delivered, then we ſhould be able to diſcuſſe that day: they would not yeeld to the motion of the ſtating the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but with a kinde of violent importunity urg'd, that the <hi>Miniſter</hi> that had <hi>preacht,</hi> would maintain his doctrine: to which at length we yeelded, and bid them object: having cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Moderators; M. <hi>Wood</hi> on ours, and a Captain on their part.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>M. <hi>Collier</hi> began to this purpoſe: I ſhall go through the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in order: the firſt point was; <hi>That openly ſcandalous and prophane perſons with true beleevers were not inconſistent with a true Church;</hi> but this I ſhall not meddle with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I thank you for that Sir, yet if you have any thing againſt it, I pray you ſay on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>No, I will let that paſſe; and come unto the ſecond, which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:114723:43"/> was, <hi>That the Churches of England are true Churches:</hi> which I have four things to except againſt; 1. That their <hi>conſtitution</hi> was falſe. 2. Their <hi>members</hi> are falſe. 3. Their <hi>Ordinances</hi> are falſe. 4. Their <hi>Miniſtery</hi> is falſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I deny them all: and firſt I deny our conſtitution to be falſe; and would have you prove it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>You were falſly conſtituted in Q. <hi>Eizabeths</hi> daies, for you were made true Churches by the <hi>civill power,</hi> the command of the Queen; and not by the Miniſtry of the Word, as you ſhould have been.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>That is denied: for we were not reclaim'd from Popery by the Queens command, without, but with the aſſiſtance of the <hi>godly Protestant Miniſtery</hi> (as Hiſtory makes to appear) and you cannot deny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>But did not the people turn for fear of the power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate? and I hope you will not ſay that the Cavaliers are good Subjects, and truly converted to the Parliament, becauſe they out of fear ſubſcribe the Engagement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>To ſay, that all did <hi>turn for fear</hi> is but a ſlander, and cannot be proved; but however I had thought you had ſpoken all the while of a <hi>viſible Church,</hi> do you require <hi>reall faith,</hi> to conſtitute a <hi>viſible Church?</hi> I ſay, that the outward ſubjection of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers is enough to make them <hi>viſible</hi> ſubjects; and the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> profeſſion of Chriſt, is enough to render men externall members of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Thomas Gorges</hi> a very worthy, godly, and learned Gentleman, and Juſtice of Peace in the County.</note> Beſides, the renoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Popery, and embracing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, was a voluntary act of the whole Land, in their Repreſentative the <hi>Parliament,</hi> that ſate in the firſt year of Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>M. <hi>Collier</hi> hearken to the Gentleman, he is a <hi>Stateſ-man,</hi> and knows what belongs to Hiſtory better then you or I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>But you ſhould have been conſtituted by the Miniſtery of the Word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I have told you <hi>we were:</hi> there were three <hi>ſpecial acts</hi> of grace ſeen in our converſion from Popery; the firſt was upon the heart of the Queen, inclining her Majeſty to propagate the true and Proteſtant Religion; the ſecond was, in inclining the people to be ſome what wrought on, by the command and influence of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:114723:43"/> good Queen; the laſt now was ſeen, in <hi>making effectuall</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the former, by the Proteſtant Miniſtry. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Several Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> before Q. <hi>Maries</hi> daies, fled in the time of perſecution, and returned in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> reign, and preaching all over <hi>England,</hi> reclaim'd the people from Popery.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>With this they ſeemed to acquieſce, urging their great obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction no more at all, which may hint unto us, that the moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſureſt way to foil ſuch adverſaries, is by dealing with them in their own <hi>principles;</hi> which was M. <hi>Fullwoods</hi> effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all courſe throughout: namely, to give them what they deſire (by way of <hi>medium</hi>) and then to wreſt the <hi>weapon</hi> out of their hand, or to ſoil them in their own play: thus it was here, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (as they would, though they can never prove) that our Churches were conſtituted in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time (who were indeed reclaimed then, but conſtituted Centuries of years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and that there was no other means to bring a people to outward profeſſion (which fouly croſſeth their own principles, as appeareth afterwards:) or that the Civill Magiſtrate is to have no hand in the reformation of a Church, which though ſuppoſed may not be granted: or that, to conclude, that we cannot be a true Church unleſſe we know the means and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of its conſtitution, which is indeed abſurd: if the eſſentiall marks of a true Church can be demonſtrated; as was in our Churches in the morning: Yet with all theſe (one of which they cannot poſſibly maintain) they could not wield their objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the very <hi>medium</hi> it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> that we were not converted or reclaim'd by the Miniſtery of the Word, being flatly falſe.</p>
            <p>Then they broke off ſomewhat abruptly from this to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm; and being there was nothing objected by any of them afterwards, againſt the two next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; (Our <hi>Members</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi>) we ſuppoſe their Diſcourſe of Infant-Baptiſm was in ſtead of them.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>Infant-Baptiſm is unlawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould we ſtep ſo large? What is Infant-Baptiſm to the buſineſſe in hand? however take your liberty, and prove Infant-Baptiſm if you can to be unlawfull, as you ſay it is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>That that hath neither <hi>precept</hi> nor <hi>preſident</hi> in the word is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, but Infant-Baptiſm hath neither, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I deny both your Propoſitions; For the firſt, I ſay, it is not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:114723:44"/> unlawfull to go to <hi>Taunton,</hi> and yet you cannot ſhew me a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or preſident</hi> in the Word for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hadridge.</speaker>
               <p>But M. <hi>Fullwood</hi> do not you know we ſpeak of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>However M. <hi>Hadridge</hi> the Propoſition is falſe, and deſerves correction: But (to come as near as you would have me) I pray tell me what you mean by Precept here, whether an expreſſe command, or ſuch a command as fals from the Word by <hi>juſt conſequence;</hi> if you require an expreſſe command in ſo many words, (though I grant that requiſite to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, as this of Baptiſm, yet) this is not <hi>abſolutely requiſite</hi> for every <hi>circumſtance</hi> that belongs to an Ordinance; not to the circumſtance of time, when the children of profeſſors ſhould be baptized; whether in <hi>Infancy</hi> or <hi>riper years,</hi> when we can prove it by <hi>juſt conſequence;</hi> for though the Ordinance of inclination be changed, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> into <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> yet that the <hi>time of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration</hi> is changed, you can never prove: ſo that then, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your propoſition be <hi>touching Ordinances,</hi> it being onely touching a <hi>circumſtance</hi> and not the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of an Ordinance, 'tis falſe ſtill. <hi>Nothing of anſwer was made to this Reply;</hi> but M. <hi>Collier</hi> went from this to prove the <hi>minor,</hi> viz. <hi>That Infants had no command to be baptized.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>There's no command for baptizing <hi>Infants,</hi> for <hi>beleevers</hi> are commanded to be baptized.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>This doth not <hi>conclude</hi> at all: for though beleevers are, yet it doth not follow, That none but beleevers are to be <hi>baptized,</hi> which you are to prove: We ſay, <hi>actuall beleevers</hi> not yet bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, <hi>are to be baptized;</hi> but we ſay alſo, that they and <hi>their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> are to be baptized; it behooves you, if you can to produce a command, wherein beleevers onely are commanded to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>The Text ſaith, <hi>He that beleeveth and is baptized, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! this is no command at all, but a <hi>Propoſition</hi> only: much leſſe that beleevers only are to be baptized; and the truth is the force of this Propoſition is onely this, That none but beleevers ſhall be ſaved, not baptized, or rather, thoſe that beleeve, as well as receive the Ordinance of baptiſm, ſhall aſſuredly be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:114723:44"/> but as this excludes not children from <hi>ſalvation,</hi> ſo neither from baptiſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>But we pray you then, if there be a command for <hi>baptizing of Infants,</hi> ſhew it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>This is indeed ſomewhat unreaſonable M. <hi>Collier;</hi> eſpecially conſidering how <hi>weary</hi> you may eaſily imagine me to be, who preacht, and ſince that <hi>diſputed</hi> ſo long with you; however give me leave for a little reſpite to chooſe a ſecond, that may ſtead me a while, and you ſhall have what liberty you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>We agree, chooſe whom you will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I chooſe my <hi>Moderator,</hi> I pray you M. <hi>Wood</hi> give them a command for Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>Chooſe you now, whether you will oppoſe or defend M. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> 'tis an indifferent thing to me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I deſire you will ſhew us a command for Infant-baptiſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>You may reade a command for Infant-baptiſm, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. whence I argue thus.</p>
               <p>Where we finde a generall command in the Word, we may not reſtrain or limit the ſame without warrant from the Word.</p>
               <p>But here we have a generall command, <hi>Baptize all Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore we may not reſtrain or limit it to beleevers onely, without we can ſhew a warrant from the Word ſo to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis reſtrain'd to Diſciples: for in the Greek, it is <hi>diſciple</hi> all Nations, baptizing them: firſt they muſt be made <hi>diſciples,</hi> and then <hi>baptized.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>You cannot conclude from the order of words in Scripture: for in <hi>Mark</hi> 'tis ſaid <hi>baptize and teach;</hi> whence we may argue as well, that we muſt baptize before we teach. 2. I am very glad that you ſo tranſlat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the words; for <hi>children are capable of being diſcipled,</hi> and <hi>therefore baptiz'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>Children have no right at all to <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>That I ſhall prove unto you thus, Thoſe to whom <hi>the spirit of grace,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and <hi>the bleſſing of Chriſt</hi> belongs; to thoſe the Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> belongs; but to <hi>ſome children;</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:114723:45"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſpirit of grace, the kingdom of God, and the bleſſing of Chriſt belongs: therefore to them belongs the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col,</speaker>
               <p>I deny your <hi>minor.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woad.</speaker>
               <p>For the firſt, <hi>John was ſanctified from the womb.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>That is, he was ſeparated to an Office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>No, for we reade of an inward work of the ſpirit, <hi>the childe leaped for joy in the womb;</hi> but the two other are more clearly proved in that known Text: Chriſt took <hi>little children into his arms, and bleſſed them, and ſaid, for of ſuch is the Kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Facy.</speaker>
               <p>That was meant of men like <hi>Children,</hi> in harmleſneſſe, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>How, good Sir, do we think that they <hi>brought men</hi> to Chriſt in their <hi>arms?</hi> or that Chriſt took <hi>men into his arms, and bleſſed them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. If our Saviour ſhould urge them to ſuffer little children to come to him, becauſe <hi>of ſuch is the kingdom of Heaven,</hi> and yet mean by <hi>ſuch</hi> here, <hi>men like to children,</hi> the reaſon here were very improper, and would no way anſwer the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>But what is this to Infant-baptiſm all this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! I bring not this to prove the baptizing of Infants <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly;</hi> but to prove the <hi>minor</hi> denied, <hi>viz.</hi> That Children are part of the Kingdom of God, and by <hi>conſequence</hi> onely, that they may be baptized.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Here they ſtuck untill they found out a way to get themſelves out of the mire, by deſiring to return to M. <hi>Fullwood</hi> again, who they pleaded had had ſome reſpite, which was accordingly yeelded unto.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>You cry out for a <hi>Command for Infants-baptiſm,</hi> I will give you two.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſhall be the ſame, my brother begun with, <hi>otherwiſe applied,</hi> it is <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Go diſciple</hi> (as you intepret well) <hi>all Nations baptizing them:</hi> Here is a cleer and expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:114723:45"/> to baptize all ſuch as are made <hi>Diſciples:</hi> according to your own interpretation of the place; but now children of profeſſors are diſciples (<hi>de jure</hi> before, <hi>de facto</hi> by baptiſm;) therefore here is a clear and expreſs command for <hi>baptizing the children of Profeſſors.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>I deny that children are diſcipled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe that are <hi>members</hi> of the viſible Church are <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples:</hi> but children of profeſſors are <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church:</hi> therefore children of profeſſors are diſciples.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>I deny, that children of <hi>profeſſors</hi> are <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>If children of profeſſors had the <hi>priviledge of being Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members once;</hi> and that priviledge was <hi>never taken away from them,</hi> they have it ſtill; but children of profeſſors had this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of being Church-members once, and it was never yet taken away from them, therefore they have it ſtill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>That priviledge of there's is repealed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>If this priviledge of <hi>children</hi> be repealed by <hi>God,</hi> it muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed either <hi>in the Old or New Teſtament,</hi> but it was never repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Old or new Teſtament; therfore it is not repealed yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis repealed in the New Teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>If ſo; It is repealed in the four Evangeliſts, <hi>Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, Epiſtles,</hi> or the <hi>Revelation;</hi> but in none of theſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>It is repealed in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>Now to Abraham and his ſeed are the promiſes made; he ſaith not, and to ſeeds, as of many, but as of one, and to thy ſeed, that is Christ:</hi> Now therefore all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are reſolv'd and center'd in Chriſt, and we have none but what we have from his hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, that all the promiſes are reſolv'd and center'd in Chriſt, but that is, in Chriſt conſidered <hi>in Aggregato,</hi> that is, Chriſt conſiſting of <hi>head and members,</hi> and which cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, becauſe elſe, all the Covenant of grace and promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Compare the Text with 1 Cor. 12. 12.</note> centered in the pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon of Chriſt, as you would urge, there ſhould be none le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>for the body of Chriſt, in the daies of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel,</hi> Now conſider, what can you gain by this Text? the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is, that the former Covenant of grace, and promiſes made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> are all centred in Chriſt; that is, in Chriſt, both head and members, in the daies of the Goſpel, as is better expla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:114723:46"/> by the 14. <hi>ver.</hi> of the ſame Chapter; the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> is come upon the Gentiles through Chriſt Jeſus: that is, the promiſes and priviledges of our Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>typicall</hi> head of the Jewiſh Church, is come upon the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>myſtical</hi> head of the <hi>Gentile Church;</hi> and were not the promiſes made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed? and did not the priviledge of being <hi>Church-members,</hi> belong to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his ſeed? and therefore the ſame promiſes and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges belong to profeſſors of the Gentiles and <hi>their ſeed</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>Again, were this Text for you at all, it would onely ſerve to prove, that Chriſts <hi>spirituall ſeed</hi> have the priviledge of being <hi>Church-members</hi> alone: the contrary we have proved in the Sermon above, ſhewing you that not only hypocrites but ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons were <hi>members of the Church of God at Corinth,</hi> againſt which you have nothing to ſay, they being members of the viſible Church, are members of the <hi>viſible</hi> body of Chriſt, and by conſequence have viſible intereſt in the promiſes and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, which you ſay are centred in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I deſire you M. <hi>Collier</hi> to ſhew us a better Text then this, therefore, for the <hi>repealing of Infants Church-memberſhip.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>But this is clear'd by the laſt verſe of the ſame Chapter; if ye be Chriſts, then are ye <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, and heirs according to the promiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>This text is clearer againſt you then the former was: what doth it ſay? it ſaith, that the Gentiles by becoming <hi>Chriſts</hi> or <hi>Christians,</hi> they <hi>become thereby Abrahams ſeed,</hi> that is, by being united to Chriſt <hi>really,</hi> they become <hi>Abrahams reall</hi> ſeed: and by being <hi>united</hi> to Chriſt <hi>viſibly,</hi> we become <hi>Abrahams viſible</hi> ſeed, and then accordingly we are intereſted in the promiſes and priviledges of <hi>Abraham, being heirs according to the promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hadridge.</speaker>
               <p>There is <hi>now neither Jew nor Gentile, bond nor free, male nor female: for ye are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>I thank you for that M. <hi>Hadridge,</hi> a moſt clear Text to prove the partition wall is broken down betwixt the Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and that the Gentile Churches being now made one with the Jewiſh (not as Jewiſh, but as a Church) have a right to all the priviledges of the Jewiſh Church: and among the reſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>to Church-memberſhip for themſelves and children:</hi> if you
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:114723:46"/> have ever a better Text, I pray produce it, for theſe will not doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>I pray then conſider <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28, 29. <hi>He is not a Jew that is one outwardly, neither is that circumciſion, which is outwardly in the fleſh, but he is a Jew which is one inwardly,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Alas this cannot be ſtrictly and properly underſtood, but by way of Compariſon; for a man cannot be a <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>not</hi> a <hi>Jew:</hi> that would be harſh: the meaning is, that he is not a <hi>Jew in Gods account;</hi> that is, ſuch a one as ſhall <hi>have</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>praiſe of God,</hi> that is onely a member <hi>of the viſible Church:</hi> God looks chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>heart:</hi> or rather the Apoſtle is aboliſhing <hi>the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of Circumciſion, and winding up their hearts to the truth of it, <hi>Circumciſion that is of the heart:</hi> not that <hi>in the dayes of the Goſpel</hi> God doth ſo much regard the <hi>heart,</hi> as that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed no outward Ordinances, no viſible Church, nor viſible worſhip; or not members of the viſible Church: but <hi>ſuch as are Circumciſed in heart:</hi> None of which you will offer to ſay; and yet the Text taken your way, offers to prove nothing elſe, which I pray you conſider. But you muſt look for another Text: this onely ſhewes that Circumciſion it ſelf is aboliſh't, but the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Circumciſion, that abides, as commanded <hi>upon Abraham and his ſeed,</hi> both of <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> for ever, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>But that <hi>Covenant</hi> was <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> ver. 10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Give the holy Ghoſt leave to interpret his own words; and we read verſe 11. That Circumciſion was onely a <hi>token</hi> of the Covenant: and though that <hi>ſign</hi> is vaniſht, the <hi>thing</hi> remains: unleſſe you will make the ſubſtance of the Covenant in the time of the Law one thing, and in the time of the <hi>Gospel</hi> another thing: and ſo make two Covenants of Grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I will not meddle with that now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>But you muſt give us another Text, or elſe, we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>That Children of Profeſſors have the priviledge of being Church-members ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hadridge.</speaker>
               <p>Matth. 3. <hi>Think not to ſay with your ſelves, We have Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham to our Father; the Ax is laid to the root of the Tree; which hath cut down all former priviledges.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:114723:47"/>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Alas, have not all the other Scriptures, which your ſelves have brought, proved that we have <hi>Abraham to our Father ſtil?</hi> and that we have no Promiſes or Priviledges at all, but <hi>as</hi> we are <hi>Abrahams ſeed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Had.</speaker>
               <p>But we muſt doe the <hi>works of Abraham,</hi> that we may become <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>True; but as doing the works of <hi>Abraham indeed,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his <hi>reall</hi> ſeed, and have a reall right unto his priviledges: ſo by doing the works of <hi>Abraham in ſhew onely,</hi> we become his ſeed <hi>in ſhew.</hi> Which though it will not ſatisfie God, who looks to the heart, yet it gives them a title to <hi>outward</hi> privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, from the hands of men, <hi>who judge according to appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:</hi> The meaning of the place, with the extent of it, is plainly this; That God requires more exactneſſe and ſtrictneſs in theſe dayes of the Goſpel, then he did in the times of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance under the Law: not that the Goſpel can any way poſſible deprive the Church of any Priviledge, which <hi>made Grace to abound, and not to diminiſh in this regard;</hi> and therefore not this priviledge of <hi>having our Children Church-members with us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>It is a <hi>Priviledge</hi> that our children are <hi>not Baptized;</hi> and that in many reſpects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>What are they I pray you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col,</speaker>
               <p n="1">1. It is a priviledge for our Children to be in that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>that God would have them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Again, Becauſe when your Children are once Baptized, you make it ſerve to make them <hi>ſecure,</hi> telling them that now they are in a happy condition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Here are two priviledges for our Children not to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. But to the firſt, I ſay, is it not a goodly priviledge for the <hi>Damned Devils</hi> to be in <hi>Hell?</hi> yet that is the Condition God will have them in.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>ſecond,</hi> 'tis a meer <hi>ſlander:</hi> for as we beleeve, ſo we <hi>tell</hi> our Children, that they are <hi>obliged</hi> by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> to ſerve <hi>God,</hi> own <hi>Chriſt,</hi> forſake the <hi>World,</hi> reſiſt the <hi>Devil,</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their <hi>fleſh</hi> the more; which if they neglect, <hi>their</hi> condition is worſe than the very <hi>Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have made good the firſt command of <hi>Matthew</hi> 28. 19.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:114723:47"/>
               <p> We ſhall now proceed to the other; which you have in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38, 39. <hi>Repent and be baptized every one of you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the promiſe is to you, and to your Children, &amp;c.</hi> Whence I argue:</p>
               <p>The <hi>command</hi> of the <hi>Sign,</hi> is as large as the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of the thing <hi>ſignified;</hi> but <hi>the promiſe is to you and your children:</hi> therefore the command of Baptiſm reacheth to you and your children too, upon your repentance: as to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he himſelf believed, God commands him to be <hi>circumciſed</hi> himſelf and his <hi>Children:</hi> So here, when you repent, both you and your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are taken into Covenant, and you are commanded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Baptiſm</hi> for your ſelves and <hi>Children. Repent ye</hi> parents, and <hi>be baptized</hi> every one of you, both Parents and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> (who have call'd for Judgement upon your ſelves and Children) for the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> notwithſtanding, is <hi>to you,</hi> and to your <hi>Children.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>But this promiſe here is a promiſe of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>And of the forgiveneſſe of ſins too, <hi>ver.</hi> 38.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>But that promiſe however is a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> promiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Yet the <hi>promiſe</hi> which is ſaid to be, to <hi>you and your Children</hi> there, is more then <hi>Spirituall:</hi> indeed, it is onely ſpiritually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed at this time: and why? Becauſe thoſe to whom it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed are at this time onely ſpiritually wounded, <hi>pricked to the hears:</hi> yet the promiſe here, is indeed the Covenant which hath both <hi>temporall and ſpirituall</hi> promiſes; which is very evident, if we turn to the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Joel;</hi> out of which the Text is taken: which Chapter is almoſt made up of temporal and ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as if it were an Expoſition of the Covenant. Which Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was openly <hi>read,</hi> and found to be <hi>ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So this command was ended too: for they being urged to ſay what they could for themſelves, they refuſed to ſay any more, but would leave what had been ſaid to the judgement of the people; we being ſomewhat imboldened by their parties ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>referr'd it to the people,</hi> as they deſired; and asked them whether they were not ſatisfied with what had been ſaid for in-Infant Baptiſm? In Anſwer to which, ſeverall perſons cryed out, They were; and not one of their partie ſaid any thing to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:114723:48"/> the contrarie; but one who call'd to the people, and asked them, <hi>Why they would ſay they were ſatisfied, when they were not:</hi> Hereupon, as we remember, Maſter <hi>Hadridg</hi> ſtood up and asked theſe two Sophiſticall queſtions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Had.</speaker>
               <p>I have three Children, which were never ſprinkled, and I would fain know what Command I have omitted: I my ſelf have been dipt; and I would fain know what Command I have broken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>As for your own being Dipt or <hi>Rebaptiz</hi>'d, you have broke the Command: that is eaſily inferr'd from the words of <note place="margin">Suppoſe I ſhould ſay, I have two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that have been both of them ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand have I broken? And for my own part I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Dipt or Baptizd again, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand have omitted? What Anſwer can you make?</note> the Apoſtle, there <hi>is but one Baptiſm;</hi> for you have had two. And for the neglecting the baptizing of your Children, you have plainly omitted the commands that have been preſt for Infant Baptiſm, which ſtand as yet unſhaken, notwithſtanding what hath been moved againſt them.</p>
               <p>Now we have given you theſe Commands; we ſhall ſhew you example alſo; which hath a probable Argument in it, that Children were baptized by the Apoſtles: It was, That we have many examples of whole houſes that were Baptized; and ſurely thoſe times were very barren, if there ſhould happen to be ſo many houſholds without <hi>one</hi> child: and if it be <hi>probable,</hi> that there was but <hi>one</hi> Child, in all theſe Houſes, as it is a very <hi>probable</hi> Argument for Infant Baptiſm, ſince the whole houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds (where ever they came) were Baptized, with the chief of their houſes, none ever excepted againſt, or rejected. <hi>There was ſome jangling about ſome particular houſes, but nothing of moment ſaid to the Argument.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then ſome indigeſted Objections were made againſt <hi>Sprinkling.</hi> The ſum of the Anſwer to them, was,
<list>
                  <item>1. We do not exclude either <hi>Dipping</hi> or <hi>Sprinkling,</hi> though we conceive that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is rather a <hi>waſhing,</hi> then either Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or Sprinkling,</item>
                  <item>2. 'Tis out of Charitie, (as well as judgement) that we doe not <hi>Dip</hi> Infants; and we have Scripture-warrant for it; <hi>I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſignifieth <hi>Sprinkling</hi> or <hi>Waſhing,</hi> as
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:114723:48"/> well as <hi>Dipping:</hi> they <hi>Baptized Beds,</hi> and <hi>Cups</hi> and <hi>Tables,</hi> &amp;c. And when Beds and Tables were <hi>Ceremoniouſly</hi> waſh'd, or Baptiz'd; no man will ſay they Dipt them under Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
               </list> The Adverſaries unwilling to ſay any more againſt Infant-Baptiſm, were urg'd to return to their firſt Diſcourſe, touching the <hi>Churches;</hi> and ſay what they could againſt our <hi>Miniſterie,</hi> the thing mainly intended: to which they agree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but Maſter <hi>Fullwood</hi> being over-wearie deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red reſpit: it was urged that Maſter <hi>How,</hi> who had ſufficiently provided for it, whoſe exerciſe was gladly and thankfully read and tranſcribed by ſeveral Godly Miniſters about us, might ſtate the Queſtion, <hi>touching the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie;</hi> which was, Whether <hi>the preſent Miniſterie of the Churches now in England, be the true Miniſterie of Jeſus Christ exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively.</hi> Which they refuſed, pretending that would be too long; but gave way, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>How</hi> might bring an Argument or two for the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> for which he engaged, and performed as followeth.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe that are Inſtruments in the hands of Chriſt for the work of Converſion, are the Miniſters of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 9. 2. But the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> are Inſtruments in the <hi>hands of Chriſt,</hi> for the <hi>work of Converſion,</hi> Rom. 10. 11. <hi>Ergo.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, Thoſe that come in <hi>at the door of the Sheepfold,</hi> are the true Shepheards. But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> came in at the door of the Sheepfold; therefore they are true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>I deny the Minor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe that come in <hi>after the mind of Chriſt,</hi> come in at the door of the ſheepfold. But we come in after the mind of Chriſt; therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:114723:49"/>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I deny the Minor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe that come in an <hi>Apoſtolicall way,</hi> come in after the minde of Chriſt; but ſo we come in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I deny the Minor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe whoſe <hi>ſubſtantialls</hi> in point of Call, were ſuch as the Apoſtles acted by <hi>in point of Ordination,</hi> came in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick way. But it was ſo with us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I deny the Minor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>Four things onely are required in Scripture ſo far as I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd, to make a compleat <hi>Apoſtolicall Ordination.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> for Abilities, 2 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2. 3. Secondly, The <hi>Savour</hi> of good report from the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 2. Thirdly, a time of <hi>ſeeking</hi> to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. Fourthly, <hi>Impoſition</hi> of hands, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>You fail in the <hi>End.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>How.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perſonall</hi> failings do not multiply the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the Act. And I pray you give me a better Anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>You want a lawfull Authority, if you have all thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. And beſides, you are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe you <hi>doe not doe the work of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Maſter</hi> Fulwood <hi>ſtep'd up and ſaid.</hi>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>How,</hi> I confeſſe I ſhall doe you an unkindneſſe; however be pleaſed to let me ſpeak with Maſter <hi>Collier</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. Maſter <hi>How,</hi> having received no ſatisfactory Anſwer, gladly gave leave.</p>
               <p>With your leave Maſter <hi>Collier;</hi> If I do not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Argument of yours prove our Miniſterie to be of Chriſt, I'le be Baptized by you to Morrow. Thus; <hi>Thoſe that doe the work of Chriſt, they are the Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi> But the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtesr of <hi>England</hi> doe the work of Chriſt; therefore they are the Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As for the Major, your own Argument grants that; and for the Minor, <hi>viz. That the Miniſters of England doe the work, of Christ</hi> is eaſily proved, if we conſider what the work of the Miniſtery of Chriſt is; namely, to <hi>beget</hi> and <hi>increaſe</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:114723:49"/> Faith; to <hi>Convert</hi> and <hi>Edifie,</hi> as <hi>Romans</hi> 10. 14. <hi>Epheſians</hi> 41. 2. Which none can well <hi>deny</hi> the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> to doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>Men may be converted many other wayes then by the Preaching of the word: The <hi>Woman of Samaria</hi> brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull.</speaker>
               <p>You can never prove, that any perſon was truly Conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by that <hi>Womans Diſcourſe:</hi> Indeed ſhe prevailed upon them for a faint <hi>Hiſtoricall</hi> faith, not a true <hi>juſtifying</hi> Faith: for none can imagine, that their faith exceeded the womans report.</p>
               <p>Again, the Caſe is <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and no man can argue from thence to an <hi>ordinarie</hi> caſe. We ſay that Converſion is not ordinarily wrought but by the ſent ordained Miniſtery; which that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14, 15. doth maintain for ever, without any colourable contradiction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I, but your Ordination came by <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>That Objection I fully anſwered (I thought) in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was a <hi>true</hi> Church, till the <hi>Councel of Trent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe it; you cannot deny it: though the <hi>ſtreſſe</hi> of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer lay not there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>How could <hi>Luther</hi> without blame, leave a true Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>Though the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was a true Church when <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> came off, yet ſhe was a Church very corrupt. Firſt, in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> in which he could not joyn, but hee muſt partake of her <hi>ſins.</hi> Secondly, in <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> if he would not embrace her corruptions, he muſt venture his <hi>life</hi> to ſtay there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coll.</speaker>
               <p>Could <hi>Rome</hi> be a true Church, and yet offer to kill ſo good a man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Full.</speaker>
               <p>As well as the <hi>People of the Jewes,</hi> when they would Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>But were the <hi>Jewes</hi> a True Church, till Chriſt his <hi>Death?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, elſe there had been no true Church in the world
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114723:50"/> at that time, which is an Article of our Creed, wherein we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the <hi>univerſal</hi> Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>True.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wood.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee you can ſay nothing againſt our Call: I pray Maſter <hi>Collier</hi> now prove your own Call.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I grant that none may preach, but <hi>ſuch as are ſent;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I believe that many are <hi>ſent</hi> to Preach that are not in <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you look over the Scripture, and ſee whether you can find one Text for that, Maſter <hi>Collier.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>The Prophets were not in <hi>Office</hi> in the time of the Law, yet <hi>preacht.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>The Prophets were in Office: the word <hi>Prophet</hi> is a name of <hi>Office,</hi> though <hi>extraordinary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>But <hi>Paul</hi> preacht before he was called.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo; he preacht indeed before he received an <hi>Ordinary</hi> Call, but not before he had an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Call: for Chriſt, when he came to call him to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> he made him a <hi>Miniſter;</hi> as is plainly expreſſed by <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>They anſwered no more; and indeed it was now late: we did mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ually congratulate the happy meeting and diſcourſe of the day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Col.</speaker>
               <p>I bleſſe God, that we have met with ſo moderate a man as you Maſter <hi>Fulwood.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Truely, I did not expect to finde a man ſo ſober and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall among you, as you have been Maſter <hi>Collier.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Barb.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Fulwood,</hi> I profeſſe ſeriouſly in the preſence of God, and all his people, that I love you as well as the deareſt friend I have in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>I thank you heartily Maſter <hi>Barber:</hi> but, truely, Maſter <hi>Templer</hi> I thought not to finde ſuch <hi>incivilities</hi> from your hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Templ.</speaker>
               <p>Truely Maſter <hi>Fulwood,</hi> I little thought to have heard you diſpute ſo well, when I heard your Sermon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! then I preacht; and now I diſpute.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:114723:50"/>
            <p> There were kinde Salutes on both parts, and a fair end. Onely ſome were urgent when we were parting, that they would prove their <hi>re-baptizing;</hi> For which they brought, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. To which Maſter <hi>Wood</hi> gave <hi>ſeveral</hi> Anſwers, and nothing of moment was replyed. So the Company parted.</p>
            <p>This we publiſh as a true, though ſhort, ſum of that large Diſpute.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Miniſters, &amp; Witneſſes.</head>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> How.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wood.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Bindon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wakely.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ball.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Darby.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:114723:51"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>THeſe new Books following are Printed and ſold by <hi>W. Roybould</hi> at the Unicorn in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttle North-Door.</p>
            <p>THe Holy Arbour; containing a Body of Divinity; or the Sum and Subſtance of Chriſtian Religion, in <hi>Folio.</hi> By <hi>John Godolphin,</hi> J. C. D. 1651.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Perſecution, from the beginning of their Converſion to Chriſtianity, to theſe times, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Ladies Vindication, or the Praiſe of worthy women in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1651.</p>
            <p>A further Diſcovery of the Myſtery of the laſt times, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1651.</p>
            <p>The Life and Reign of King <hi>Charles,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1651.</p>
            <p>The Antiquity of Common-wealths, inſtanced by that of <hi>Holland,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1652.</p>
            <p>Church-caſes cleared with a Pacificatory Preface to reconcile the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the Presbyterians, Independents, and Anabaptiſts: by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>N. Homes,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1652.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1650. before the L. Mayor, &amp;c. By D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Homes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miſchief of mixt Communions, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. By D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Homes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Plea for the Miniſtrie in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>VV. Wickins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1651. By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Jenkins,</hi> being the firſt he preach'd after his Releaſement.</p>
            <p>The Lawfull Preacher. Or, A Diſcourſe, proving that they only ought to preach that are ordained Miniſters. Alſo, The Pulpit-Guard Relieved, in Anſwer to <hi>Colliers</hi> Pulpit-Guard Routed, By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Ferriby,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1652.</p>
            <p>The Ordering and Setling of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi> 1652.</p>
            <p>Chriſt alone exalted, in 17 Sermons, by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Criſp,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Aſſertion of Grace, by <hi>R. Town,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>Taunton,</hi> by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Newton, May</hi> 12. 1652.</p>
            <p>Poems with Additions. Alſo, The Muſes Looking-glaſſe. <hi>Amyntas.</hi> Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Lovers; and <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> the jovial Philoſopher. By <hi>Tho. Randolph, M. A.</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1652.</p>
            <p>The Life of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Marriot</hi> the great Eater in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. With all his merry Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Travails.</p>
            <p>A Cat may look upon a King. Or, A Character of the Lives and Actions of all the Kings, from <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour to King <hi>Charles,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
